<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Tom Lee - DC, misc</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/feeds/dc-misc.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>https://tomlee.wtf/</id><updated>2008-04-24T11:36:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>grocerynomics</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/04/24/grocerynomics/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-04-24T11:36:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-04-24T11:36:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-04-24:/2008/04/24/grocerynomics/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://remakingleslumhistorique.blogspot.com/2008/04/thinking-about-teeter-effect.html"&gt;RenewShaw&lt;/a&gt; (with apologies for quoting the full entry):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;As a North Carolinian, I took for granted Harris Teeter grocery stores: they're clean, well-stocked (fresh, beautiful fruits and veggies, awesome delis, great meat departments, outstanding wine/beer departments, a variety of all the essentials and more), well-staffed, and generally pleasant …&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://remakingleslumhistorique.blogspot.com/2008/04/thinking-about-teeter-effect.html"&gt;RenewShaw&lt;/a&gt; (with apologies for quoting the full entry):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;As a North Carolinian, I took for granted Harris Teeter grocery stores: they're clean, well-stocked (fresh, beautiful fruits and veggies, awesome delis, great meat departments, outstanding wine/beer departments, a variety of all the essentials and more), well-staffed, and generally pleasant shopping experiences. Since moving to D.C., I have relished the few opportunities I've had to grocery shop at Teets out in Virginia.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;As reported elsewhere, the District's first HT finally opened today yesterday in Adams Morgan. Boo-yah. Another one is set to open on the Hill soon, and yet another is planned for NoMa. I don't know if any of these Tajma Teeters will ever be a routine grocery stop for me, but it's exciting to have them in the city, and hopefully they will inspire other grocers (Safeway and Giant) to take a hard look at how they do business.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;That said, I've had positive experiences at the Shaw Giant lately. While the store has some definite shortcomings due to its limited space (e.g., the produce department is woefully lacking, the place is generally unattractive and uninviting), I've not encountered lines stretching to the back of the store lately and have generally experienced helpful people at the checkouts.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All true! I live right by that Giant, and over the last year or two it really has improved: the staff is better trained, they've introduced some yuppie-compatible brands (look, an organic section!), and the produce is at least &lt;em&gt;less&lt;/em&gt; rotten.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it's a mistake, albeit an easy one, to assume that every store in a chain is the same. Of the proletarian grocery companies I've encountered, Giant has had both the nicest and worst stores. I've been to Safeways that look like fallout shelters, and others that are gleaming temples built for the greater glory of the deli counter. So far Harris Teeters seem to be consistently nice, but they're a relatively new player on the DC grocery scene. Wait twenty years, or head back to the region where they were founded. You'll find some atrocities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, this isn't to excuse the people responsible for the Shaw Giant. Actually, it makes them &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; culpable, because their crappy offerings are the result of deliberate inattention rather than simple incompetence. Grocery stores, like a lot of businesses, work like engines that the central office can rev up or rev down as economic circumstances dictate. I'm sure that Giant HQ noticed the percentage of WIC and EBT sales declining as I and my gentrifying ilk moved into the neighborhood. The better food and better-trained staff followed in due course.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So as long as the customers going to the new Harris Teeter are relatively rich, the store will be nice. As long as the ones shopping at the Shaw Giant are relatively poor, the store will be lousy. It's as simple as that, I'm afraid — the brands' individual virtues don't have much to do with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do have another question about grocery stores, though. You hear constantly about how the industry operates with razor-thin margins, and survives only thanks to massive volume. But I've recently done a bunch of shopping at the Italian Market in Philly — a historic, year-round, daily open-air market that starts at Ninth and Christian and trickles down to the great cheesesteak palaces of the South. And the price difference is astounding. Three pounds of grapes cost $2. A dozen green peppers and two bags of onions cost less than $5. You can get five nice navel oranges for a dollar, and even more lemons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Philly is a cheaper town than DC in general, but not &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; much cheaper — costs at Whole Foods and Superfresh are roughly comparable to the ones at Whole Foods and the Giant in Shaw. So can it really be the case that the cost of a roof, refrigeration and employee benefits is the difference? I guess so. The only other explanation I can come up with is that the mob is subsidizing my produce purchases in order to maintain their South Philly fronts.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC, misc"/></entry></feed>