<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Tom Lee - DC, music, personal</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"/><link href="/feeds/dc-music-personal.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>/</id><updated>2009-01-16T14:34:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>no wammie no wammie no wammie no... wait, what?</title><link href="/2009/01/16/no-wammie-no-wammie-no-wammie-no-wait-what/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-01-16T14:34:00-05:00</published><updated>2009-01-16T14:34:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2009-01-16:/2009/01/16/no-wammie-no-wammie-no-wammie-no-wait-what/</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hey! &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dccharles.blogspot.com/2009/01/cant-talk-now-i-have-class-to-teach.html"&gt;The City Veins got nominated for a Wammie&lt;/a&gt;! That's kind of awesome. Nice work, fellas.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC, music, personal"/></entry><entry><title>tonight! Gestures! Fort Reno!</title><link href="/2008/06/30/tonight-gestures-fort-reno/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-06-30T13:11:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-06-30T13:11:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2008-06-30:/2008/06/30/tonight-gestures-fort-reno/</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;You know &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.fortreno.com/about.html"&gt;what to do&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC, music, personal"/></entry><entry><title>talented friends</title><link href="/2008/04/03/talented-friends/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-04-03T12:31:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-04-03T12:31:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2008-04-03:/2008/04/03/talented-friends/</id><summary type="html">&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://thecityveins.com/"&gt;The City Veins&lt;/a&gt;! Tonight! &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.rockandrollhoteldc.com/portal/"&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt;! Come for the music; stay to be a part of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.informationleafblower.com/blog/"&gt;Kyle's&lt;/a&gt; growing media empire. Remember: it starts strangely early. I'll see you there.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don't miss Spencer &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://jezebel.com/375563/neo+con-nipples-new-crushes-and-clinton-on-iraq"&gt;putting on an IM clinic&lt;/a&gt; at Jezebel. Have you been listening to his &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.publicbroadcasting.net/fairgame/.jukebox?action=viewMedia&amp;amp;mediaId=690185"&gt;radio appearances&lt;/a&gt;? You should be. The …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://thecityveins.com/"&gt;The City Veins&lt;/a&gt;! Tonight! &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.rockandrollhoteldc.com/portal/"&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt;! Come for the music; stay to be a part of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.informationleafblower.com/blog/"&gt;Kyle's&lt;/a&gt; growing media empire. Remember: it starts strangely early. I'll see you there.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don't miss Spencer &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://jezebel.com/375563/neo+con-nipples-new-crushes-and-clinton-on-iraq"&gt;putting on an IM clinic&lt;/a&gt; at Jezebel. Have you been listening to his &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.publicbroadcasting.net/fairgame/.jukebox?action=viewMedia&amp;amp;mediaId=690185"&gt;radio appearances&lt;/a&gt;? You should be. The man has got some mic skills.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</content><category term="DC, music, personal"/></entry><entry><title>rock show!</title><link href="/2007/02/15/rock-show/" rel="alternate"/><published>2007-02-15T13:48:00-05:00</published><updated>2007-02-15T13:48:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2007-02-15:/2007/02/15/rock-show/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Well, I'm 27. 26 was a fairly traumatic year, but I'm sorry to leave it behind — it seemed like a pretty good age to be. But I've still got over a thousand days until the crystal in my left palm turns black, so I'm not &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; upset at marking this …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Well, I'm 27. 26 was a fairly traumatic year, but I'm sorry to leave it behind — it seemed like a pretty good age to be. But I've still got over a thousand days until the crystal in my left palm turns black, so I'm not &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; upset at marking this year off the calendar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm still sort of apathetic about the whole birthday observance ritual, though. So instead of trying to guilt you all into celebrating the anniversary of my glorious birth, I think I'll just try to guilt you into coming to this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://www.dcist.com/archives/2007/02/15/unbuckled_5_has.php"&gt;&lt;img alt="unbuckled flyer" class="center" src="http://www.dcist.com/attachments/dcist_amanda/unbuckled%20flyer.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm confident that it'll be great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other news, it appears that the song on the new Arcade Fire CD that's my current favorite is &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.stereogum.com/archives/004615.html"&gt;actually&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://thetorturegarden.blogspot.com/2007_01_01_archive.html"&gt;about&lt;/a&gt; what a jerk Jessica Simpson's dad is. That makes me like it even more.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC, music, personal"/></entry><entry><title>late night</title><link href="/2006/11/08/late-night/" rel="alternate"/><published>2006-11-08T01:36:00-05:00</published><updated>2006-11-08T01:36:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2006-11-08:/2006/11/08/late-night/</id><summary type="html">&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Well, things are winding down. The candidates have gone to bed, nobody's releasing new election results, and all that's really left is for someone to unplug the Chris Matthewsbot and drape him with his protective dust cover. I'm pretty optimistic about my home state's chances of banishing George Allen and …&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Well, things are winding down. The candidates have gone to bed, nobody's releasing new election results, and all that's really left is for someone to unplug the Chris Matthewsbot and drape him with his protective dust cover. I'm pretty optimistic about my home state's chances of banishing George Allen and his pathetically small lizardbrain to the wilds of the Commonwealth (or California — it's time to reconnect with your roots, George). But the senate is just barely, tantalizingly, within reach. I won't jinx it. I'm not optimistic. But I'm hopeful.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;I'm just catching up with all of the election-watching now, I'm afraid. I went to go see Broken Social Scene with Catherine, so most of my election updates came via text message and anxious web browsing on my sidekick (good job on mobile accessibility, CNN.com!).&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;The band was pretty good, overall. When they resisted the temptation to succumb to jam-band awfulness, they were great: &amp;quot;Ibi Dreams Of Pavement&amp;quot; and a countrified version of &amp;quot;Major Label Debut&amp;quot; were both genuinely fantastic. &amp;quot;It's All Gonna Break&amp;quot; was pretty good too, although trying to make a song that's so sprawlingly enormous and of-the-moment even bigger and more spontaneous rendered it just a little silly. Still, I love horn-induced catharsis.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;On the other hand, the untitled, minutes-long batch of noodling before IAGB — when a guitarist stubbornly tried to create feedback that didn't want to come and a bass player tried out his new guitar to no one's amusement but his own — that shit was simply infuriating. I was walking out when they stopped and started playing &amp;quot;It's All Gonna Break&amp;quot; — that made me turn around. But I was genuinely disgusted: $33 should buy you something better than a jam session. I've sat through a &lt;em&gt;Disco Biscuits&lt;/em&gt; show before (it's a long story), and by god I'm not going to do it again. I wasn't disappointed with the show, but I didn't stick around for an encore.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE:&lt;/strong&gt; I almost forgot! Also on stage was DC's own &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brendan_Canty"&gt;Brendan Canty&lt;/a&gt;, fulfilling the terms of his plea agreement (namely, that he participate in every musical project, anywhere, forever). Woooo DC!&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;hr class="docutils" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm home now. Claire McCaskill is about to go on TV. Chris Matthews keeps saying &amp;quot;Missurrah&amp;quot; for some reason, as if it's a word (the Missourians speaking on TV seem to disagree with him) . I'm thinking seriously about bed. Here's hoping I wake up to a uniformly Democratic legislature. McCaskill just claimed victory; Tester's up by several points with 2/3rds reporting; and I have childlike faith in my home state. I've got a sneaking suspicion that tomorrow morning is going to be &lt;em&gt;great&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="DC, music, personal"/></entry></feed>