<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Tom Lee - DC, music</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"/><link href="/feeds/dc-music.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>/</id><updated>2009-04-03T00:47:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Impossible Hair @ the Black Cat</title><link href="/2009/04/03/impossible-hair-the-black-cat/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-04-03T00:47:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-04-03T00:47:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2009-04-03:/2009/04/03/impossible-hair-the-black-cat/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Man! There are few things I like more than getting back from a good show at the Black Cat. Chris suggested we go see his buddy's CD release party, and it was unexpectedly great. With the exception of the City Veins' horn-heavy, guest-star-laden offering, it was probably the best local …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Man! There are few things I like more than getting back from a good show at the Black Cat. Chris suggested we go see his buddy's CD release party, and it was unexpectedly great. With the exception of the City Veins' horn-heavy, guest-star-laden offering, it was probably the best local CD release observation I've attended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A big part of that was Olivia Mancini, whose opener status continues to perplex me. She's got stage presence, she's got pipes, she can play and, most importantly, she's got the songs to make all of the aforementioned matter. All I can hope is that she's on deck for the next doo-woppy pop/rock slot — between the Pipettes and the Ting Tings it seems like the market can bear one such act every year or two. Olivia certainly deserves that level of... well, if not stardom, then whatever replaced it in the current music industry landscape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://oliviamancini.com/audio/OLIVIA_MANCINI-Jealous_Type.mp3"&gt;Olivia Mancini &amp;amp; the Mates – Jealous Type&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next up: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dcist.com/2005/11/08/three_stars_the.php"&gt;The Caribbean&lt;/a&gt;. I spent a large part of their set retrieving beer, so I'm probably not in a good position to judge them. What I heard I mostly liked, but I think it's safe to say that they're not really my thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally there was Impossible Hair. And while they were oversold — if pressed, I would rate their haircuts as merely unlikely — they proved to be an excellent rock band. It was a tight performance filled with really, really good songs. Recommended! Would buy a t-shirt from again. Go see 'em if you have a chance — &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.impossiblehair.com/MPSBL/TOUR.html"&gt;looks like&lt;/a&gt; your next opportunity closer than Baltimore will be May 13 at Velvet. Unless you're planning a trip to Europe, that is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.impossiblehair.com/mp3/whatisthesecretofimpossiblehair.mp3"&gt;Impossible Hair – What is the Secret of Impossible Hair?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;(which seems to be their entire album, unfortunately — I wish they offered some individual tracks on their site)&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content><category term="DC, music"/></entry><entry><title>City Veins @ Black Cat</title><link href="/2008/07/16/city-veins-black-cat/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-07-16T12:55:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-07-16T12:55:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2008-07-16:/2008/07/16/city-veins-black-cat/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've been friends with Charles for a long time now. There's no use trying to fool anyone, so I'll fess up: I'd support his musical endeavors even if they were terrible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it's awfully nice that they're not. I'm not sure when it happened, exactly — the frenzy of the Iota …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've been friends with Charles for a long time now. There's no use trying to fool anyone, so I'll fess up: I'd support his musical endeavors even if they were terrible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it's awfully nice that they're not. I'm not sure when it happened, exactly — the frenzy of the Iota show and the vastness of Fort Reno may have concealed the exact moment — but &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://thecityveins.com/blog/2008/07/16/were-gonna-make-it-after-all/"&gt;last night at the Black Cat&lt;/a&gt; it was clear that the City Veins' live show has passed a new threshhold. God &lt;em&gt;damn&lt;/em&gt; but they killed it. Maybe it's just Stockholm Syndrome; if it is, I'm prepared to embrace it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Watching them play, I couldn't help feeling a pang of envy: it's tough to see such wholehearted commitment to the moment without wanting more of it for yourself. Fortunately it was easy to drown that wistfulness in joy, and pride, at watching your friends throw themselves so completely into something they clearly love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It looks like it's easy now, like the songs have been worked and reworked until they're so pliable that they can be twisted into whatever shape the band imagines during the count-off. I'm sure that's just an illusion. But it's a convincing one, and a testament to how good these guys have gotten at playing together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm sorry I didn't mercilessly promote last night's show; if you weren't there, I wish you had been. I'll do my best to step up my harassment when their next DC gig rolls around.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC, music"/></entry><entry><title>City Veins @ Ft. Reno</title><link href="/2008/07/07/city-veins-ft-reno/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-07-07T15:34:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-07-07T15:34:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2008-07-07:/2008/07/07/city-veins-ft-reno/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Charles &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://thecityveins.com/blog/2008/07/07/fort-reno-tonight/"&gt;says&lt;/a&gt; they're slated to go on second, around 7:50. Looking at the sky right now makes my weather widget's dire predictions look unfounded. We seem poised to rock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And hey, not only will you be able to enjoy a beautiful summer day, free music, and the sight of …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Charles &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://thecityveins.com/blog/2008/07/07/fort-reno-tonight/"&gt;says&lt;/a&gt; they're slated to go on second, around 7:50. Looking at the sky right now makes my weather widget's dire predictions look unfounded. We seem poised to rock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And hey, not only will you be able to enjoy a beautiful summer day, free music, and the sight of adorable children gamboling across the lawn as their embittered ex-musician parents look on, you'll also be able to soak up some X-Files-style conspiracy theorizing. Behold!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A DCist commenter &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dcist.com/2008/05/19/fort_reno_updat.php#comment-1366009"&gt;noted&lt;/a&gt; that Ft. Reno is well-known as a not-so-secret presidential hidey-hole and linked to a&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://coldwar-c4i.net/PEF/index.html"&gt;Related site&lt;/a&gt; with the following documents:
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;-&amp;nbsp;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://coldwar-c4i.net/PEF/Cartwheel/tower-sect.html"&gt;Artists' rendition&lt;/a&gt; of the facility's hypothesized layout (&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://bp3.blogger.com/_d4Fw-OAa1ms/R5Vxk8rNO9I/AAAAAAAAAM8/Ml0r5cQM2E8/s1600-h/baxter_building_final.jpg"&gt;see also&lt;/a&gt;)
&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;-&amp;nbsp;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.ncpc.gov/UserFiles/File/NCPC%20Commission%20Actions%20and%20EDRs/2007%20NCPC%20Commission%20Actions%20and%20EDRs/June%202007/6.7.07%20-%206738%20(delegated)%20FAA%20Fort%20Reno%20Park_.pdf"&gt;Incriminating document&lt;/a&gt; (PDF) indicating that the FAA sought to build a secret mind control transceiver/shed on the property&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.abovetopsecret.com/forum/thread355857/pg1"&gt;Reports&lt;/a&gt; of a mysterious motorcade at the park in the midst of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dcist.com/2008/06/17/ding_dong_the_arsenics_dead_fort_re.php"&gt;arsenic scare&lt;/a&gt;. Could the purported potential for poisoning be dastardly Dick Cheney's bid for a new lair?!! It seems all but certain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content><category term="DC, music"/></entry><entry><title>summer may not be cancelled after all</title><link href="/2008/05/19/summer-may-not-be-cancelled-after-all/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-05-19T15:50:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-05-19T15:50:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2008-05-19:/2008/05/19/summer-may-not-be-cancelled-after-all/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Via Sommer I see that &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://wtop.com/?nid=596&amp;amp;sid=1406503"&gt;Fort Reno might be fine after all&lt;/a&gt;. I suppose this isn't that surprising: the park's initial closure was the result of aerial assays that used imaging to estimate the level of contamination. But of course the spectral signatures of arsenic and indie rock earnestness are …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Via Sommer I see that &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://wtop.com/?nid=596&amp;amp;sid=1406503"&gt;Fort Reno might be fine after all&lt;/a&gt;. I suppose this isn't that surprising: the park's initial closure was the result of aerial assays that used imaging to estimate the level of contamination. But of course the spectral signatures of arsenic and indie rock earnestness are nearly identical (despite the latter being at least somewhat less toxic).&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC, music"/></entry><entry><title>Fort Reno!</title><link href="/2007/08/09/fort-reno/" rel="alternate"/><published>2007-08-09T10:37:00-04:00</published><updated>2007-08-09T10:37:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2007-08-09:/2007/08/09/fort-reno/</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;True to form, I've been really bad about making it out to the wilds of Tenleytown this summer. But I intend to make amends this evening. Anyone else planning on going?&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC, music"/></entry><entry><title>woooUnbuckledwoo!</title><link href="/2007/07/12/wooounbuckledwoo/" rel="alternate"/><published>2007-07-12T10:56:00-04:00</published><updated>2007-07-12T10:56:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2007-07-12:/2007/07/12/wooounbuckledwoo/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Alright, it was a little crowded and hot, at least one channel could be counted on to be clipping until 2/3 of the way through each song, and somebody standing near me seemed to have had a big meal of chili and corn nuts immediately before coming to DC9 …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Alright, it was a little crowded and hot, at least one channel could be counted on to be clipping until 2/3 of the way through each song, and somebody standing near me seemed to have had a big meal of chili and corn nuts immediately before coming to DC9 (my personal recommendation: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.oyamel.com/"&gt;grasshopper tacos&lt;/a&gt; — the taste is just okay, but the horrifying-your-girlfriend potential is pretty solid).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, that was a fine, fine rock show. Congratulations to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://blogstretch.blogspot.com"&gt;Amanda&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.informationleafblower.com"&gt;Kyle&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://cruelsommer.blogspot.com"&gt;Sommer&lt;/a&gt; for another wildly successful Unbuckled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I think we need a new term for whatever genre of music Le Loup belongs to, or aspires to belong to. Along with Arcade Fire, the Polyphonic Spree, Broken Social Scene and who knows who else, this is a band that clearly has a ridiculous number of members, but somehow manages to use them to productive ends. And there are jammy elements, but I'd hate to call any of them jam bands. And there's a lot of melodrama, but — well, okay, there's just a lot of melodrama, I just don't care. I belong to a generation that shed tears when Optimus Prime died — I'm always ready to be emotionally manipulated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class="docutils" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've been a bad blogger recently, but I've got a few semi-nifty technical projects in the works. Hopefully I'll be able to wrap one or two of em up tonight; stay tuned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, the tag links aren't working anymore, if anyone cares — looks like Google crawling them was slowing down my webhost's machine so much that they disabled it. I'll probably just ditch the tags completely.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC, music"/></entry><entry><title>Georgie James / Middle Distance Runner</title><link href="/2007/07/10/georgie-james-middle-distance-runner/" rel="alternate"/><published>2007-07-10T12:51:00-04:00</published><updated>2007-07-10T12:51:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2007-07-10:/2007/07/10/georgie-james-middle-distance-runner/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I suppose &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2007/07/09/scene-dc-bloggy-types-ro_n_55432.html"&gt;this writeup&lt;/a&gt; is making Friday's show still relevant, so I may as well put up the post that the demands of wedding-attendance preempted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, it was great, and you should check out &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.informationleafblower.com"&gt;Kyle's&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/leafblower/sets/72157600719786699/"&gt;amazing photos&lt;/a&gt; of the show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, the two bands I saw — Middle Distance Runner and …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I suppose &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2007/07/09/scene-dc-bloggy-types-ro_n_55432.html"&gt;this writeup&lt;/a&gt; is making Friday's show still relevant, so I may as well put up the post that the demands of wedding-attendance preempted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, it was great, and you should check out &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.informationleafblower.com"&gt;Kyle's&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/leafblower/sets/72157600719786699/"&gt;amazing photos&lt;/a&gt; of the show.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, the two bands I saw — Middle Distance Runner and Georgie James — both struck me as having a similar quirk: dueling songwriters. It's not an uncommon phenomenon, certainly, but it seemed particularly obvious in these two cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't know much about MDR, having had to leave their Unbuckled appearance early, but it was pretty easy to see that their songs come in two flavors. First, catchy pop that occasionally aspires to Bends-era Radioheadishness, and which is strangely lacking in bridges (seriously guys, key changes: they're good for what ails ya). Second, garage/stomp/Kings of Leon-style rock, the kind of stuff played by shirtless dudes in jeans and mesh caps who spend a lot of time trying to shop for belt buckles without anyone noticing them doing it. I'm not a huge fan of the latter and so couldn't tell you whether MDR's take on it is particularly good or not. But I really liked the songs of type A.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Georgie James has this sort of split personality, too. John writes angular pop songs (angular — what a fantastically cliched music critic word), while Laura's melodies seem to be more about mellow, bouncy notes tumbling over one another. I like John's hooks better, but although he has a very nice voice, Laura's clearly the one with the distinctive vocals and charisma (also: she's purty). It was nice to hear them making larger (though still tentative) forays into one another's songs on their older material, but I was surprised to see how divided their styles remained.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, I haven't seen the songwriting credits on their demo EP or their unreleased album, so perhaps I'm just imagining a division where none actually exists. But in my mind, at least, the band's got two distinct styles. Each one has a lot to recommend it, but I'm looking forward to hearing more stuff that capitalizes on both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE:&lt;/strong&gt; While you're at it, why not go check out the first song from &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.myspace.com/bulletsdc"&gt;Bullets&lt;/a&gt;, the newest band in the great Q &amp;amp; Not U diaspora. Pretty catchy, although I've gotta say that the &lt;em&gt;Purple Rain&lt;/em&gt; screengrab may be overkill.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC, music"/></entry><entry><title>le loup</title><link href="/2007/05/16/le-loup/" rel="alternate"/><published>2007-05-16T16:34:00-04:00</published><updated>2007-05-16T16:34:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2007-05-16:/2007/05/16/le-loup/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.brightestyoungthings.com/svetlana/music/signings-of-spring-georgie-james-saddles-up/"&gt;Another solid DC band&lt;/a&gt;! Color me pleased. Check out their attractively-designed site &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://leloupmusic.net"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; or their MySpace page &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://myspace.com/leloupmusic"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. And if you're sad to be limited to the three songs... well, there's practically nothing that the command line can't solve these days...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
for((i=1;i&amp;lt;=10;i+=1)); do
printf …&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.brightestyoungthings.com/svetlana/music/signings-of-spring-georgie-james-saddles-up/"&gt;Another solid DC band&lt;/a&gt;! Color me pleased. Check out their attractively-designed site &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://leloupmusic.net"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; or their MySpace page &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://myspace.com/leloupmusic"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. And if you're sad to be limited to the three songs... well, there's practically nothing that the command line can't solve these days...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;pre class="literal-block"&gt;
for((i=1;i&amp;lt;=10;i+=1)); do
printf &amp;quot;%02d&amp;quot; $i | xargs -I {} wget http://leloupmusic.net/BIRDS/music/{}.mp3
done
&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Be forewarned: it's only 64kbps.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC, music"/></entry></feed>