<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Tom Lee - DC, personal, tech</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"/><link href="/feeds/dc-personal-tech.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>/</id><updated>2009-02-27T13:27:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>two transformer plugs, one too late</title><link href="/2009/02/27/two-transformer-plugs-one-too-late/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-02-27T13:27:00-05:00</published><updated>2009-02-27T13:27:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2009-02-27:/2009/02/27/two-transformer-plugs-one-too-late/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's too late for you now, you poor suckers, but you should be sorry if you missed &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://attackerman.firedoglake.com"&gt;Spencer&lt;/a&gt;'s virtuoso performance at Transformer last night. &lt;em&gt;Iron Man vs. the Imperialists&lt;/em&gt; expanded on his &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.prospect.org/cs/articles?article=iron_man_vs_the_imperialists"&gt;Prospect essay of the same name&lt;/a&gt;, and managed to not only make me feel self-conscious about my …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's too late for you now, you poor suckers, but you should be sorry if you missed &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://attackerman.firedoglake.com"&gt;Spencer&lt;/a&gt;'s virtuoso performance at Transformer last night. &lt;em&gt;Iron Man vs. the Imperialists&lt;/em&gt; expanded on his &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.prospect.org/cs/articles?article=iron_man_vs_the_imperialists"&gt;Prospect essay of the same name&lt;/a&gt;, and managed to not only make me feel self-conscious about my pathetic knowledge of 20th century American history — which is perfectly normal, and something that happens pretty much any time someone mentions a historical event not explicitly depicted in a &lt;em&gt;Simpsons&lt;/em&gt; episode — but also made me feel self-conscious about my limited knowledge of comic books, which is not something that usually happens in places that aren't the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I didn't mind, because Spencer was engaging, funny and had an interesting argument to make. And, more importantly, I didn't mind because it's inspiring to see a friend deploy an impressive set of skills toward a whimsical end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On that note: I can't boast any impressive skills myself other than wide-ranging dilettantism, but my co-presenter on Saturday &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://selforganizingsystem.org/images/sculpture-magazine_April-2008.pdf"&gt;certainly can&lt;/a&gt; (PDF). So come see us tomorrow at Transformer Gallery and learn a thing or two about microcontrollers and why they're about to escape the realm of geekery and enter into the mainstream hobbiest's arsenal. 2pm, on the same block as Whole Foods.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC, personal, tech"/></entry><entry><title>one night only!</title><link href="/2008/03/25/one-night-only/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-03-25T14:06:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-03-25T14:06:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2008-03-25:/2008/03/25/one-night-only/</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Dorkbot! &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dorkbot.org/dorkbotdc"&gt;Tonight&lt;/a&gt;! Come see me talk! Or don't, and download a podcast of it! If I remember to buy batteries!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hurrah!!!&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC, personal, tech"/></entry><entry><title>not even a day</title><link href="/2007/07/18/not-even-a-day/" rel="alternate"/><published>2007-07-18T14:44:00-04:00</published><updated>2007-07-18T14:44:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2007-07-18:/2007/07/18/not-even-a-day/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Walking into the Old Dominion Brewhouse yesterday, two guys stopped me and asked if I could direct them to &lt;a class="reference external" href="/2007/07/17/membership-has-its-privileges-theyre-just-all-kind-of-lame/"&gt;The Space&lt;/a&gt;. Clearly I have no idea what the market actually wants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other news, I'm interested to hear if there's a section on La/te Ni/ght Sh/ots where …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Walking into the Old Dominion Brewhouse yesterday, two guys stopped me and asked if I could direct them to &lt;a class="reference external" href="/2007/07/17/membership-has-its-privileges-theyre-just-all-kind-of-lame/"&gt;The Space&lt;/a&gt;. Clearly I have no idea what the market actually wants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other news, I'm interested to hear if there's a section on La/te Ni/ght Sh/ots where users can employ any HTML — links, images, whatever. If you've used the site enough to notice such a spot, let me know. Science projects are hatching.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC, personal, tech"/></entry></feed>