<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Tom Lee - DC, personal</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/feeds/dc-personal.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>https://tomlee.wtf/</id><updated>2008-08-14T12:01:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>good's triumph</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/08/14/goods-triumph/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-08-14T12:01:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-08-14T12:01:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-08-14:/2008/08/14/goods-triumph/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;You've already seen this, but for the record: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.mediabistro.com/fishbowlDC/hottest_media_types/hottest_media_types_your_2008_winners_91436.asp"&gt;Brian has emerged victorious&lt;/a&gt;, as he inevitably must in a world that still clings to some shred of sanity — or, at the least, aspires to dignity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Impressively, over 221,000 votes were cast for Brian. That's one out of every four District …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;You've already seen this, but for the record: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.mediabistro.com/fishbowlDC/hottest_media_types/hottest_media_types_your_2008_winners_91436.asp"&gt;Brian has emerged victorious&lt;/a&gt;, as he inevitably must in a world that still clings to some shred of sanity — or, at the least, aspires to dignity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Impressively, over 221,000 votes were cast for Brian. That's one out of every four District residents, and about a hundred thousand more than were cast in the city during &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://elections.gmu.edu/Voter_Turnout_2006.htm"&gt;the 2006 election&lt;/a&gt;! Truly, this represents a mandate. A mandate to continue being hot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ALSO:&lt;/strong&gt; An impressive showing by runner-up Jeff Young. One to watch for 2009! I think this kid's got a big upside.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC, personal"/></entry><entry><title>((sum(wrongs) % 2)==0) ? right : er, let's say moral ambiguity</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/08/06/sumwrongs-20-right-er-lets-say-moral-ambiguity/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-08-06T16:56:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-08-06T16:56:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-08-06:/2008/08/06/sumwrongs-20-right-er-lets-say-moral-ambiguity/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's that time of year again: the FishbowlDC Hottest Media Types contest is upon us. And frankly, I'm a bit disappointed: due to last year's... &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://machinist.salon.com/feature/2007/08/22/fishbowl_bots/"&gt;irregularities&lt;/a&gt;, Patrick Gavin promised new and improved technology. And I was ready! I checked &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://simile.mit.edu/wiki/Crowbar"&gt;Crowbar&lt;/a&gt; out of SVN and into a virtualized environment; I created …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's that time of year again: the FishbowlDC Hottest Media Types contest is upon us. And frankly, I'm a bit disappointed: due to last year's... &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://machinist.salon.com/feature/2007/08/22/fishbowl_bots/"&gt;irregularities&lt;/a&gt;, Patrick Gavin promised new and improved technology. And I was ready! I checked &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://simile.mit.edu/wiki/Crowbar"&gt;Crowbar&lt;/a&gt; out of SVN and into a virtualized environment; I created a custom screen-scraper script for it, and got it working with XulRunner in such a way that it could be called by Ruby. I started looking into firing up a farm of Amazon EC2 instances to run the operation in parallel. I hit a snag when trying to find a decent RDF parsing gem for examining Crowbar's output, but then the poll went up and I saw it didn't matter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's the same goddamn PollDaddy crap as last year! And it's still just as vulnerable to a looped one-liner shell script. Fire up Firebug to grab the AJAX call's URL, then set curl to keep loading it. You don't even need to fake your user agent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ah well. We can still have some fun with this. Thanks to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://arantius.com/misc/greasemonkey/script-compiler"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; handy GreaseMonkey script compiler I've put together a little Firefox extension that should help this year's voting arrive at the appropriate result: namely, one that puts Mr. Brian Beutler at the top.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those who question the propriety of this enterprise or (gasp) Brian's hotness — well, there's probably no hope for you. But look, maybe an analogy will help: Fifty Cent got shot a bunch and it made people start acting like he can rap. Now he's a millionaire with access to unlimited supplies of Vitamin Water. A public acknowledgment of Brian's post-shooting beauty is a pittance in comparison. It's the very least we can do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it should be really easy, too. All you have to do is click the link below, say OK to whatever security warnings come up, and install the extension. I think it'll work in Firefox 2 and 3; I've only tested it in the latter, though. After it's installed and you've restarted Firefox, navigate over to the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.mediabistro.com/fishbowlDC/hottest_media_types/hottest_media_types_get_voting_male_off_air_90977.asp"&gt;appropriate page&lt;/a&gt;. A message should pop up, then the robovoting will begin. You'll get feedback, too, and the total number of votes you've cast (and your associated rank) will be displayed as it proceeds (it should remember the total even if you stop and restart the process).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if you &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; want to demonstrate your love for Brian, you can leave proof of your vote total here in comments by pasting the tiny hexadecimal garbage displayed under it (along with the vote total you're claiming) — each total has a unique code. No cheating!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/static/2008/08/06/beutlerator.xpi"&gt;Install the Beutlerator&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC, personal"/></entry><entry><title>Brian</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/07/03/brian/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-07-03T11:17:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-07-03T11:17:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-07-03:/2008/07/03/brian/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Wow. Well, yesterday was &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.prospect.org/csnc/blogs/ezraklein_archive?month=07&amp;amp;year=2008&amp;amp;base_name=brian#107421"&gt;kind of terrifying&lt;/a&gt;, huh? I haven't got anything original to say but of course like everyone else I'm extremely glad that Brian is okay and seems poised to have an improbably, miraculously complete recovery. I suppose I shouldn't be surprised: he's pretty much the most unflappable …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Wow. Well, yesterday was &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.prospect.org/csnc/blogs/ezraklein_archive?month=07&amp;amp;year=2008&amp;amp;base_name=brian#107421"&gt;kind of terrifying&lt;/a&gt;, huh? I haven't got anything original to say but of course like everyone else I'm extremely glad that Brian is okay and seems poised to have an improbably, miraculously complete recovery. I suppose I shouldn't be surprised: he's pretty much the most unflappable guy I know. That his body is greeting three bullets with what amounts to an unimpressed shrug seems perfectly in character.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond gratitude for his well-being, though, I'm not sure how to react. My instinct is to resist the urge to draw new conclusions about crime and guns and the city based upon this one horrible incident. Don't let the immediacy of the thing confuse you, I tell myself. Yet on the same day I read about &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.vanityfair.com/politics/features/2008/08/hitchens200808?currentPage=1"&gt;someone else&lt;/a&gt; using the purely experiential to arrive at what I consider to be the truth, and it doesn't seem like he could have gotten there any other way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can rationalize together a system for how I've decided to discriminate between these two potential lessons, but I'm not really sure I buy it.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC, personal"/></entry><entry><title>when I became a manboy</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/05/16/when-i-became-a-manboy/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-05-16T12:16:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-05-16T12:16:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-05-16:/2008/05/16/when-i-became-a-manboy/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Go forth and read Spencer's &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.prospect.org/cs/articles?article=iron_man_vs_the_imperialists"&gt;piece in the Prospect&lt;/a&gt; about Iron Man's evolution as an embodiment of American imperial power. And, while you're at it, make sure you read &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.prospect.org/cs/articles?article=the_revolt_of_the_comic_boooks"&gt;Julian's analysis of how comics have grappled with the rise of bellicose authoritarianism in the wake of 9/11&lt;/a&gt; (although if …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Go forth and read Spencer's &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.prospect.org/cs/articles?article=iron_man_vs_the_imperialists"&gt;piece in the Prospect&lt;/a&gt; about Iron Man's evolution as an embodiment of American imperial power. And, while you're at it, make sure you read &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.prospect.org/cs/articles?article=the_revolt_of_the_comic_boooks"&gt;Julian's analysis of how comics have grappled with the rise of bellicose authoritarianism in the wake of 9/11&lt;/a&gt; (although if you didn't see that one in the print edition you really should hunt down a copy so you can see the associated art). Both are excellent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I have to admit that I'm a little embarrassed by just how excellent I think they are — how compelling I find the arguments, and how seriously I'm prepared to engage with them. Not because the authors aren't brilliant, but because — c'mon — &lt;em&gt;comic books&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is our generation really about to start running society? Really? Shouldn't an adult step in and do something about this before the joke goes too far?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not that I'm complaining, mind you. I'm just feeling slightly sheepish about the fact that back issues of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Official_Handbook_of_the_Marvel_Universe"&gt;Marvel Universe&lt;/a&gt; seem poised to supplant French and German as gateways to the structures underpinning our society's intellectual discourse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To everyone who's going to find this tedious: sincere apologies. It'll only be for the next fifty years or so.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC, personal"/></entry><entry><title>welcome, brother!</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/04/23/welcome-brother/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-04-23T11:14:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-04-23T11:14:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-04-23:/2008/04/23/welcome-brother/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://matthewyglesias.theatlantic.com/archives/2008/04/prepare_for_bikeblogging.php"&gt;Matt got a bike&lt;/a&gt;! This is wonderful news. I'm a big cycling proponent, of course, and am very glad to see a friend take up this healthy and convenient hobby. The benefits are myriad: why, just this week I received a check compensating me for the repair bill incurred the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://matthewyglesias.theatlantic.com/archives/2008/04/prepare_for_bikeblogging.php"&gt;Matt got a bike&lt;/a&gt;! This is wonderful news. I'm a big cycling proponent, of course, and am very glad to see a friend take up this healthy and convenient hobby. The benefits are myriad: why, just this week I received a check compensating me for the repair bill incurred the last time I was hit by a car (true!). More to the point, though, I think neither Matt nor I are particularly patient people. Hopefully he will enjoy being freed from the torpor of his pathetic human limbs as much as I have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally Matt's commenters have a ton of advice for him, ranging from the stupefyingly obvious (you should use a lock!) to the idiotic (&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://matthewyglesias.theatlantic.com/archives/2008/04/prepare_for_bikeblogging.php#comment-1978747"&gt;don't sweat the helmet, bro&lt;/a&gt;) to the completely inane (&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://matthewyglesias.theatlantic.com/archives/2008/04/prepare_for_bikeblogging.php#comment-1977834"&gt;you need fenders&lt;/a&gt;(!?)). Allow me to add my own suggestions to the chorus:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be prepared to adopt startlingly new ideas about the appropriateness of various traffic laws. This may be unsettling at first, but don't worry: you will quickly develop elaborate justifications for these opinions, many of them loudly based on your right to defend your safety, and many more quietly originating from your own preferences and convenience. The experience roughly approximates what I think it must be like to be an NRA member, except you're concerned with fending off regulatory challenges to your momentum rather than to your firearms.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Understand that your bike shop experience is about to get catastrophically worse. If you're anything like me, while shopping for a bike you probably had a chipper salesgirl show you around, distrac you from your ignorance and gently hint that maybe you two could go out after this major purchase, because, you know, she doesn't get to meet a lot of guys who know nothing about bikes in this job and she finds that really attractive. But your time in retail land is over, my friend.
From now on you'll be dealing with the maintenance department, and the experience is fraught. This is the only shopping experience I'm aware of where the customer is treated with more contempt than at a record store. It's understandable: the employees are highly skilled and in demand, yet &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; in dead-end jobs. Also, they're much, much cooler than you, and would prefer to hang out with the messengers milling around the repair counter instead of taking your money. My best advice is to find an older mechanic, as they tend to spend about 80% of their time on long disquisitions about bicycle repair, which is both kind of interesting and leaves them less time for staring at you disdainfully. Special bonus if you go to CityBikes: the guy there looks exactly like &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.chrismclaren.com/blog/wp-content/images/2007/02/Alan_Moore.jpg"&gt;Alan Moore&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's best to live in constant fear of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.webmd.com/erectile-dysfunction/news/20050825/studies-link-bike-seats-erectile-dysfunction"&gt;what bicycling is doing to your sex life&lt;/a&gt;. I've never experienced any ill effects, and given the small amount of biking I do I doubt I ever will. But it's a fantastic thing to worry about, particularly given its likelihood to result in your getting hit by a car while carefully fidgeting on your saddle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Which reminds me: be prepared for other cyclists to call their bike seats &amp;quot;saddles&amp;quot;. I know, it's pretty annoying.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Maintenance tasks you can easily do yourself and probably should: fixing tires, replacing brake pads, tightening brakes, installing saddles and pedals, adjusting your shifting if it gets slightly unaligned. Things you can do but probably will be better off paying someone to do for you: replacing chains, replacing cables. Things that you can't do: true a wheel, perform a really good tune-up, or anything more complicated. After I post this my friend Chris will probably accost me in the hall and say, &amp;quot;You can totally do all those things!&amp;quot; But that is only true if you have someone like Chris on hand who is overly generous with his time and bike knowledge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, this list is becoming dangerously practical. I'll stop right there. Enjoy your new freedom and speed! Oh, and the secret anti-pedestrian meetings are the first Tuesday of every month.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC, personal"/></entry></feed>