<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Tom Lee - DC, science</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"/><link href="/feeds/dc-science.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>/</id><updated>2009-10-21T20:12:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>beeronomics</title><link href="/2009/10/21/beeronomics/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-10-21T20:12:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-10-21T20:12:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2009-10-21:/2009/10/21/beeronomics/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Matt has taken &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/manifestdensitynet/~3/G5TwQ8E8AtU/"&gt;my offhanded complaint about DC beer prices&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://yglesias.thinkprogress.org/archives/2009/10/the-wages-of-high-wages.php"&gt;placed it within the context of social justice&lt;/a&gt;, noting that DC's high wages account for its high beer prices (our average drink prices are comparable to New York's; our median annual wage, at $57.1k, is somewhat higher than …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Matt has taken &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/manifestdensitynet/~3/G5TwQ8E8AtU/"&gt;my offhanded complaint about DC beer prices&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://yglesias.thinkprogress.org/archives/2009/10/the-wages-of-high-wages.php"&gt;placed it within the context of social justice&lt;/a&gt;, noting that DC's high wages account for its high beer prices (our average drink prices are comparable to New York's; our median annual wage, at $57.1k, is somewhat higher than New York's, at $52.8k; both are significantly above the national median of $42.3k). His basic project is all to the good: thus is the charge of any thoughtful person concerned with the common weal and/or our ability to drink away worries about the state it's in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However! I object to his specific analysis of the situation for two reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first concerns the relevance of the wage figures Matt cites -- I think the average DC beer-buyer is poorer than those numbers imply.&amp;nbsp; Matt's reliance on pan-workforce statistics is understandable, but still insufficient for the task at hand. One needs to look at the &lt;em&gt;bar-going&lt;/em&gt; slice of the population in order to characterize the market for happy hour beer. Sadly, the BLS does not consider this a focus of their work. However! Both New York and DC are on the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://pewresearch.org/pubs/1380/marriage-and-divorce-by-state"&gt;high end&lt;/a&gt; of the marriage age spectrum, so let's assume that bar-going rates are roughly similar for both populations. I contend that DC's drinking class is likely to be impoverished relative to New York's, for two reasons. First, DC's young professionals are likely to have a substantially larger average debt burden than those of New York, given that we have &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://factfinder.census.gov/servlet/GRTTable?_bm=y&amp;amp;-_box_head_nbr=R1503&amp;amp;-ds_name=ACS_2008_1YR_G00_&amp;amp;-_lang=en&amp;amp;-format=US-30&amp;amp;-CONTEXT=grt"&gt;twice the incidence of graduate degrees&lt;/a&gt; and, one imagines, student loans (&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dcist.com/2009/12/dc_grads_have_the_most_college_debt.php"&gt;proof&lt;/a&gt;!). Second: while I don't have stats to back it up, the incidence of unpaid internships in this city must be abnormally high, even when compared to New York's wage-depressed economy of starry-eyed small-town dreamers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second objection is based on evidence that the supply of alcohol in DC is artificially constrained, producing higher prices than would otherwise be found. I'm pretty sure that Matt's aware of this effect, because I think I stole the idea from him. Namely: the terrible regulatory situation faced by DC bars. A &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.trans.abc.state.ny.us/JSP/query/PublicQueryAdvanceSearchPage.jsp"&gt;search&lt;/a&gt; for retailers licensed to sell alcohol for on-premises consumption in New York, NY yields 14,718 records. An extremely generous summing of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://abra.dc.gov/abra/cwp/view,A,1272,Q,635589.asp"&gt;DC's licensed alcohol sellers&lt;/a&gt; — I included everyone but grocery stores, liquor stores and caterers — shows 1,039 licensees. Normalizing this to population is challenging: liquor licenses aren't administered at the MSA level, and it should be obvious that a larger proportion of DC's happy hour attendees are from the suburbs than is the case for New York. But Wikipedia puts the workday population of DC at &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Washington,_dc"&gt;around a million&lt;/a&gt;, so let's run with that number. If we do, we can see that DC has 1.039 milli-watering holes per capita (mWHPC), versus a robust 1.760 mWHPC for New York City (using per capita rates across the entire population -- not just the bar-going segment -- because of our our assumption that the demographics (if not the economics) of bar attendance are similar in both cities). Even using the formal population of DC (591,833) leaves New York in the lead, with a DC score of 1.756. And this is to say nothing of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Last_call_%28bar_term%29#US_State_specific_laws"&gt;New York's later last call&lt;/a&gt;, which provides the city's residents with 8.3% more drinking hours per bar (marginal though they may be).&amp;nbsp; Normalizing the mWHPC score to DC's last call, New York emerges with a commanding 1.91 mWHPC&lt;sub&gt;w(2AM)&lt;/sub&gt; -- nearly twice as much as DC!*&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The significance of this disparity is bolstered by looking at alcohol consumption stats.&amp;nbsp; These are actually pretty hard to track down on an MSA level, and obviously state figures won't do when making comparisons to DC. &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://oas.samhsa.gov/96state/appendix.htm#AppC"&gt;This&lt;/a&gt; admittedly-dated survey is about the best I could find, and shows a rate of alcohol use over a 30-day window that's five percentage points higher for DC than New York. All else being equal, one would assume that the per-capita quantity of bars would be higher in harder-drinking cities.&amp;nbsp; Yet in this case we see exactly the opposite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This all suggests to me that wages aren't the whole story -- at least when that story is told in comparison to New York -- and that regulatory forces play a significant role in distorting the DC market for alcohol by keeping supply artificially low relative to demand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;* As I went to sleep last night I realized that, unless something has changed since I last stayed out late and DC bars are now open for 24 of the day's 26 hours, my math is wrong. The real percentage increase caused by a later last call should probably be substantially higher, even though a contrary effect should be introduced by applying something like a discount rate to the extra hours themselves.&amp;nbsp; So I can't really propose a firm number, though using no discount and assuming drinking begins at 5pm would give you an adjustment weight of 1.22; it therefore seems safe to say that New York's weighted score should be no more than 2.15.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC, science"/></entry><entry><title>wires are the best!</title><link href="/2009/01/28/wires-are-the-best/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-01-28T14:48:00-05:00</published><updated>2009-01-28T14:48:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2009-01-28:/2009/01/28/wires-are-the-best/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm now hopelessly late with this, so I'll try (and fail) to make it brief. On Friday &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.ryanavent.com/blog/?p=1755"&gt;Ryan discussed D.C.'s ban on overhead &amp;quot;catenary&amp;quot; wires&lt;/a&gt;, which would be necessary for electric streetcars. Apparently you can't use an electrified sunken rail in cities that have to salt their roads …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm now hopelessly late with this, so I'll try (and fail) to make it brief. On Friday &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.ryanavent.com/blog/?p=1755"&gt;Ryan discussed D.C.'s ban on overhead &amp;quot;catenary&amp;quot; wires&lt;/a&gt;, which would be necessary for electric streetcars. Apparently you can't use an electrified sunken rail in cities that have to salt their roads — there are corrosion issues. Unfortunately, changing the law to allow overhead wires would require congressional involvement. Ryan mentions a company that's pushing a technology providing for the wireless transfer of power from the street to the streetcar, allowing the system to be sealed and immune to salt. It sounds like a pretty clever solution. But that doesn't make it a good one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like a transformer, this technology works through induction, converting electricity to magnetism and back again. In a normal transformer you have a core of some sort — picture an iron ring — and you've got two wires, one for input and one for output. These get wrapped around the core like in &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Transformer3d_col3.svg"&gt;this picture&lt;/a&gt;. Send alternating current into the input wire and its wrappings will generate a magnetic field, which will be conducted along the core, which will excite electrons in the other wire's coils and generate an output current. If you change the ratio of windings on the input and output coils the voltage will change, too, which is a very useful thing to be able to do. As you might imagine, transforming energy from one form to another in this way isn't perfectly efficient (although in large, well-designed units it can be very close to it). Some electricity is lost to heat, which is why those heavy old wall-wart adapters — heavy thanks to their iron cores — tend to be warm to the touch after they've been plugged in for a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Newer &amp;quot;switchmode&amp;quot; adapters use a different technique for changing voltage levels. This method doesn't require an iron core, which is why they can be so much lighter and smaller. Strictly speaking, transformers don't need the iron core, either. The problem is that they're much less efficient without one — which brings us to inductive power transfer and the streetcars. In this case one coil is sitting in the street and one's sitting in the streetcar. The core, such as it is, is made of air, which is terrible at guiding magnetic fields, and gets ever-more terrible the further apart the coils are — this is not a useful technique for moving power anything but very short distances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point of all this is that you're going to be wasting energy if you try to move it around wirelessly. Worse, it's going to be more expensive to build the system to do all this than it would be to just make the connection with wires. It's not as if inductive charging hasn't been tried in the marketplace: some early electric cars used inductive paddles to charge, and various efforts are &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.dansdata.com/danletters150.htm"&gt;intermittently made&lt;/a&gt; to provide magical laptop-charging desks. But aside from electric toothbrushes — which, as the previous link notes, can afford to waste some energy if it lets them stay watertight — there just aren't that many applications where choosing a more expensive, more wasteful way of transmitting energy makes sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I have a feeling that the same will prove to be true of streetcars. Wikipedia &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wireless_energy_transfer#Resonant_induction"&gt;cites&lt;/a&gt; an 80% efficiency number from an experimental bus system developed in 1990. That was a while ago, but it's hard for me to imagine that the situation has gotten that much better — or that real-world applications could match the performance of a system in a closed test track. It's going to cost more money than catenary wires, and you won't be able to get your coils very close together on hilly streets, so your electricity bill is going to be 10% or 20% more than it would if you used direct conduction. It would be a shame to let an accident of bureaucratic history make this engineering choice.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC, science"/></entry></feed>