<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Tom Lee - DC, tech</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/feeds/dc-tech.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>https://tomlee.wtf/</id><updated>2010-03-02T11:21:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>making mintyboost</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2010/03/02/making-mintyboost/" rel="alternate"/><published>2010-03-02T11:21:00-05:00</published><updated>2010-03-02T11:21:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2010-03-02:/2010/03/02/making-mintyboost/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=F6OMX9pvuwo"&gt;Kriston and I built Lady Ada's Game of Life kit&lt;/a&gt; over at HacDC a while back, and it roused the interest of a few folks. Sommer asked that I be on the lookout for another kit that might be a good candidate for learning to solder. I eventually suggested another …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=F6OMX9pvuwo"&gt;Kriston and I built Lady Ada's Game of Life kit&lt;/a&gt; over at HacDC a while back, and it roused the interest of a few folks. Sommer asked that I be on the lookout for another kit that might be a good candidate for learning to solder. I eventually suggested another Lady Ada kit: the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.ladyada.net/make/mintyboost/"&gt;MintyBoost&lt;/a&gt;, a simple circuit that lets you top up your USB gadgets' batteries through the use of a pair of AAs. By the time I got my act together, six(!) people had expressed interest in building the kit, pushing supplies of my tools (somewhat scarce) and electronics knowledge (decidedly meager) to their limits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it went surprisingly well! Everyone's kit worked immediately; in fact, they even seemed to work with the iPhone 3GSes that were on hand -- something that &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://forums.adafruit.com/viewtopic.php?f=15&amp;amp;t=11661"&gt;the MintyBoost can't necessarily be relied upon to do&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/sbma44/sets/72157623412860639/"&gt;&lt;img alt="glamor shot" class="center" src="http://farm5.static.flickr.com/4029/4400244166_568b4809a5.jpg" style="width: 500px; height: 375px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[flickr]set:72157623412860639[/flickr]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that my favorite part was watching everyone &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/sbma44/4399474921/"&gt;mess around with the Dremel&lt;/a&gt;. That's some advanced nerdery for you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think that folks had fun; we might do this again, perhaps with more of an Arduino bent. If you want in, let me know.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC, tech"/></entry><entry><title>some NextBus stats</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2009/07/02/some-nextbus-stats/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-07-02T22:26:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-07-02T22:26:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2009-07-02:/2009/07/02/some-nextbus-stats/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;No word yet from WMATA, but I did end up writing a script to grab NextBus's routeconfig data (download &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.megaupload.com/?d=NUI1B2H8"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). Then I tried to match each NextBus-defined stop with the closest one in the GTFS dataset. Some stats*:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;NextBus's dataset tracks 711 unique stop IDs. GTFS has 10,380.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;No word yet from WMATA, but I did end up writing a script to grab NextBus's routeconfig data (download &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.megaupload.com/?d=NUI1B2H8"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). Then I tried to match each NextBus-defined stop with the closest one in the GTFS dataset. Some stats*:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;NextBus's dataset tracks 711 unique stop IDs. GTFS has 10,380.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://stefanobittante.blogspot.com/2007/11/latitude-longitude-distance-in-mysql.html"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; function to measure distance, the average space between matched stops is 164 feet. The smallest is 11 feet. The largest is 9/10ths of a kilometer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;218 NextBus stops wound up sharing the same GTFS stop.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, pretty bad — this level of data quality is clearly unusable. My GIS skills are weak; this may be my own stupid fault. I'll consult with some experts and see what I might be doing wrong. But the basic distance-matching idea is pretty straightforward, so I'm not terrifically optimistic. It's possible that data quality is just going to really, really stink — to be sure, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dcist.com/2009/07/testing_next_bus_stop_numbers_poste.php"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; is not particularly encouraging. Here's hoping we can get a proper lookup table out of WMATA or NextBus. Otherwise I don't see a great alternative to manual intervention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;* These numbers ignore the routes that NextBus tracks but which GTFS does not; those are B99, F99, L99, NH1, P99, REX, S80 and S91 (they appear to be shuttles and the like). I haven't yet identified the routes that are in GTFS but not tracked by NextBus.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC, tech"/></entry><entry><title>shameless non-self promotion</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2009/04/04/shameless-non-self-promotion/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-04-04T11:55:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-04-04T11:55:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2009-04-04:/2009/04/04/shameless-non-self-promotion/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://sunlightlabs.com/"&gt;Sunlight Labs&lt;/a&gt; has been running its now-annual &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://sunlightlabs.com/appsforamerica/"&gt;Apps for America contest&lt;/a&gt;, and this morning I've been paging through a bunch of the entries. There's some pretty cool stuff! I haven't made it all the way through the 40-some submissions — and frankly, I'm just trying to orient myself, not delve into …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://sunlightlabs.com/"&gt;Sunlight Labs&lt;/a&gt; has been running its now-annual &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://sunlightlabs.com/appsforamerica/"&gt;Apps for America contest&lt;/a&gt;, and this morning I've been paging through a bunch of the entries. There's some pretty cool stuff! I haven't made it all the way through the 40-some submissions — and frankly, I'm just trying to orient myself, not delve into the apps with attention to make solid judgments about which ones are worthwhile (this is where you notice that the views expressed here have no bearing on the contest or its judging, are not representative of my eployer, are completely misinformed, etc.). But I feel like pointing out two entries in particular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://geekybuddha.org/buddy/"&gt;Buddy&lt;/a&gt;, partly because I have a soft spot for chatbots but mostly because I find the robotic logo both adorable and terrifying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And second, there's &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://filibusted.us/"&gt;Filibusted&lt;/a&gt;, which my filibuster-hating friends may find interesting, or at least encouraging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But do check out &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://sunlightlabs.com/appsforamerica/apps/"&gt;the rest of the entries&lt;/a&gt; — there's some really good stuff in there. Although I should probably warn my fellow D.C. residents that repeatedly stopping yourself from entering your own zip code when searching for information about congressional representation is kind of depressing.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC, tech"/></entry><entry><title>GTFS drudge work</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2009/04/02/gtfs-drudge-work/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-04-02T10:08:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-04-02T10:08:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2009-04-02:/2009/04/02/gtfs-drudge-work/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last night I finally found a moment to begin playing around with the WMATA GTFS data. Well, that's not quite right: I tried to use the Django ORM to load the dataset when it was first released, but a memory leak killed the process when I left it to run …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last night I finally found a moment to begin playing around with the WMATA GTFS data. Well, that's not quite right: I tried to use the Django ORM to load the dataset when it was first released, but a memory leak killed the process when I left it to run overnight — something that doesn't bode particularly well for our use of the ORM &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.subsidyscope.com"&gt;at work&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last night I shoved the data it into a barebones MySQL database and added a few convenience columns to make it easier to work with the embedded time and date information. The scripts I used to do this take a little while to run (a few hours, perhaps, on the index-creation step — this could doubtless be sped up by moving the math into the SQL itself). And my use of MySQL is somewhat dumb, as the GIS capabilities of Postgres make it a more obvious choice. But if you're just looking to get started with this stuff, this will at least save you from having to write the CREATE TABLE statements yourself. It's all up on GitHub — &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://github.com/sbma44/py-gtfs-mysql/tree/master"&gt;have at it&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next step for me is to generate a second-by-second snapshot of where every bus in the city is throughout the day, then feed that into &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://processing.org"&gt;Processing&lt;/a&gt; to make a movie like &lt;a class="reference external" href="/2008/05/22/i-made-a-movie/"&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;. Maybe I'll even add a soundtrack this time — anybody feel like doing some field recordings of Metrobuses?&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC, tech"/></entry><entry><title>Metro and Google</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/12/16/metro-and-google/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-12-16T15:01:00-05:00</published><updated>2008-12-16T15:01:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-12-16:/2008/12/16/metro-and-google/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Let's talk about Metro's recent decision to eschew Google Transit. This is a topic about which I have a small amount of inside knowledge, actually. At the end of August I wrote to WMATA's CTO, Suzanne Peck. I talked about some of the projects I'd done with WMATA data and …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Let's talk about Metro's recent decision to eschew Google Transit. This is a topic about which I have a small amount of inside knowledge, actually. At the end of August I wrote to WMATA's CTO, Suzanne Peck. I talked about some of the projects I'd done with WMATA data and expressed my affection for the agency. I explained that I was frustrated by the limits of the data available on wmata.com, and I requested a meeting. I received a response almost immediately (even though it was 11pm or so — a good sign in a CTO!). She thanked me for my interest, complimented me on my projects and directed me to Victor Grimes, her deputy, whom she instructed to meet with me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I met with Mr. Grimes a week or two later. He was cordial but not too interested in what I had to say about opening up WMATA's data: according to him, the situation was well in hand. WMATA was already on its way to integrating with Google Transit. There were just a few lingering problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To discuss those properly, we first need to talk briefly about Google Transit. The heart of Google's system is their &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://code.google.com/transit/spec/transit_feed_specification.html"&gt;GTFS format&lt;/a&gt; — this stands for Google Transit Feed Specification, and it's quickly become an industry standard. It's not too complicated: basically a GTFS feed consists of a bunch of comma-delimited files with names like &amp;quot;routes.txt&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;stops.txt&amp;quot;, which all get zipped up into one file and placed on the transit agency's website. You could open these up in Excel if you wanted. Google sucks this data down once a week or so, processes it and displays it within their own systems — but a transit agency doesn't have to worry about all that. They just need to make sure they get their GTFS file right, and that Google knows where to find it. Many other systems have adopted GTFS, and a lot of them make the data &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.bart.gov/schedules/developers/open.aspx"&gt;available to the public&lt;/a&gt;, not just to Google.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The frequency with which Google picks up the GTFS data was an issue, according to Mr. Grimes. Google wanted to do it about once a week; that wouldn't cut it for Metro, he said. WMATA updates its data daily with bus detours, route changes and the like. It sounded like this had been worked out, though, and Google would simply arrange to pull the data every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second objection involved the display of fare information. Google Transit couldn't manage this, apparently. The format does &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://code.google.com/transit/spec/transit_feed_specification.html#fare_rules_txt___Field_Definitions"&gt;make allowances&lt;/a&gt; for transferring fare information, but for whatever reason it wasn't up to the task of handling WMATA fares. That was fine, though; users could just be directed to the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.wmata.com/rider_tools/tripplanner/tripplanner_form_solo.cfm"&gt;RideGuide&lt;/a&gt; website if they wanted to know fare information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The final hurdle was bureaucratic. The various jurisdictions that make up Metro had to sign off on the release of the (already public) data. Last I heard, Maryland was the holdup. But Mr. Grimes thought this would be resolved soon. The GTFS dataset and Google Transit functionality would be released around September 23, he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, that didn't happen. I gave it a week, then wrote to ask what had happened. Here's the last I've heard, received on October 10:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Anyway, the Google/WMATA transit integration project has come to a stand still for reasons I can't explain, but I expect things to get back on track in the near future. We are having a meeting to discuss our participation in the Google transit initiative next week and I'll let you know how that turns out.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presumably that meeting didn't go very well. &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.welovedc.com/2008/12/16/wmata-says-no-to-google-transit/"&gt;We Love DC spots WMATA's explanation&lt;/a&gt; — it comes in the form of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.wmata.com/about_metro/news/faqs/preview.cfm?faqID=54"&gt;a FAQ page&lt;/a&gt; put online yesterday, seemingly in effort to control the fallout surrounding their decision to ditch Google. Here's the meat of it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Google could not guarantee accurate and up-to-date Metro trip information and could not provide Metro fare information. Metro's own Web site provides near real-time travel and fare information to viewers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many transit providers in the region are not part of Google Transit so Google's Web site viewers could not get a complete and accurate picture of their transit travel options in the Washington Metropolitan area when they use Google Transit. Metro has partnered with all the local transit providers in the Washington region to provide up-to-date and accurate information for Metro's Trip Planner. The Trip Planner factors in other area bus and rail providers, such as Fairfax Connector, DASH, ART and Ride On, and their schedules and fare information when giving customers travel options.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Metro and Google have not yet come to acceptable terms regarding licensing agreements, which put Metro at a greater legal liability. Google is a for-profit company while Metro is a taxpayer subsidized public agency. Google wanted Metro's transit data at no cost and wanted the transit agency to open itself up to greater legal liability. Given financial constraints, Metro officials are exploring whether there is a way for the transit agency to generate revenue in such a partnership.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think we can safely dismiss the second point — hearing about the ART bus might be nice, but it's hardly a sufficient reason for scrapping this project. Based on my conversation with Mr. Grimes, I also think point one is probably a red herring. Those limitations were known in August, and they weren't considered show-stoppers then. I suppose Google may have ultimately decided that they couldn't support a daily GTFS update, but this seems very unlikely to me — the Metro system is big, this technical problem is small, and enough people would find this integration useful that I'm sure they'd find a way to support it. I suppose point one could also be interpreted to mean that WMATA was insisting on some sort of service level/data accuracy guarantee that Google couldn't or wouldn't provide, but insisting on such a point seems a bit unreasonable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that leaves us with point three, which basically boils down to: Google needs to cough up some dough. I'm actually a bit more sympathetic to this idea than you might expect. &amp;quot;Google Transit Feed Specification&amp;quot; sure &lt;em&gt;sounds&lt;/em&gt; like a proprietary format. It's easy to imagine a bureaucrat with sign-off powers seeing that and saying, &amp;quot;Wait a minute. We're doing all this work for a private enterprise and they're not even paying us for it?&amp;quot; Google is an awfully helpful company, but presumably it's offering transit information because it makes them money (or at least supports their brand). WMATA's in perpetual need of cash; there's no reason it should be giving Google freebies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this misses the larger point. GTFS may be unfortunately eponymous, but it's an open format. Exposing schedule data in useful ways should be part of WMATA's mandate — the current system of bulky PDFs used for bus schedules is downright inexcusable. I don't particularly care whether WMATA lets private firms like Google use its data for commercial ends, but it should certainly grant noncommercial rights to the public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;THIS JUST IN:&lt;/strong&gt; More from Mr. Grimes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Yes, there is still an issue between WMATA and Google regarding the licensing agreement. However, we are in continuing discussions with Google and looking at other options for making the data available in GTFS format not only to Google but to others who have requested the information. You are correct in that much consideration has been given to this effort and it is not over. I will let you know as soon as a decision has been made regarding the direction WMATA will take to provide the transit data in GTFS format.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dcist.com/2008/12/16/google_transit_here_come_the_excuse.php"&gt;via DCist&lt;/a&gt; the Examiner &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.dcexaminer.com/local/Metro_involvement_with_Google_Transit_held_up_by_the_details.html"&gt;confirms&lt;/a&gt; that this is really about money. Well, good. WMATA should put the GTFS dataset online under a Creative Commons noncommercial license, and Google should cough up the $68k of online ad revenue that WMATA's afraid of losing. Lord knows they've got the money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FURTHER:&lt;/strong&gt; One of Ezra's commenters &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.prospect.org/csnc/blogs/ezraklein_archive?month=12&amp;amp;year=2008&amp;amp;base_name=google_and_the_dc_metro#comment-6243029"&gt;points out&lt;/a&gt; that Google Transit isn't actually all that great. I'm not that familiar with it, but I'm not too surprised — it's a hard problem. But even if Google can't do it, someone else can.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also: it's worth mentioning that the real payoff here is for buses. Figuring out how to ride the train is dead simple; the bus, not so much. Right now it's easy for people to read the PDF bus schedules, but hard for them to figure out what the schedule means (or which schedule is the correct one); these difficulties are reversed for computers. If WMATA releases the GTFS dataset, riding the bus could become much easier for a lot of people.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC, tech"/></entry><entry><title>I made a movie</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/05/22/i-made-a-movie/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-05-22T11:45:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-05-22T11:45:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-05-22:/2008/05/22/i-made-a-movie/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Inspired by &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.flight404.com/blog"&gt;Robert Hodgin&lt;/a&gt;'s &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.flight404.com/blog/?p=121"&gt;impressive work&lt;/a&gt;, I decided I wanted to take a crack at making animations in Processing. Inspired by &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://goodspeedupdate.com/"&gt;Rob Goodspeed&lt;/a&gt;'s thoughtful experiments, I figured I might as well try to make it about something interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The DC &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dcstat.octo.dc.gov/dcstat/site/default.asp?dcstatNav=%7C30914%7C"&gt;Office of the CTO&lt;/a&gt; makes a lot of …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Inspired by &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.flight404.com/blog"&gt;Robert Hodgin&lt;/a&gt;'s &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.flight404.com/blog/?p=121"&gt;impressive work&lt;/a&gt;, I decided I wanted to take a crack at making animations in Processing. Inspired by &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://goodspeedupdate.com/"&gt;Rob Goodspeed&lt;/a&gt;'s thoughtful experiments, I figured I might as well try to make it about something interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The DC &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dcstat.octo.dc.gov/dcstat/site/default.asp?dcstatNav=%7C30914%7C"&gt;Office of the CTO&lt;/a&gt; makes a lot of interesting data available, so I decided to take a crack at doing something with it. Here's my first pass: it's a visualization of every reported crime incident in 2007.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blue means property crime — robbery, larceny, etc. Red means violence — assaults, murders and the like. Green means sex crimes. The color-coding is obviously less than perfect, but is at least sort of interesting. Each frame in the video represents 8 hours — one police shift. Colors gradually fade to a dark, translucent gray after two weeks' worth of time has elapsed. You can view a larger version of this video by clicking through to the movie's &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://vimeo.com/1049199"&gt;Vimeo page&lt;/a&gt;, and an even better-quality version by then scrolling down to the lower right for a Quicktime download link. You'll need to log in or create a Vimeo account for the Quicktime — but you should! Vimeo is the best videosharing site I've used by a mile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the moment I'm trying to figure out where I should go from this point. A few ideas:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add graphs and a calendar display to help users see the relative levels of crime over the course of the movie&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identify and place a street map under the crime visualization&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Produce a static, high-resolution render showing the differences in location of crime between 2007 and 2008 (YTD)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do it all over again with the city's pothole data (also geocoded!)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Add a jaunty soundtrack&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have any other suggestions, please let me know. Those of you interested in the geeky details should keep an eye on &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://labs.echoditto.com"&gt;EchoDitto Labs&lt;/a&gt; — if I can find time I'll be posting an accounting of the tools I used over there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;City-mandated disclaimer after the jump&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
The data made available here has been modified for use from its original source, which is the Government of the District of Columbia. Neither the District of Columbia Government nor the Office of the Chief Technology Officer (OCTO) makes any claims as to the completeness, accuracy or content of any data contained in this application; makes any representation of any kind, including, but not limited to, warranty of the accuracy or fitness for a particular use; nor are any such warranties to be implied or inferred with respect to the information or data furnished herein. The data is subject to change as modifications and updates are complete. It is understood that the information contained in the dataset is being used at one's own risk&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content><category term="DC, tech"/></entry><entry><title>Dorkbot DC: Arduino, Meet Fonera</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/03/26/dorkbot-dc-arduino-meet-fonera/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-03-26T12:05:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-03-26T12:05:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-03-26:/2008/03/26/dorkbot-dc-arduino-meet-fonera/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Whew! Well, I presented last night at Dorkbot and it seemed to go pretty well. Thanks to Gareth, Alberto and everyone else who makes Dorkbot possible. Alberto was particularly helpful and encouraging, and I greatly appreciate it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As promised I've got an audio recording of the talk to share, as …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Whew! Well, I presented last night at Dorkbot and it seemed to go pretty well. Thanks to Gareth, Alberto and everyone else who makes Dorkbot possible. Alberto was particularly helpful and encouraging, and I greatly appreciate it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As promised I've got an audio recording of the talk to share, as well as a PDF of my slides and some Arduino and Ruby code. I haven't yet taken any really good photos of my project, but once I do I'll add some links to them here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those just wandering in: I spoke about using a router with a custom firmware as a way of adding wireless internet access (and more!) to your Arduino project. In particular I used the Fonera router, which is especially ubiquitous and cheap. Once you've got a custom firmware loaded you can use a simple serial link to make the router speak to your Arduino and relay whatever internet goodness you might like. I used this functionality to create an ambient display that talks to the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.wmata.com/tripplanner_d/TripPlanner_Form_Solo.cfm"&gt;WMATA website&lt;/a&gt; via wifi and uses a couple of needle gauges and LEDs to tell me when the next bus and train will be arriving at the stops nearest my apartment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dorkbot DC: Arduino, Meet Fonera&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/static/2008/03/26/dorkbot_tom_64_mono.mp3"&gt;Audio (MP3/64kbps, 11M)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/static/2008/03/26/dorkbot-tom_lee-arduino_meet_fonera.pdf"&gt;Slides (PDF, 10M)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/static/2008/03/26/bus_o_meter.pde"&gt;bus_o_meter.pde (Arduino code, 3.2k)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/static/2008/03/26/wmatarideguide.rb"&gt;wmatarideguide.rb (Ruby class, 1.6k)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rest of the project code is available inside the slides. You can find some useful hyperlinks in there, too, as well as my email address.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE:&lt;/strong&gt; The original version of the Arduino project code uploaded here contained a number of critical bugs. I've replaced it with a more complete version, but it should still be considered a work in progress.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC, tech"/></entry><entry><title>check me out</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/03/17/check-me-out/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-03-17T13:30:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-03-17T13:30:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-03-17:/2008/03/17/check-me-out/</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm going to be presenting at the next &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dorkbot.org/dorkbotdc/"&gt;Dorkbot DC&lt;/a&gt;, and I'm pretty excited about it. If you're free a week from Wednesday why not come down to GW and listen to folks get excited about DIY hardware?&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC, tech"/></entry><entry><title>dorkbot DC</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2007/09/10/dorkbot-dc/" rel="alternate"/><published>2007-09-10T22:58:00-04:00</published><updated>2007-09-10T22:58:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2007-09-10:/2007/09/10/dorkbot-dc/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I finally made it to a meeting. In brief: loquacious audience members ignorant of the limits of technology; presenters that were, if anything, too aware of them. But the disconnected dynamic was partly the fault of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.koshlandscience.org/visitor/dandp.jsp"&gt;the space&lt;/a&gt;, which — despite providing a &amp;quot;WONDERS OF SCIENCE&amp;quot; banner above the podium — didn't …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I finally made it to a meeting. In brief: loquacious audience members ignorant of the limits of technology; presenters that were, if anything, too aware of them. But the disconnected dynamic was partly the fault of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.koshlandscience.org/visitor/dandp.jsp"&gt;the space&lt;/a&gt;, which — despite providing a &amp;quot;WONDERS OF SCIENCE&amp;quot; banner above the podium — didn't prove to be a particularly great setting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, there were some interesting projects, I got pointed toward some &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Simulated_annealing"&gt;interesting&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.lantronix.com/device-networking/embedded-device-servers/xport.html"&gt;things&lt;/a&gt;, and I'll be going back.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC, tech"/></entry><entry><title>Twitter evangelism, take two</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2007/08/03/twitter-evangelism-take-two/" rel="alternate"/><published>2007-08-03T11:47:00-04:00</published><updated>2007-08-03T11:47:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2007-08-03:/2007/08/03/twitter-evangelism-take-two/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I gave Twitter a try back around SXSWi. I liked it, but it posed a couple of problems. First, I ended up getting so many SMSes that it made my phone significantly less useful. Second, the messages were typically from acquaintances on the west coast — nobody in DC used it …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I gave Twitter a try back around SXSWi. I liked it, but it posed a couple of problems. First, I ended up getting so many SMSes that it made my phone significantly less useful. Second, the messages were typically from acquaintances on the west coast — nobody in DC used it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that's all changed. I finally installed &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://growl.info/"&gt;Growl&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://iconfactory.com/software/twitterrific"&gt;Twitterific&lt;/a&gt;, which allow me to see my friends' updates in tasteful, unobtrusive windows in the upper right of my screen. &amp;quot;Ambient intimacy&amp;quot; is the phrase the Twitter people use, and it's just about right — I really do like knowing that &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.al3x.net"&gt;al3x&lt;/a&gt; just had a sub-par bagel, or that &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.strangebirdlabs.com/"&gt;Rich&lt;/a&gt; found an awesome new software tool. And Yglesias and Ezra have started using it with gusto, providing content relevant to my life in DC and encouraging me to respond in kind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I'm a Twitter born-again, I suppose, and have even gone so far as to install a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://twitter.com/badges"&gt;badge&lt;/a&gt; in the sidebar, which is the web services equivalent of going steady. If any of this sounds intriguing, maybe you should give it a shot, too. Which is my long-winded way of saying: come entertain me, dammit.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC, tech"/></entry><entry><title>meaningful applications for technology</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2007/07/18/meaningful-applications-for-technology/" rel="alternate"/><published>2007-07-18T16:28:00-04:00</published><updated>2007-07-18T16:28:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2007-07-18:/2007/07/18/meaningful-applications-for-technology/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ezraklein.typepad.com/blog/2007/07/hot-or-not-nerd.html"&gt;Thanks for the reminder, Ezra&lt;/a&gt;! Man, I can't believe it's been a whole year since MediaBistro's last &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.mediabistro.com/fishbowlDC/hottest_media_types/fishbowldcs_2006_hottest_media_types_the_voting_41396.asp"&gt;DC journo beauty pageant&lt;/a&gt;. As you may recall, last year's contest featured a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://mediabistro.com/articles/poll/000091/result.asp"&gt;stunning come-from-behind victory&lt;/a&gt; — one that unfortunately didn't count due to the deciding surge of democratic expression occurring in the 24 …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ezraklein.typepad.com/blog/2007/07/hot-or-not-nerd.html"&gt;Thanks for the reminder, Ezra&lt;/a&gt;! Man, I can't believe it's been a whole year since MediaBistro's last &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.mediabistro.com/fishbowlDC/hottest_media_types/fishbowldcs_2006_hottest_media_types_the_voting_41396.asp"&gt;DC journo beauty pageant&lt;/a&gt;. As you may recall, last year's contest featured a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://mediabistro.com/articles/poll/000091/result.asp"&gt;stunning come-from-behind victory&lt;/a&gt; — one that unfortunately didn't count due to the deciding surge of democratic expression occurring in the 24 hours after voting closed. This in turn can be attributed to the parties responsible for the outpouring of support accidentally misreading the end date of the contest. I bet they felt pretty stupid about that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But don't worry! I'm confident that democracy will triumph this year.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC, tech"/></entry><entry><title>better Google Maps/Metro integration</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2007/07/12/better-google-mapsmetro-integration/" rel="alternate"/><published>2007-07-12T20:23:00-04:00</published><updated>2007-07-12T20:23:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2007-07-12:/2007/07/12/better-google-mapsmetro-integration/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Tech project the first!: I've revisited my venerable &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.dcist.com/map"&gt;DCist Map&lt;/a&gt; project and ported it over to Google Mapplets — a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.techcrunch.com/2007/07/11/google-to-launch-my-maps/"&gt;just-launched&lt;/a&gt; feature that lets you add user-contributed mashups to your Google Map display in a wholly integrated way. This lets you do all kinds of neat stuff. For example, you can …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Tech project the first!: I've revisited my venerable &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.dcist.com/map"&gt;DCist Map&lt;/a&gt; project and ported it over to Google Mapplets — a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.techcrunch.com/2007/07/11/google-to-launch-my-maps/"&gt;just-launched&lt;/a&gt; feature that lets you add user-contributed mashups to your Google Map display in a wholly integrated way. This lets you do all kinds of neat stuff. For example, you can turn on a crime overlay by checking the &amp;quot;crime overlay&amp;quot; box. Then you could compare area muggings to gas prices by clicking the &amp;quot;gas price&amp;quot; checkbox. You'll be revolutionizing sociology in no time!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've dusted off my code and ported it to the Mapplet version of the GMaps API, which actually entailed porting it to the GMaps v2 API first. It's nice of them to have finally un-switched latitude and longitude, but it made things kind of a pain in the ass for me. Still, it's nice to have it done and the tool up-to-date. Oh, and while I was at it I finally extended the yellow line up to Ft. Totten, as I should've long ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've submitted the mapplet to Google's directory, but who knows when or if they'll add it. For now, if you want to add it to your &amp;quot;My Maps&amp;quot; toolbox, you can do so in the following way. You'll only have to do this once, then it should sit happily in your sidebar, waiting for you to toggle it on whenever you need it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://maps.google.com/maps/mm?mapprev=1"&gt;Launch the mapplet-enabled version of Google Maps&lt;/a&gt; (it's still in beta).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click on &amp;quot;Add content&amp;quot; in the upper left of the &amp;quot;My Maps&amp;quot; section.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To the right of the search bar at the top of this page is a tiny little link that says &amp;quot;Add by URL&amp;quot;. Click it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enter &amp;quot;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dcist.com/map/mapplet.xml"&gt;http://dcist.com/map/mapplet.xml&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;. Note the lack of www! The Gothamist folks have set up the hostname to redirect to the www-less version, but Google isn't smart enough to handle that. Enter it like this and you'll be fine. Click &amp;quot;Add&amp;quot;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Say &amp;quot;OK&amp;quot; to the security warning that'll pop up. Trust me, I'm a nice guy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Follow the &amp;quot;Back to Google Maps&amp;quot; link in the upper left of the screen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That's it! You should have a new item in the &amp;quot;My Maps&amp;quot; section. Check the box next to it and the metro overlay will be activated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll write up a post for DCist about this tomorrow (or maybe I'll wait to see if it's accepted into the directory). But I thought I'd put it up here first, so that you guys can give it a try and let me know if you run into any horrible problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE:&lt;/strong&gt; One other interesting side-effect: this makes it easy to see where Google and I disagree about a Metro station's location. In most cases this is because the station has multiple entrances; I usually went with whichever one was most visible. In others its because of different standards: I generally used the satellite view to find the platform and geocoded that (yeah, I did them all manually). Google appears to use street entrances. I'd consider redoing them, but it'd mostly be for pride — having both on there is (arguably) the best solution.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC, tech"/></entry></feed>