<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Tom Lee - DC</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/feeds/dc.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>https://tomlee.wtf/</id><updated>2009-03-22T14:57:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>making excuses</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2009/03/22/making-excuses/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-03-22T14:57:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-03-22T14:57:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2009-03-22:/2009/03/22/making-excuses/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.grammarpolice.net"&gt;Kriston&lt;/a&gt; asked &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.ryanavent.com"&gt;Ryan&lt;/a&gt; and me to write about &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.washingtonian.com/print/articles/6/174/11722.html"&gt;Larry Van Dyne's article on historic preservation&lt;/a&gt; for DCist. This was at least half of a good idea: Ryan always has interesting things to say about the business of running cities. And for my part, I imagine Kriston was counting on me …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.grammarpolice.net"&gt;Kriston&lt;/a&gt; asked &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.ryanavent.com"&gt;Ryan&lt;/a&gt; and me to write about &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.washingtonian.com/print/articles/6/174/11722.html"&gt;Larry Van Dyne's article on historic preservation&lt;/a&gt; for DCist. This was at least half of a good idea: Ryan always has interesting things to say about the business of running cities. And for my part, I imagine Kriston was counting on me to bring my own trademark brand of techno-philistinism (&amp;quot;Why preserve buildings when we can just make models of them in Second Life?&amp;quot;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The joke's on him, though. The past couple of years' worth of Ryan's writing have been so convincing that whatever opinions I may have originally had on these matters have been almost entirely replaced with his — this happens an embarrassing amount when you have smart friends who write a lot. I'm afraid that the essay I produced is consequently just a half-baked version of the one that Ryan wrote. On the upside, I was glad to see Ryan take the potshot at the FBI building that I'd barely restrained myself from making (it's &lt;em&gt;so awful&lt;/em&gt;). So really, he wins on all fronts — &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dcist.com/2009/03/two_takes_ryan_avent_on_historic_pr.php"&gt;go have a read&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC"/></entry><entry><title>there's an inauguration going on or something</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2009/01/20/theres-an-inauguration-going-on-or-something/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-01-20T14:26:00-05:00</published><updated>2009-01-20T14:26:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2009-01-20:/2009/01/20/theres-an-inauguration-going-on-or-something/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I didn't go downtown this morning. Getting anywhere even potentially worth being seemed to require a very early start, and although &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.unfogged.com"&gt;Becks&lt;/a&gt;' promise of a delicious pre-inaugural spread was tempting, I opted out. I'd gotten up before dawn the day before in order to catch a flight, making me even …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I didn't go downtown this morning. Getting anywhere even potentially worth being seemed to require a very early start, and although &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.unfogged.com"&gt;Becks&lt;/a&gt;' promise of a delicious pre-inaugural spread was tempting, I opted out. I'd gotten up before dawn the day before in order to catch a flight, making me even less inclined than normal to wake up early. Instead I woke up around 10, made some coffee and french toast, then plopped down in front of the TV. Honestly, I think this was the way to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did head out on my bike around 1, though, to see what things were like around town. I made a rough circle down to Chinatown, over to Freedom Plaza, up Fourteenth, across U, then back down Eleventh. The verdict: there are a lot of people here! They all seem excited to bustle about and enjoy the historic occasion, but there's no comparison to &lt;a class="reference external" href="/2008/11/05/between-the-click-of-the-light-and-the-start-of-the-dream/"&gt;the emotion that flooded the streets on election night&lt;/a&gt;. I guess for that sort of joyousness to spread to the daylight hours we'd need to be transitioning from an even worse president than Bush to an even more trailblazing and exciting one than Obama. Like, say, a resurrected Freddie Mercury succeeding a two-term Palpatine administration. Well, fingers crossed!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You'll be glad to know that I took some crappy pictures with my iphone:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/sbma44/3213516732/"&gt;&lt;img alt="water damage rOBAMAration service" class="center" src="http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3108/3213516732_c66c13977a.jpg" style="width: 500px; height: 375px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gallery Place was ground zero for nonsensical Obama paraphernalia, including this plumber's truck with photos of the new president plastered on it. Despite the street being closed, a cop yelled at me for stopping my bike to take this photo, and then again when I took five seconds to begin moving. Ah, officiousness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/sbma44/3212671461/"&gt;&lt;img alt="Fourteenth Street" class="center" src="http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3425/3212671461_2b8f635c78.jpg" style="width: 375px; height: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fourteenth had stalls set up, but aside from folks queued to get into the perimeter around the mall, it wasn't too flooded with people. It was pretty fun to bike through the closed streets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's an Obama ice sculpture outside of Ben's. And yeah, the line still goes down the alley:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/sbma44/3212636453/"&gt;&lt;img alt="Obama ice sculpture outside of Ben's" class="center" src="http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3308/3212636453_0df63ec757.jpg" style="width: 500px; height: 375px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MOST EXCITINGLY: I'm pretty sure I saw Matthew Lesko walking down my street as I returned home. I mean, okay, it could have been someone else. But whoever it was, he was wearing a leather jacket emblazoned with question marks, pants with question marks on the back pocket, a question mark hat, and ludicrous shoes (which seem likely to have also involved punctuation symbols of one sort or another).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/sbma44/3213479890/"&gt;&lt;img alt="Lesko at ease" class="center" src="http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3319/3213479890_7b5af81d07.jpg" style="width: 500px; height: 375px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC"/></entry><entry><title>prescience</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/12/30/prescience/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-12-30T12:07:00-05:00</published><updated>2008-12-30T12:07:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-12-30:/2008/12/30/prescience/</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I think &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dccharles.blogspot.com"&gt;Charles&lt;/a&gt; has this just about right:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
I am predicting that in a year the New York Times will write one of those irritating &amp;quot;look, things sometimes happen outside of our city&amp;quot; articles about DC theater/art scene. They will attribute the increase in quality to Obama.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</content><category term="DC"/></entry><entry><title>it's fun to bray at the...</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/12/11/its-fun-to-bray-at-the/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-12-11T21:17:00-05:00</published><updated>2008-12-11T21:17:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-12-11:/2008/12/11/its-fun-to-bray-at-the/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Alright, enough of this &amp;quot;saying nice things about employers&amp;quot; nonsense. That's not what the internet is about! It's about complaining, goddammit. So let's do some of that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To wit: the YMCA. Man, I really like the YMCA. I grew up going to one with my family; once I moved into …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Alright, enough of this &amp;quot;saying nice things about employers&amp;quot; nonsense. That's not what the internet is about! It's about complaining, goddammit. So let's do some of that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To wit: the YMCA. Man, I really like the YMCA. I grew up going to one with my family; once I moved into the city I joined the National Capital Y pretty quickly. It's not the cheapest or best-appointed gym out there, but I find the atmosphere congenial. Everything's old: from the unused wall nozzles that powered pneumatic equipment back in the day; to the inch-thick layer of paint on the walls; to the patrons themselves, who wander about the locker room naked while endlessly discussing squash (whatever that is). The skeptical, tentative, ever-inconclusive conversations among themerely-fiftyish men offer a glimpse into the bureaucratic lifestyle that's hard to find anywhere else. It's not exciting, but it's an essential part of this city, goddammit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But they've invited my wrath. Two things. First: when I signed up, they corralled me into some sort of reverse direct deposit business. I hate doing these things because I'm paranoid about giving companies the keys to my checking account. And hey, guess what? I got a letter from the Y, and I (&lt;a class="reference external" href="/2007/08/20/admitting-defeat/"&gt;somewhat improbably&lt;/a&gt;) opened it, and they had decided to help themselves to an extra $25 or $50 or whatever. Times are tough, you know. They were sure I wouldn't mind. They just took it out from the larger wad of money, I probably wouldn't even notice, and besides they needed it for cigarettes so they could smoke with the seniors at lunch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This left me feeling rather cross, and the reaction from the folks at the front desk (&amp;quot;it's only $25&amp;quot;) only buttressed my righteous indignation. But further indignities laid in wait.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Kickball. They're hosting kickball again this winter. Not that I remember them ever having done so before, but the signs in the hallway claim they did. Perhaps we have always been at war with kickball; I don't really know. I do know that this fills the hallways with clots of drunk or soon-to-be-drunk assholes, who whoop and don't get out of my way even when I say &amp;quot;excuse me&amp;quot; (admittedly through gritted teeth and a facial expression designed to drive the observer to suicide). It's a bad situation, and if you ask me, pretty disrespectful of the Y's dues-paying members, all of whom detest the kickballers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should say: I know people who play kickball who I like very much. That's the social scene they found themselves in, and so they play kickball. I can't fault them for that. Hell, my ancestors owned slaves — we're all victims of our milieu. Further, I understand perfectly well the need to invent flimsy social pretexts to justify increasingly worrying levels of post-graduation alcohol consumption. But most people don't conduct their writing workshops or networking events or connoisseurship rituals in the hallway leading to the fifth floor weight room — that's the key difference, I think. Kickball has got to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The combination of the two is especially galling. Kickball's awash in money — you can tell because the idiots responsible &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dcist.com/2008/08/05/kickball_lawsuit_finally_strikes_ou.php"&gt;keep trying to sue each other&lt;/a&gt;. This is a for-profit enterprise that's wormed its drunken way into my quasi-charitable dues-based fitness club. And yet on top of the imposition-for-cash, they &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; need to steal from me? It's a bit much. The first time I run into people playing flipcup in the locker room I'm going to wind up killing somebody.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC"/></entry><entry><title>oof</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/09/15/oof/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-09-15T12:53:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-09-15T12:53:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-09-15:/2008/09/15/oof/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I haven't really followed the local sports media much over the past couple of years. The last time I regularly checked in, Wilbon was still handling quite a bit of the paper's Redskins columns, and it was clear that he was intensely bored by it. A professional disdain for home …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I haven't really followed the local sports media much over the past couple of years. The last time I regularly checked in, Wilbon was still handling quite a bit of the paper's Redskins columns, and it was clear that he was intensely bored by it. A professional disdain for home team jingoism and fatigue from the formulaic but necessary cycle of columns that a bad local franchise necessitates combined to produce columns that were mostly about how much he hated writing them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I figured the turnover since then would have improved things, but &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/09/14/AR2008091402428_pf.html"&gt;holy crap is today's Mike Wise column a piece of garbage&lt;/a&gt;. It's like he was having a competition with his colleagues to see how many sentence fragments he could get past their editor. Also, take a moment and contemplate the horror of the phrase &amp;quot;and who this team really cannot get the ball enough to&amp;quot;. Is it possible to write that clause any more awkwardly? Did anyone even read this before it went to the presses?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realize that many sports reporters get bored with sports. That's probably inevitable. But it's still a pretty cushy job — show at least a &lt;em&gt;little&lt;/em&gt; effort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;HMM:&lt;/strong&gt; Charles tells me that he thinks Mike Wise ran a triathlon on the day that he had to write that column. If so, its quality is a bit more understandable. Presumably his editor was similarly indisposed (boxing match?).&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC"/></entry><entry><title>it's mostly architectural controversies, but I hear they lend books, too</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/08/14/its-mostly-architectural-controversies-but-i-hear-they-lend-books-too/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-08-14T11:01:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-08-14T11:01:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-08-14:/2008/08/14/its-mostly-architectural-controversies-but-i-hear-they-lend-books-too/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Interesting developments on the Logan Circle listserv! Apparently the new Shaw library has been going through a design process since January, at which time residents were shown this design:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://www.districtdynamos.org/dynamos/shaw/library_evolution"&gt;&lt;img alt="image1" class="center" src="/static/2008/08/14/oldshawlibrary-20080814-110156.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They liked it! But now months have passed, and somehow the project has changed into this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://www.districtdynamos.org/dynamos/shaw/library_evolution"&gt;&lt;img alt="image2" class="center" src="/static/2008/08/14/skitched-20080814-110246.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It certainly looks, um, more …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Interesting developments on the Logan Circle listserv! Apparently the new Shaw library has been going through a design process since January, at which time residents were shown this design:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://www.districtdynamos.org/dynamos/shaw/library_evolution"&gt;&lt;img alt="image1" class="center" src="/static/2008/08/14/oldshawlibrary-20080814-110156.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They liked it! But now months have passed, and somehow the project has changed into this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://www.districtdynamos.org/dynamos/shaw/library_evolution"&gt;&lt;img alt="image2" class="center" src="/static/2008/08/14/skitched-20080814-110246.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It certainly looks, um, more... frugal? Maybe those who know something about architecture will be able to defend it on the merits. I don't know anything about these matters, but I can see how some might think the earlier, prettier design is less &lt;em&gt;interesting&lt;/em&gt;. Or maybe the second one really is the trainwreck it appears to be.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC"/></entry><entry><title>they're on to us, comrade</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/08/13/theyre-on-to-us-comrade/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-08-13T17:17:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-08-13T17:17:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-08-13:/2008/08/13/theyre-on-to-us-comrade/</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A comment left on a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://voices.washingtonpost.com/rawfisher/2008/08/you_can_ride_one_mayor_fentys.html"&gt;Raw Fisher post about the city's new bikesharing program&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image1" class="center" src="http://www.manifestdensity.net/skitch/You_Can_Ride_One_of_Mayor_Fenty_s_Bicycles_%28But_not_the_really_good_one%29_-_Raw_Fisher-20080813-171729.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC"/></entry><entry><title>bitching about townhouse</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/08/05/bitching-about-townhouse/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-08-05T14:16:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-08-05T14:16:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-08-05:/2008/08/05/bitching-about-townhouse/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Lord knows we need all the tolerable bars in DC we can get, but last night's experience is making me want to write off Townhouse Tavern. We ended up there with a larger-than-expected and somewhat unwieldy group, but arrived early and had secured chairs for everybody outside. After an hour …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Lord knows we need all the tolerable bars in DC we can get, but last night's experience is making me want to write off Townhouse Tavern. We ended up there with a larger-than-expected and somewhat unwieldy group, but arrived early and had secured chairs for everybody outside. After an hour or so one of our party went a few feet up the street to take a call. When the bartender came to clear empties he pushed the guy's chair a bit out of the way, making it look like it belonged to a different, unoccupied table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some new arrivals approached another table out front that had folks around it, and one of them grabbed the now-slightly-displaced chair. We tried to explain that it was spoken for, but the guy who had snagged it just ignored us. Emily politely tapped him on the shoulder and explained the situation again, but he continued to blow us off, not even bothering to make eye contact. One of his group found the whole thing funny, and asked us incredulously if we realized that the chair-taker owned the bar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, hell, did he? My gullibility is well-established, but it actually seems pretty possible to me: the bartenders were hanging out with their table all night, and the guy certainly carried an attitude of entitlement sufficient to mark him as a proprietor. If so, man, what a lousy way to treat your customers. I left that place pretty pissed off, and am sorry to have had a chip placed on my shoulder about what is, like I said, one of the few endurable bars in DC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suppose when you buy a place like Townhouse a large part of your motivation is a desire to host your friends exactly how and when you want. I can understand that. But it's tough to want to put money in the pocket of someone who treats you like garbage, regardless of how nice his bartenders are. Hopefully somebody'll pipe up and tell me that no, there's no way that was the owner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;KRISTON TO THE RESCUE:&lt;/strong&gt; Mr. Capps, a good friend to me and Townhouse both, writes with assurances that the TH owner is considerably taller, beardier and more Scottish than the thoroughly dude-like dude who behaved so poorly toward us. Sounds like it was just a bunch of regulars with delusions of grandeur. Good.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC"/></entry><entry><title>it's that time of year...</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/07/30/its-that-time-of-year/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-07-30T09:28:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-07-30T09:28:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-07-30:/2008/07/30/its-that-time-of-year/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Don't miss &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dceiver.blogspot.com/2008/07/highlights-from-hill-hotties-2008.html"&gt;Jason's annual commentary&lt;/a&gt; on the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://hill6.thehill.com/cover-stories/50-most-beautiful-people-on-capitol-hill-2008---top-10-2008-07-29.html"&gt;Hill Hotties list&lt;/a&gt;. My favorite line:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&amp;quot;Rep. Gresham Barrett (R-S.C.) is proof positive that a high school quarterback can marry his cheerleader girlfriend and live happily ever after.&amp;quot; Phew! Glad that's been proven! It's certainly an improvement over the quarterback who was …&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Don't miss &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dceiver.blogspot.com/2008/07/highlights-from-hill-hotties-2008.html"&gt;Jason's annual commentary&lt;/a&gt; on the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://hill6.thehill.com/cover-stories/50-most-beautiful-people-on-capitol-hill-2008---top-10-2008-07-29.html"&gt;Hill Hotties list&lt;/a&gt;. My favorite line:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&amp;quot;Rep. Gresham Barrett (R-S.C.) is proof positive that a high school quarterback can marry his cheerleader girlfriend and live happily ever after.&amp;quot; Phew! Glad that's been proven! It's certainly an improvement over the quarterback who was proof positive that being a fake cowboy moron could only take you so far if you were a crypto-racist goon (George Allen).&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other highlights:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Andrew Savage: I totally know that guy. He's good friends with &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://silbatron.com"&gt;Michael&lt;/a&gt;. I can't say I've ever seen him make any furniture, but I suppose he could have slipped off to cut decorative scrollwork while I was in the bathroom at St. Ex.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Check out Otto Mucklo, then try to tell me with a straight face that you believe the bio when it says he's not German. Otto! C'mon!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content><category term="DC"/></entry><entry><title>bye Rob!</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/07/17/bye-rob/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-07-17T12:08:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-07-17T12:08:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-07-17:/2008/07/17/bye-rob/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dcist.com/2008/07/17/goodspeed_to_boston.php"&gt;also&lt;/a&gt; sorry to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://goodspeedupdate.com/2008/2238"&gt;see Rob and Libby go&lt;/a&gt;. Not only because they're great people who I already don't see often enough, but also because this means Bostonians will suddenly get to learn fascinating new things about their city as Rob discovers, researches and writes them up — a luxury that …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dcist.com/2008/07/17/goodspeed_to_boston.php"&gt;also&lt;/a&gt; sorry to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://goodspeedupdate.com/2008/2238"&gt;see Rob and Libby go&lt;/a&gt;. Not only because they're great people who I already don't see often enough, but also because this means Bostonians will suddenly get to learn fascinating new things about their city as Rob discovers, researches and writes them up — a luxury that I've grown accustomed to having for myself over the past few years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there's solace to be had, it's that Rob's membership in this city's secret transit cabal seems unlikely to be affected. So take heart, and if you're feeling wistful, go reread my &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://goodspeedupdate.com/2007/2125"&gt;all-time favorite Goodspeed Update entry&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC"/></entry><entry><title>washcycle on jaybiking</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/07/15/washcycle-on-jaybiking/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-07-15T12:33:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-07-15T12:33:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-07-15:/2008/07/15/washcycle-on-jaybiking/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;WashCycle has a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://washcycle.typepad.com/home/2008/07/the-myth-of-the.html"&gt;good post&lt;/a&gt; on scofflaw cyclists and the outsized anger directed at them by pedestrians and drivers. It's worth &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://washcycle.typepad.com/home/2008/07/the-myth-of-the.html"&gt;reading the whole thing&lt;/a&gt;, but here's a bit about jaybiking:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;[A] better question is &amp;quot;why don't drivers 'jaydrive'?&amp;quot;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Is it because they love the law so much? Did you …&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;WashCycle has a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://washcycle.typepad.com/home/2008/07/the-myth-of-the.html"&gt;good post&lt;/a&gt; on scofflaw cyclists and the outsized anger directed at them by pedestrians and drivers. It's worth &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://washcycle.typepad.com/home/2008/07/the-myth-of-the.html"&gt;reading the whole thing&lt;/a&gt;, but here's a bit about jaybiking:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;[A] better question is &amp;quot;why don't drivers 'jaydrive'?&amp;quot;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Is it because they love the law so much? Did you skip the previous section?&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;It's because their risk/reward calculation is coming up with a different answer. And that makes sense. In a car you're several feet farther back from the intersection and you're often a foot or two lower, meaning you can't see as well (I bet those on recumbents don't jaybike as often as those on standard bikes). In a car you're in a soundproof enclosure so you have no stereoscopic hearing. And if you make a mistake you aren't as maneuverable as you are on a bike or on your feet. You can't just ditch to the sidewalk. Driver's don't jaydrive because, in their own estimation, they can't. But if they could, I'm sure they would.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Still, that doesn't explain the anger. Drivers get — I feel — irrationally angry about this. After wondering why for so long, an anthropologist friend of mine helped me to understand. Running a red light is so dangerous for cars that it isn't just illegal, it's taboo. You're breaking a social construct. Which means people find it objectionable and abhorrent. So if education is needed, maybe it's needed to explain why it's safer for cyclists to do this than for drivers.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;[...]&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;The way to end jaybiking violations is to decriminalize them. [...] Idaho has changed its law — and California is considering it — to allow cyclist to treat stop signs as yield signs and stop lights as stop signs.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I agree with all of this, although it doesn't really apply to me any more: over the past few months I've become a very, very good citizen cyclist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not that I think patiently waiting for a red light to change is making me or anyone else safer — it's just that I can't stand the thought that I might provide grist for those who whine about bicyclists' lawlessness. Besides, the instinctive anger that drivers feel upon seeing a bicyclist is no doubt that much more intense when they can't put their fingers on a handy excuse for why the biker's presence infuriates them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My traffic safety habits are now entirely spite-based.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC"/></entry><entry><title>the emerging bus nonconspiracy</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/07/14/the-emerging-bus-nonconspiracy/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-07-14T12:20:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-07-14T12:20:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-07-14:/2008/07/14/the-emerging-bus-nonconspiracy/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;First: the plan to move DC's intercity buses to the L'Enfant wasteland is on hold. I got the following in an email on Friday:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;The District Department of Transportation as of July 3, 2008 has suspended the new intercity bus permit regulations to allow for additional evaluation and review of …&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;First: the plan to move DC's intercity buses to the L'Enfant wasteland is on hold. I got the following in an email on Friday:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;The District Department of Transportation as of July 3, 2008 has suspended the new intercity bus permit regulations to allow for additional evaluation and review of the program. Originally intended to begin in early July, the regulation seeks to better manage the use of public space and institute curbside management practices through new permitting requirements and by identifying specific locations for passenger drop off and pickup. [...]&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Further details will be available as DDOT continues to evaluate the new policy.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hilariously, the email's author appears to have simply cc'ed everybody who wrote in about the issue. It looks like they got about 400 complaints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On Friday Kriston and Matt tried to convince me that the whole bus terminal project was a sinister plot to legislate Greyhound's competition out of existence, delivering yet another crooked victory to Big Bus. Key to this undertaking, they said, was a little-noticed but crucially important new rule forbidding the bus companies from selling tickets at curbside. Instead the companies must maintain a storefront — a requirement that, given the lack of available real estate at the new depot site, could not be met. Presto: no more intercity buses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was dubious, and after reading the text of the (now tabled) proposal, I'm even more so. Here, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.ddot.dc.gov/ddot/lib/ddot/information/publicspace/emergencyrule.pdf"&gt;have a look yourself&lt;/a&gt;. Section 3307.8:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;An intercity bus operator shall not:&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;(a)&amp;nbsp;Vend tickets in the public space;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;(b)&amp;nbsp;Arrive sooner than thirty (30) minutes prior to scheduled departure in the intercity bus zone;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;(c)&amp;nbsp;Remain in the intercity bus zone for more than thirty (30) minutes after arrival; or&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;(d)&amp;nbsp;Allow intercity bus passengers to obstruct the flow of pedestrian traffic in the public space and into adjacent buildings.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously the curbside ticket-sale question would have hinged on what &amp;quot;public space&amp;quot; means. I am not a [etc.], but 3307.8(d) strongly implies to me that the interior of the bus isn't considered a part of the public space — certainly it's legally distinct in at least &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; ways, since the bus operators can charge admission to and eject people from it. And of course many of the intercity bus companies sell their tickets at the pickup site, but do so as their representative moves through the loaded bus checking tickets. Sometimes you pay as you get on, sometimes you pay once you're seated. I can't imagine mandating one or the other would dramatically disrupt these businesses' operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides which, the proposal sidesteps more obvious ways to inconvenience Greyhound's competitors. Fines for noncompliance are only $200 or $300 (depending on whether it's a first offense); the fee for renting space for loading and unloading works out to less than $2.50/hr. This isn't to say that moving these buses to L'Enfant is a good idea, but I don't think it's a conspiracy, either.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC"/></entry><entry><title>the funniest phrase you will read on the internet this week</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/07/09/the-funniest-phrase-you-will-read-on-the-internet-this-week/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-07-09T14:24:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-07-09T14:24:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-07-09:/2008/07/09/the-funniest-phrase-you-will-read-on-the-internet-this-week/</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;is &amp;quot;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.ta-nehisi.com/2008/07/a-very-uncomfortable-post-about-black-crime.html#comment-121667968"&gt;pre-gentrification Clarendon&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC"/></entry><entry><title>in a continuing series</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/07/08/in-a-continuing-series/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-07-08T10:42:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-07-08T10:42:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-07-08:/2008/07/08/in-a-continuing-series/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A 22 year-old woman on a bicycle &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/07/08/AR2008070800975.html"&gt;was run over and killed by a garbage truck this morning&lt;/a&gt;. Commenters in the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dcist.com/2008/07/08/woman_killed_by_garbage_truck_in_du.php#comments"&gt;DCist thread&lt;/a&gt; are speculating that she was in a bike lane, which makes sense given the location of the accident — the area north of Dupont is actually pretty bike-friendly …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A 22 year-old woman on a bicycle &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/07/08/AR2008070800975.html"&gt;was run over and killed by a garbage truck this morning&lt;/a&gt;. Commenters in the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dcist.com/2008/07/08/woman_killed_by_garbage_truck_in_du.php#comments"&gt;DCist thread&lt;/a&gt; are speculating that she was in a bike lane, which makes sense given the location of the accident — the area north of Dupont is actually pretty bike-friendly by District standards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, over at WTOP it took a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://wtop.com/index.php?nid=25&amp;amp;sid=1436169&amp;amp;comments=true#msg_4"&gt;whopping five comments&lt;/a&gt; before someone began complaining about cyclists' behavior. Classy!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dcist.com/2008/07/08/woman_killed_by_garbage_truck_in_du.php#comment-1401482"&gt;Good&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dcist.com/2008/07/08/woman_killed_by_garbage_truck_in_du.php#comment-1401507"&gt;stuff&lt;/a&gt; later in the DCist thread, too. Cyclists really need to clean up their act — think of how that poor truck driver must be feeling!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE 2:&lt;/strong&gt; Jake mentions in comments that he &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://citizenjake.com/2008/07/08/an-awful-way-to-start-the-morning/"&gt;rode past the scene of the accident&lt;/a&gt; this morning.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC"/></entry><entry><title>about enough of this crap</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/06/24/about-enough-of-this-crap/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-06-24T14:45:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-06-24T14:45:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-06-24:/2008/06/24/about-enough-of-this-crap/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Christ: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.washingtoncitypaper.com/blogs/citydesk/2008/06/24/cyclist-rights-cyclist-wrongs/"&gt;another one&lt;/a&gt;. Why is it that any time someone points out that despite bicycling being a clean and cheap mode of transportation our cities make it much more dangerous and difficult than it ought to be, the first reaction is always, ALWAYS for people to exclaim: &amp;quot;But sometimes bicyclists …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Christ: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.washingtoncitypaper.com/blogs/citydesk/2008/06/24/cyclist-rights-cyclist-wrongs/"&gt;another one&lt;/a&gt;. Why is it that any time someone points out that despite bicycling being a clean and cheap mode of transportation our cities make it much more dangerous and difficult than it ought to be, the first reaction is always, ALWAYS for people to exclaim: &amp;quot;But sometimes bicyclists run stop signs or ride on sidewalks!&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm really trying to keep this short, so I'll just say: speaking for cyclists everywhere, out A-#1 top priority is not getting killed by automobiles. I'm sorry that this edges out &amp;quot;not startling those not on bikes&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;not inconveniencing those driving&amp;quot;, but it does. The stakes are just a wee bit higher, is the thing. We're riding to get away from cars, to get seen by cars, and to avoid winding up under cars. If you don't ride a bike you don't understand, and you certainly have no right to make assumptions about the correctness of typical cyclist behavior based on your occasional prudish outrage at the antics of a few reckless downtown couriers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Someday I hope we'll all be able to live in peace and harmony. But as someone who's employed all three modes of transportation, take it from me: right now irresponsible or dim-witted drivers put cyclists in danger much more frequently and to a greater degree than cyclists endanger walkers and drivers. Please try to apportion your outrage accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC"/></entry><entry><title>also</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/03/17/also-2/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-03-17T11:01:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-03-17T11:01:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-03-17:/2008/03/17/also-2/</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I missed all the excitement, but Cristen has a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://cuteandnerdy.com/2008/03/13/fire-in-mt-pleasant-one-hell-of-a-night/"&gt;great first-person account&lt;/a&gt; of the Mount Pleasant fire that you should read if you haven't already.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC"/></entry><entry><title>DC taxis</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/01/18/dc-taxis/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-01-18T12:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2008-01-18T12:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-01-18:/2008/01/18/dc-taxis/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Matt's &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://matthewyglesias.theatlantic.com/archives/2008/01/taxi_fares.php"&gt;concerned&lt;/a&gt; that Mayor Fenty's reduction of proposed metered fares for D.C. taxis will make it harder to hail a cab. I'm not so worried. Have a look at the comments in &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dcist.com/2008/01/16/fenty_lowers_ta.php#comments"&gt;this DCist thread&lt;/a&gt;. It's full of stories of cabbies refusing to take fares because of the requested …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Matt's &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://matthewyglesias.theatlantic.com/archives/2008/01/taxi_fares.php"&gt;concerned&lt;/a&gt; that Mayor Fenty's reduction of proposed metered fares for D.C. taxis will make it harder to hail a cab. I'm not so worried. Have a look at the comments in &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dcist.com/2008/01/16/fenty_lowers_ta.php#comments"&gt;this DCist thread&lt;/a&gt;. It's full of stories of cabbies refusing to take fares because of the requested destination or because a surcharge wouldn't apply to the trip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, perhaps these cabs are refusing to provide service (illegally, I might add) because they're already perched on the brink of financial ruin, and taking anything less than maximally lucrative fares would send them tumbling into bankruptcy. But I have my doubts. By all accounts the taxi commission in this city has been unusually powerful for an unusually long time. And although I don't know how hard D.C. cabbies work relative to their peers in other cities, I can say with certainty that cabs in Philadelphia are cheaper, easier to hail, more convenient (you can pay with credit cards!) and generally better maintained. I could be mistaken, but it certainly &lt;em&gt;seems&lt;/em&gt; like D.C. cabs have been operating as a cartel, isolated from true competitive pressure and, in general, enjoying something of a sweetheart deal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I admit, I'm a little hesitant to make this criticism. Although I strongly suspect that driving a taxi in D.C. is a better job than driving one elsewhere, I'm absolutely positive that being a software developer in D.C. is a better job than either. But although I'm sorry to advocate making cab operators' lives harder, I also have a pretty strong sense of resentment over how many times I've emerged from a Washington taxi feeling ripped off — I'd put it at about 50% of my trips, whether from dubious surcharges, phantom zones springing to life or the driver's insistence that he only ever carries $2 in change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The obvious caveat to all of this is Washington's size. It's a small city — maybe expecting an efficient taxi system in such a small space is unrealistic. But although the city is small, the metropolitan area is large. If D.C. cabbies really can't make a living charging New York prices, the answer is simple: start allowing Virginia and Maryland taxis into the District and, if possible, vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At that point you might have an efficiently operating market for taxi service — and at that point I think it'd be safe to start worrying about the system reacting to manipulation in straightforward economic ways. But at the moment I seriously doubt that the factors constraining the supply of taxis in this town have anything to do with price.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC"/></entry><entry><title>and I awoke and found me here / on the cold (capitol) hill's side</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2007/12/05/and-i-awoke-and-found-me-here-on-the-cold-capitol-hills-side/" rel="alternate"/><published>2007-12-05T11:10:00-05:00</published><updated>2007-12-05T11:10:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2007-12-05:/2007/12/05/and-i-awoke-and-found-me-here-on-the-cold-capitol-hills-side/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As someone who has to think about how to write DCist Morning Roundup introductions on a somewhat regular basis, I feel that I can say this with confidence: there are only so many ways to whimsically express the idea that Washingtonians are bad at driving in snow. But that doesn't …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As someone who has to think about how to write DCist Morning Roundup introductions on a somewhat regular basis, I feel that I can say this with confidence: there are only so many ways to whimsically express the idea that Washingtonians are bad at driving in snow. But that doesn't make it the underlying fact any less true, as &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://blogstretch.blogspot.com/2007/12/oh-what-dummy-full-moooorning.html"&gt;Amanda can attest&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can attest to it, too. Riding my bike this morning, I coasted down the left-hand side of M Street, in the gap between the traffic and parked cars. The light was red but clearly about to change. Suddenly the driver's side door of the car one length in front and to the right of me began to swing open, and a leg emerged. I skidded to a halt, cursed and glared at the driver.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But his face was totally blank, uncomprehending, and remained so as he slowly reversed his motions. Why &lt;em&gt;shouldn't&lt;/em&gt; he suddenly abandon his car and start wandering around as the light changed? It's still locomotion, after all. And in this dumbfounding urban hallucination, where even frozen water can fall from the sky, who's to say that one way of navigating the dreamscape is more valid than another?&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC"/></entry><entry><title>Gilbert Arenas is launching a cartoon</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2007/10/12/gilbert-arenas-is-launching-a-cartoon/" rel="alternate"/><published>2007-10-12T19:56:00-04:00</published><updated>2007-10-12T19:56:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2007-10-12:/2007/10/12/gilbert-arenas-is-launching-a-cartoon/</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;...according to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.nba.com/blog/gilbert_arenas.html#071012_01"&gt;his blog&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.gazothepranksta.com/"&gt;Here's&lt;/a&gt; the website for the series, which displays the cast of ethnically diverse characters that will be featured.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't see how this could possibly end badly.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC"/></entry><entry><title>blog blog blog</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2007/09/12/blog-blog-blog/" rel="alternate"/><published>2007-09-12T09:34:00-04:00</published><updated>2007-09-12T09:34:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2007-09-12:/2007/09/12/blog-blog-blog/</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://online.wsj.com/public/article/SB118945161322222870-bXYxKiJLpOaWB_OQ3i8yGp8dqwM_20071012.html?mod=tff_main_tff_top"&gt;Nice job, guys&lt;/a&gt;. The lack of stipple portraits of Sommer is admittedly dispiriting, but otherwise it seems pretty alright.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="DC"/></entry></feed>