<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Tom Lee - internal affairs</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"/><link href="/feeds/internal-affairs.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>/</id><updated>2008-01-08T11:06:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>comments: fixed (again!)</title><link href="/2008/01/08/comments-fixed-again/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-01-08T11:06:00-05:00</published><updated>2008-01-08T11:06:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2008-01-08:/2008/01/08/comments-fixed-again/</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Bah. Apparently I need to make my comment-script rotating script a little more robust — if it hangs halfway the whole system gets screwed up. Sorry about that, aspiring commenters. Things are fixed.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="internal affairs"/></entry><entry><title>now with less broken</title><link href="/2007/11/14/now-with-less-broken/" rel="alternate"/><published>2007-11-14T10:40:00-05:00</published><updated>2007-11-14T10:40:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2007-11-14:/2007/11/14/now-with-less-broken/</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Comments were busted for a while there — my &lt;a class="reference external" href="/2007/01/26/fighting-movable-type-comment-spam-part-1/"&gt;epic antispam solution&lt;/a&gt; didn't make the trip to the new server undamaged (I think the cron job fired in the middle of the transfer, leaving the files out of sync). It's all better now!&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="internal affairs"/></entry><entry><title>all better</title><link href="/2007/11/04/all-better-2/" rel="alternate"/><published>2007-11-04T22:30:00-05:00</published><updated>2007-11-04T22:30:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2007-11-04:/2007/11/04/all-better-2/</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Back online! See, the new machine uses CGI and suexec instead of mod_php, and so files with permissions greater than 0755 throw an error, but Movable Type creates files at 0666 by default. It's obviously all pretty fascinating, but the short version is that everything should now be fixed.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="internal affairs"/></entry><entry><title>offline</title><link href="/2007/11/02/offline/" rel="alternate"/><published>2007-11-02T11:19:00-04:00</published><updated>2007-11-02T11:19:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2007-11-02:/2007/11/02/offline/</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm switching servers, which may result in some site downtime — hopefully this entry will weasel its way into your RSS readers before that happens. Just wanted to provide some advance warning, lest a big ugly error message catch you by surprise. I am a competent internet professional, I swear!&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="internal affairs"/></entry><entry><title>comment feed: finally fixed</title><link href="/2007/08/25/comment-feed-finally-fixed/" rel="alternate"/><published>2007-08-25T11:29:00-04:00</published><updated>2007-08-25T11:29:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2007-08-25:/2007/08/25/comment-feed-finally-fixed/</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;To the one or two people who actually use the &lt;a class="reference external" href="/2007/08/25/comment-feed-finally-fixed/"&gt;comment RSS feed&lt;/a&gt;: rejoice! I finally fixed it so that entry titles and links work properly within it.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="internal affairs"/></entry><entry><title>comment rss = fixed(ish)</title><link href="/2007/06/13/comment-rss-fixedish/" rel="alternate"/><published>2007-06-13T10:48:00-04:00</published><updated>2007-06-13T10:48:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2007-06-13:/2007/06/13/comment-rss-fixedish/</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Comment RSS permalinks now actually work. Hurrah! Now you won't have to go hunting for how to find disc0unt clonazepam or hot young teens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll turn this into a completed website yet, goddammit. Next up: a comment preview template, tentatively scheduled for completion in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="internal affairs"/></entry><entry><title>new header graphic</title><link href="/2006/11/01/new-header-graphic/" rel="alternate"/><published>2006-11-01T21:39:00-05:00</published><updated>2006-11-01T21:39:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2006-11-01:/2006/11/01/new-header-graphic/</id><summary type="html">&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Courtesy of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://flickr.com/photos/perdita/"&gt;Perdita&lt;/a&gt; and her use of a By-Attribution Creative Commons license.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;I still haven't gotten around to fixing the archives or comment preview form or a bunch of other things. But I did write a semi-ridiculous script that automatically assembles the header graphic (in multiple resolutions!) very easily. All …&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Courtesy of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://flickr.com/photos/perdita/"&gt;Perdita&lt;/a&gt; and her use of a By-Attribution Creative Commons license.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;I still haven't gotten around to fixing the archives or comment preview form or a bunch of other things. But I did write a semi-ridiculous script that automatically assembles the header graphic (in multiple resolutions!) very easily. All I've got to do is upload a photo to my photostream, tag it as &amp;quot;blogheader&amp;quot; and run a password-protected script. It's kind of slick, if I do say so myself (although I have to admit that, judging by the aspect ratio of this shot, I think some of my image-resizing math is probably a little screwed up).&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;I'd post the code, but it's a pain in the ass to install the PEAR libraries that are necessary for talking to Flickr. If anyone's willing to jump through the necessary hoops, let me know.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="internal affairs"/></entry><entry><title>hi there</title><link href="/2006/10/09/hi-there/" rel="alternate"/><published>2006-10-09T00:30:00-04:00</published><updated>2006-10-09T00:30:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2006-10-09:/2006/10/09/hi-there/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hello, internet people, and welcome to the new blog. I'm making a conscious effort not to bog myself down in introductions and ruminations and other pretensions aimed at making this kind of endeavor seem weightier than it actually is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So! I'll just say that I really enjoyed writing &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.zunta.org/blog"&gt;the old …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hello, internet people, and welcome to the new blog. I'm making a conscious effort not to bog myself down in introductions and ruminations and other pretensions aimed at making this kind of endeavor seem weightier than it actually is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So! I'll just say that I really enjoyed writing &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.zunta.org/blog"&gt;the old blog&lt;/a&gt; with &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://outtamindouttasite.typepad.com"&gt;Catherine&lt;/a&gt;. By the time it was done, I'd written 265,971 words' worth of ecstatic technology evangelism, prejudiced music elitism and feeble attempts at humor. Stand by for more of the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also coming: a completed site. Archives? IE compatibility? Finished templates? I guess some people enjoy those sorts of things. I'll try to humor them by and by.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="internal affairs"/></entry></feed>