<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Tom Lee - misc, politics</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"/><link href="/feeds/misc-politics.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>/</id><updated>2009-01-31T16:50:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>delicious, delicious bailout</title><link href="/2009/01/31/delicious-delicious-bailout/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-01-31T16:50:00-05:00</published><updated>2009-01-31T16:50:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2009-01-31:/2009/01/31/delicious-delicious-bailout/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Gelt!" class="right" src="/static/2009/01/31/20090131_gelt-20090131-165317.jpg" /&gt;The one thing that the warring experts agree on is that the proposed stimulus is extraordinary. One side shouts: &amp;quot;It's outrageous! It's unprecedented! In terms of economic and political theory, it's odious!&amp;quot; The other replies that yes, you're right about all of that, but if we do nothing the alternative …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Gelt!" class="right" src="/static/2009/01/31/20090131_gelt-20090131-165317.jpg" /&gt;The one thing that the warring experts agree on is that the proposed stimulus is extraordinary. One side shouts: &amp;quot;It's outrageous! It's unprecedented! In terms of economic and political theory, it's odious!&amp;quot; The other replies that yes, you're right about all of that, but if we do nothing the alternative will probably be worse. We've already tried all of the less objectionable things that we normally do, but now we're out of alternatives and so the only options we have left are nationalizing banks or giving handouts to financiers or, god forbid, cleaning up the National Mall so that our great American commons isn't a disgusting barren mudpit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So yes, it's a bad situation, but a lack of ideas seems to be at least part of the problem. And then last night it struck me: a bold, novel solution, which I offer here in the humble spirit of citizenship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need more money flowing around, right? But we can't just print more money because of the inflationary risk, right? It has to be short term — new money that disappears after a while. The answer is simple: chocolate gelt. Edible currency. Fiat finger food! It'll circulate for a while, then gradually disappear as people consume it. For those of you who still believe in economics, I think the technical rationale is that the currency will be consumed once its marginal deliciousness (or whatever) exceeds its face value. Personally, I think it'll probably just be consumed by the drunk, hungry or drunk &amp;amp; hungry. Either way, there's a built-in safety check against long-term inflationary effects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are of course some practical concerns. The foil would have to be significantly upgraded to make regular handling of the currency viable — perhaps some sort of carefully engineered tin design would be necessary. Also, it may be that chocolate is too cheap (or melting-prone) a commodity to turn into a useful form of currency. Or perhaps forgers would refill empties with Hershey's chocolate — presumably inferior to delicious federal chocolate. But there are solutions to these problems. Maybe we could use ampules of liquor. Or, simpler still, the government could storm Hidden Valley, seize its ranch-producing operations and make the Treasury Department the only source of our precious national condiment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever the specifics, I think this is an initiative that would be welcomed by the public. Certainly I'd be a lot happier about it than I was when I received five one-dollar coins' worth of change from the Chinatown bus people last night.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc, politics"/></entry><entry><title>toward a more enlightened vitriol</title><link href="/2008/05/21/toward-a-more-enlightened-vitriol/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-05-21T12:25:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-05-21T12:25:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2008-05-21:/2008/05/21/toward-a-more-enlightened-vitriol/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yglesias &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://matthewyglesias.theatlantic.com/archives/2008/05/thick_moral_concepts.php"&gt;links&lt;/a&gt; to a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/Feministing/~3/295051381/009237.html"&gt;Feministing post&lt;/a&gt; about a GOP consultantdefense of the word &amp;quot;bitch&amp;quot;, then discusses the difficulty of untangling the high-minded, purely pejorative nature of the insult from its sexist connotations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it happens I found myself thinking about this just the other day when, while biking, a driver …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yglesias &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://matthewyglesias.theatlantic.com/archives/2008/05/thick_moral_concepts.php"&gt;links&lt;/a&gt; to a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/Feministing/~3/295051381/009237.html"&gt;Feministing post&lt;/a&gt; about a GOP consultantdefense of the word &amp;quot;bitch&amp;quot;, then discusses the difficulty of untangling the high-minded, purely pejorative nature of the insult from its sexist connotations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it happens I found myself thinking about this just the other day when, while biking, a driver cut me off. I immediately thought some unkind things, then found myself tentatively rephrasing them when I saw the driver was a woman, then found myself backing off from the effort entirely when the most obvious alternate reformulation struck me as inherently sexist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be clear, I think that justifying the application of the word &amp;quot;bitch&amp;quot; to Hillary Clinton, as the consultant in question is trying to do, is pretty obviously sexist — Senator Clinton seems just as amiable as the next politician, and I doubt she's ever done anything to this specific guy other than disappoint him by not having murdered Vince Foster. But in the abstract I wonder if the use of sex-specific insults is any more inherently problematic than the use of sex-specific pronouns. Obviously any such epithets will inevitably become tangled up with indefensible opinions and prejudices related to the gender with which they've been associated; but equally obviously, a truly egalitarian society will make it equally easy to spew venom at someone, regardless of their sex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, given that people will continue to get upset with one another, it seems like we're probably stuck with gendered swearwords: perhaps my capacity for creative profanity just isn't up to the task, but it seems like androgynous put-downs are inevitably stilted or lame. Whether that's because they aren't in common usage or because harsh words lose some impact when divorced from visceral, unspeakably ugly hatreds like racism and sexism, I couldn't say. Ideally it'd be the former — and on this score, the decreasing (but still significant) ridiculousness of the word &amp;quot;frak&amp;quot; is encouraging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I suspect that all the best insults — the single words that actually sting — will remain connected to sexist conceptions of gender roles. But we can all at least aspire to liberally apply these horrible oaths more evenly across gender lines. That's the future I'd want to live in, anyway. Call me a utopian dreamer if you must, but the next time I'm endangered by a driver I'll call them an asshole loudly, proudly, and without consideration of their sex. To do any less would betray a lack of respect for a fellow human being.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc, politics"/></entry><entry><title>The Project for an Organo-American Century</title><link href="/2008/03/27/the-project-for-an-organo-american-century/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-03-27T11:38:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-03-27T11:38:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2008-03-27:/2008/03/27/the-project-for-an-organo-american-century/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Matthew Yglesias says that &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://matthewyglesias.theatlantic.com/archives/2008/03/the_real_threat.php"&gt;our nation is blind to the looming robot threat&lt;/a&gt;. But then, he &lt;em&gt;would&lt;/em&gt; say that, wouldn't he? After all, his corporate paymasters are quite keen on the idea of an outbreak of hostilities between the U.S. and a nationless mechanized fighting force. I'm sure in …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Matthew Yglesias says that &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://matthewyglesias.theatlantic.com/archives/2008/03/the_real_threat.php"&gt;our nation is blind to the looming robot threat&lt;/a&gt;. But then, he &lt;em&gt;would&lt;/em&gt; say that, wouldn't he? After all, his corporate paymasters are quite keen on the idea of an outbreak of hostilities between the U.S. and a nationless mechanized fighting force. I'm sure in some labyrinthine GE facility they're working on robots at one end of the hall and the weapons to destroy them at the other, with representatives from the accounting department gleefully shuffling between the two. Think it sounds far-fetched? You do know who owns &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Consolidated_Robotics"&gt;Consolidated Robotics&lt;/a&gt;, don't you?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, the news will be good for Mr. Yglesias closer to home, too: the Sino-American War he poo-poos will only increase demand for trenchant English-speaking foreign policy analysis on one side of the ocean, as the Chinese prefer their news written in their own language (&lt;em&gt;quelle provinciale!&lt;/em&gt;). A war with the machines, on the other hand, would afford multitudes of perfect electrical minds programmed with English character sets and keen to know thy enemy by consuming our media at a breakneck pace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, launching America into a fight with the machines would provide quite a windfall for the ascendant pundit. Sadly, this media self-interest is nothing new. The press has tirelessly beaten the robo-war drum over the past few years — and the rhythm has approached a crescendo as of late. &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://google.com/trends"&gt;Google Trends&lt;/a&gt; tells the tale:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="PROOF" class="center" src="/static/2008/03/27/20080327_robots.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aside from those few innocent days in 2004 when America fell in love with Will Smith's &lt;em&gt;I,&amp;nbsp;Robot&lt;/em&gt;, the picture is clear: the media has consistently hyped the robot menace in a manner completely out of proportion to its significance for the average American.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A typical middle class family doesn't feel threatened by the improving fortunes of robots. The basic generosity of the American spirit rightly acknowledges that a rising tide lifts all boats (well, alright, not boats propelled through the air by shining discs of electrostatic plasma, which hum softly as their masters rain laser death upon the landscape below — but those boats can lift themselves, so the upshot is the same). No, Americans are more concerned about being able to pay for their kids to go to college, and saving for retirement, and making the mortgage payment that just shot up — and, crucially, being able to do those things while &lt;em&gt;constantly being robbed by pirates&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, as is all too typical, the pirate menace that dominates the nightmares of the nation's breadwinners is going unacknowledged by our warmongering village elites. You see it's just not that glamorous to talk seriously about the roots of piracy, or to build the sorts of institutions that can stop its spread in a meaningful way. No, it's much easier to craft a self-flattering narrative about plucky humans standing up to gleaming mechanical terrors. Frankly, I expected more of Matt.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc, politics"/></entry></feed>