<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Tom Lee - misc, tech</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/feeds/misc-tech.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>https://tomlee.wtf/</id><updated>2015-09-18T01:24:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>ad blockers won't be a big deal</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2015/09/18/ad-blockers-wont-be-a-big-deal/" rel="alternate"/><published>2015-09-18T01:24:00-04:00</published><updated>2015-09-18T01:24:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2015-09-18:/2015/09/18/ad-blockers-wont-be-a-big-deal/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the few downsides to attending a conference in Asia is that when the English-speaking world is waking up and beginning to groggily think serious thoughts, you will have just returned to your hotel from a reception with free beer, which you will have had sort of a lot …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of the few downsides to attending a conference in Asia is that when the English-speaking world is waking up and beginning to groggily think serious thoughts, you will have just returned to your hotel from a reception with free beer, which you will have had sort of a lot of. The food here is spicy enough that beer availability is a basic amenity, like electrical outlets or ventilation. Korea is a great country.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although fundamentally delightful, this dynamic can push your level of Twitter cantankerousness out of global circadian sync. Last night it led me to wade, intemperately, into the Great Media Ad Blocker Freakout of '15.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This morning I woke up and resolved to be a better, more understanding conversational partner. It was easy enough to identify the pieces influencing everyone's thinking via the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.fastcompany.com/3051234/today-in-tabs/today-in-tabs-live-from-carly-fiorinas-feverish-imagination"&gt;Today in Tabs Media Monoculture&lt;/a&gt;. But these pieces are surprisingly bad!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.theverge.com/2015/9/17/9338963/welcome-to-hell-apple-vs-google-vs-facebook-and-the-slow-death-of-the-web"&gt;Here is The Verge's Nilay Patel&lt;/a&gt; bringing the kind of tech blogger tunnel vision that &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.theverge.com/a/apple-watch-review"&gt;can turn a wristwatch into the fulcrum of conscious experience&lt;/a&gt;. He thinks this minor iOS feature is best understood as a major chapter in the Manichean conflict between tech company nation-states. &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.theawl.com/2015/09/welcome-to-the-block-party"&gt;Here is The Awl's Casey Johnston&lt;/a&gt; relaxing into the newly-minted blend of evocative GIFs, Marxist analysis and depressive fatalism that has made her employer the web's most prestigious purveyor of media industry commentary. She never mentions pop-up blockers or points out that non-Safari webviews aren't affected. The other pieces just don't make any fucking sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notwithstanding the App Store rankings of the new iOS ad blockers--which are better understood as a measure of download acceleration, not velocity--I doubt that all this handwringing will be justified by the number of ads whose lives are actually cut short. But let's suppose that's wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ad blockers work by preventing your operating system from speaking to ad networks' domains. Those domains are where the ad network Javascript lives, which gets added to the page and loads the images or video or flash for the ad (among other things).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You could make ad blocking much, &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; harder by serving this Javascript from the same domain as the page content. Ad networks don't want to do this for two reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their first objection is about control. It's coming from their servers, it's their Javascript, and they get to make the decisions. Handing these Javascript responsibilities to publications would introduce a big support headache and would require the networks to police the code to ensure it isn't modified. Their Javascript is often inexcusably shitty, and modifying it would be a great idea, so publishers might be tempted to do so. Personally, I would be very excited to see this devolution of technical power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their second objection is about capability. Something called the same-origin policy means that when you visit &lt;em&gt;publisher-a.com&lt;/em&gt; the site cannot detect that you have visited &lt;em&gt;publisher-b.net&lt;/em&gt;. However, if both pages include Javascript from &lt;em&gt;ad-network.biz&lt;/em&gt;, your path between sites can be observed. This allows your behavior to be tracked, and enables the networks to assign you to &lt;em&gt;segments&lt;/em&gt; like &amp;quot;auto buyer&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;likely golfer&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;pervert&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can pull off tracking while serving everything from a constellation of publisher domains, but it's not trivial to do so. Many publishers would need a hosted solution to handle these engineering details, and this is where the Awl's paranoia about a totalitarian Facebook dystopia starts to look a bit plausible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The hypothesized migration toward a central Facebook-like architecture has a cyclical fat/thin client whiff about it, and I suspect the pendulum will swing back before too many of us are forcibly grafted to Oculus Rifts. But then again I earn my living in a different industry and have the luxury of waiting to form a conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, I'm unconvinced that audience segmentation is actually good for publishers. The goal of segmentation is to target ads efficiently. But efficiency means achieving a result with fewer resources than you otherwise might. In this case, those resources are the very things that pay for all those tickets to XOXO. (I've meandered toward this point &lt;a class="reference external" href="/2010/12/05/more-efficiency-means-less-profit/"&gt;before&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Besides which, there's a convincing case to be made that &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.bloomberg.com/bw/articles/2014-03-03/advertisings-century-of-flat-line-growth"&gt;ad efficiency is meaningless&lt;/a&gt;. A roughly constant share of the economy goes to advertising:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;img alt="ADS_gdp_vs_spending" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2966" src="/static/2015/09/ADS_gdp_vs_spending.jpg" style="width: 630px; height: 550px;" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;img alt="ADS_percent_GDP_b" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-2967" src="/static/2015/09/ADS_percent_GDP_b.jpg" style="width: 630px; height: 550px;" /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe some of the spikes in those graphs came from VCRs or &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.truthinadvertising.org/static/2011/10/Advertisement-Loudness-Mitigation-Act.pdf"&gt;loudness regulation&lt;/a&gt; or FTC actions or the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Payola"&gt;payola scandal&lt;/a&gt; or Tivo or pop-up blockers. But I doubt it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So. Could ad blockers damage or destroy some publishers? Yeah, this seems possible, particularly for niche publications with geeky audiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Could ad blockers hasten Facebook's ingestion of the media industry? Sure, maybe. Kind of seems like a long-shot but I know a lot of people are freaking out about this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Could ad blockers shift spending to TV or print, overwhelming trends toward mobile and away from cable? Kind of implausible, don't you think?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, will ad blockers reduce the size of the ad dollar pool, shrinking the total resources available to content creators? Flatly: no.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ALSO:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.vox.com/2015/9/18/9351759/ad-blocking-controversy"&gt;Matt's post is characteristically excellent&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc, tech"/></entry><entry><title>that jerk in Warcraft really IS emblematic of mankind's doom</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/08/04/that-jerk-in-warcraft-really-is-emblematic-of-mankinds-doom/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-08-04T12:43:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-08-04T12:43:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-08-04:/2008/08/04/that-jerk-in-warcraft-really-is-emblematic-of-mankinds-doom/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I thought &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/08/03/magazine/03trolls-t.html?ei=5124&amp;amp;en=b5085d50ee5c65e5&amp;amp;ex=1375329600&amp;amp;partner=permalink&amp;amp;exprod=permalink&amp;amp;pagewanted=all"&gt;this weekend's article on trolls&lt;/a&gt; was pretty good, and that the author did a nice job balancing the need to treat his subjects respectfully against his obligation to point out that they're completely full of shit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.unfogged.com/archives/week_2008_07_27.html#009080"&gt;associated Unfogged thread&lt;/a&gt; descended unfortunately quickly into an elucidation of who …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I thought &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/08/03/magazine/03trolls-t.html?ei=5124&amp;amp;en=b5085d50ee5c65e5&amp;amp;ex=1375329600&amp;amp;partner=permalink&amp;amp;exprod=permalink&amp;amp;pagewanted=all"&gt;this weekend's article on trolls&lt;/a&gt; was pretty good, and that the author did a nice job balancing the need to treat his subjects respectfully against his obligation to point out that they're completely full of shit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.unfogged.com/archives/week_2008_07_27.html#009080"&gt;associated Unfogged thread&lt;/a&gt; descended unfortunately quickly into an elucidation of who wasn't paying attention when their English class discussed &lt;em&gt;Crime and Punishment&lt;/em&gt;. But prior to that everyone at least acknowledged that the activities described in the article aren't really what most people think of when they say &amp;quot;trolling&amp;quot;. I think that's right for a couple of reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For one thing, I suspect that trolling as it's understood in the blogosphere is probably a lot less prevalent than people tend to think. Deliberate bad-faith argumentation is much rarer than people who just strongly disagree or are otherwise unable to engage with the conversation in a way that others find interesting. Communities have a right to avoid having the same discussions over and over, and occasionally saying &amp;quot;don't feed the trolls&amp;quot; is one of the few ways to accomplish that, I guess. But it always strikes me as unfortunately dishonest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course even if the prevalence of blog trolls is overstated, the existence of griefers can't be in doubt. Just log in to a game on Xbox Live and wait to be paired with someone who spends all his time shooting teammates in the back of the head. I think that's a better, less ambiguous description of what Fortuny and Weev and the rest of the people mentioned in the article really are. The only thing that sets them apart from a MMORPG PKer is their technical sophistication and their decision to ply their trade on the web.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I found most interesting, though, was the ease with which these damaged individuals are able to damage others. Although I think Weev's Malthusian spiel is grandiose bullshit, I have my own similarly gloomy predictions. Specifically, I worry about the inevitable increase of personal power. Modern societies are fundamentally reliant on growth, and technology is no exception. But of course there are certain biological, physical and mental limits that will remain fairly static even as our ability to process information, wield energy and manipulate living systems expands. That means that over time every individual will be able to exert more power over others. Those potential victims will be similarly empowered to defend themselves, of course, but the advantage of surprise and the gulf in power between the average citizen and the expert will continue to grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I usually think of this in terms of weapons: we're already at the point where a disturbed and dedicated hobbyist is able to create a device or organism that can kill a lot of people. The difficulty of this task will continue to decrease and the associated potential devastation will continue to increase. The article on trolls made me realize that this effect will hold for psychological harm inflicted by a stranger just as well as it does for physical harm. And it made me feel much gloomier about our prospects for collectively ceasing to do damage for its own sake before the stakes get catastrophically high.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE:&lt;/strong&gt; Go see what &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://meganmcardle.theatlantic.com/archives/2008/08/culture_matters_1.php"&gt;Megan has to say&lt;/a&gt;, too:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
I doubt that the solution is, as the author suggests, just to learn to live with it. Rather, I'd expect that countertrolls will emerge--hackers who put as much energy into harassing these people as they put into harassing us. Evolutionary biologists call people like that &amp;quot;altruistic punishers&amp;quot;, and they serve an invaluable purpose in any society.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think she's probably right. I mentioned player killers above — I didn't mention &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Player_killer#Player_killer_killing"&gt;player killer killers&lt;/a&gt;: in-game vigilantes targeting PKers that have emerged enough times and places to be recognized as a phenomenon in its own right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whether or not PKKers have ever had much of an effect on any of the online communities in which they operate, though, I couldn't say. &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.doombot.com"&gt;Jason&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc, tech"/></entry><entry><title>Freakonomics full-text feed</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2007/08/27/freakonomics-full-text-feed/" rel="alternate"/><published>2007-08-27T11:26:00-04:00</published><updated>2007-08-27T11:26:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2007-08-27:/2007/08/27/freakonomics-full-text-feed/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I almost forgot: a little birdy tells me that you can find a full-text version of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://freakonomics.blogs.nytimes.com/2007/08/22/the-last-word-for-now-on-our-rss-feed-an-excruciatingly-long-and-boring-post-that-will-please-exactly-no-one/"&gt;recently-bowdlerized Freakonomics RSS feed&lt;/a&gt; at the following URL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/freakonomics-full"&gt;http://feeds.feedburner.com/freakonomics-full&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the moment, the authors are asking a very good question: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://freakonomics.blogs.nytimes.com/2007/08/27/why-are-we-eating-so-much-shrimp/"&gt;why are we eating so much more shrimp than …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I almost forgot: a little birdy tells me that you can find a full-text version of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://freakonomics.blogs.nytimes.com/2007/08/22/the-last-word-for-now-on-our-rss-feed-an-excruciatingly-long-and-boring-post-that-will-please-exactly-no-one/"&gt;recently-bowdlerized Freakonomics RSS feed&lt;/a&gt; at the following URL.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/freakonomics-full"&gt;http://feeds.feedburner.com/freakonomics-full&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the moment, the authors are asking a very good question: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://freakonomics.blogs.nytimes.com/2007/08/27/why-are-we-eating-so-much-shrimp/"&gt;why are we eating so much more shrimp than we used to&lt;/a&gt;? Shrimp just isn't very good relative to other seafood. But it's &lt;em&gt;everywhere&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Being the sort of blog that it is, I'm sure that the answer will be &amp;quot;because aquaculture and/or other factors have made the margins on shrimp much better&amp;quot;. I think the other half of the answer, likely to remain unblogged elsewhere, is that Americans are squeamish about seafood that tastes like seafood, and you can't order chicken &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; time you go to Applebee's.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc, tech"/></entry></feed>