<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Tom Lee - misc, personal</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/feeds/misc-personal.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>https://tomlee.wtf/</id><updated>2009-06-02T11:32:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Houstonians are weird</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2009/06/02/houstonians-are-weird/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-06-02T11:32:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-06-02T11:32:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2009-06-02:/2009/06/02/houstonians-are-weird/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm back from the beach, and already rapidly spending down the sleep surplus I accrued there. It's a little bit strange being back. I find it comforting to have a plan on the horizon — something out of the usual routine to look forward to. There are plenty of events looming …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm back from the beach, and already rapidly spending down the sleep surplus I accrued there. It's a little bit strange being back. I find it comforting to have a plan on the horizon — something out of the usual routine to look forward to. There are plenty of events looming, but aside from Emily's birthday none of them yet have definite dates attached. I crave structure! Otherwise it's too easy for summer to start looking like an air-conditioned march through sunshine and into autumn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is nice being back, though, and I'm itching to start work on a few non-Artomatic projects. First, though, I've got to make sure things are working properly at AoM — thanks to Victor my piece was saved from malfunction on opening night, but I haven't yet had a post-opening chance to get down there and confirm that everything's working the way it ought to be (I tried to last night, but had forgotten that Artomatic is closed on Mondays and Tuesdays).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But here, the nominal reason for the post: my sister Beth (whose birthday is today!) sent along &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.rice.edu/virtualtours/cityofhouston/tourfiles/flash/index.html"&gt;this link&lt;/a&gt;, and it's worth a look. It's one of those full-browser 360° panoramic photo dealies, in this case showing off Houstonian attractions that might be of interest to Rice students. Of particular interest are the scenes linked to by the thumbnail of the clown face, and the one two spaces to its right. The first shows off the Orange Show, the bizarre visionary art compound created by an eccentric former orange arbitrageur and his commitment to largely incorrect nutrition education. The second is the Beer Can House, a somewhat less deranged but no less impressive work in which a man fashioned thousands (millions?) of beer cans into artistic armor for his home. Both are managed by the organization that Beth works for and are worth a visit if you find yourself in Houston and temporarily unable to spend the time eating more tacos.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc, personal"/></entry><entry><title>the impression of competence is easier to attain and nearly as good</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2009/04/22/the-impression-of-competence-is-easier-to-attain-and-nearly-as-good/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-04-22T23:22:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-04-22T23:22:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2009-04-22:/2009/04/22/the-impression-of-competence-is-easier-to-attain-and-nearly-as-good/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have not been having good bicycle luck. Since Friday I've ruptured five innertubes and had two tire levers snap. The flats have forced me to walk through the cold, then the rain, then the cold again; I've had to skip appointments and be late to work and walk in …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have not been having good bicycle luck. Since Friday I've ruptured five innertubes and had two tire levers snap. The flats have forced me to walk through the cold, then the rain, then the cold again; I've had to skip appointments and be late to work and walk in bad shoes until my feet ache. My fingers are suffused with brake dust; my hands look like they belong to a Pompeiian mummy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet! I am now &lt;em&gt;so much faster&lt;/em&gt; at changing tires, and this feeling of accomplishment almost makes up for all of the hassle. The operation requires finesse, see, and you tend to accidentally hurt yourself and waste time and materials when you're still getting the hang of it. But now I have the hang of it! I don't do those things anymore! It's great!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, alright, I'm still wasting materials at a phenomenal clip. But there's a reliable and thoroughly pleasant honeymoon period of about forty minutes before the newly-installed innertube explodes, and that's enough for basking. Tomorrow the offending rim goes back to the bike shop and people who objectively know what they're doing; for now, for me, the subjective experience is going to have to be sufficient.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc, personal"/></entry></feed>