<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Tom Lee - misc</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"/><link href="/feeds/misc.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>/</id><updated>2009-12-18T16:39:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>justifying hatred of a word</title><link href="/2009/12/18/justifying-hatred-of-a-word/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-12-18T16:39:00-05:00</published><updated>2009-12-18T16:39:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2009-12-18:/2009/12/18/justifying-hatred-of-a-word/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yglesias &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://yglesias.thinkprogress.org/archives/2009/12/memo-to-michael-wolff-bitch-is-a-sexist-term.php"&gt;responds&lt;/a&gt; to Michael Wolff's ruminations on Chuck Schumer calling a flight attendant a bitch:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...by eliding the term “bitch” he manages to completely avoid the subject of sexism, which I think is at the core of the complaint here. But the term is a pure contentless gender-slur. It’s …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yglesias &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://yglesias.thinkprogress.org/archives/2009/12/memo-to-michael-wolff-bitch-is-a-sexist-term.php"&gt;responds&lt;/a&gt; to Michael Wolff's ruminations on Chuck Schumer calling a flight attendant a bitch:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;...by eliding the term “bitch” he manages to completely avoid the subject of sexism, which I think is at the core of the complaint here. But the term is a pure contentless gender-slur. It’s like you’re saying “I disagree with what you’re doing and also you’re a woman which is a bad thing to be!!!!!!!!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if a woman is doing something legitimately bad, it’s no more appropriate to insult her with that term than it is to break out a racial slur just because a guy you have a legitimate beef with happens to be black. That’s the issue here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Disclaimer: &amp;quot;bitch&amp;quot; is not a term I like nor one that I use. When I hear other people use it, I think less of them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I'm not sure that what Yglesias says above is correct. I wrote something about this years ago, but it came out hopelessly muddled, so let's try again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The difficulty here is in figuring out what we find objectionable about the word. It's easy to become confused by the fact that pejorative language is reserved for unpleasant situations, and give in to the temptation to think that wishing away the word will also make those situations disappear. Yglesias understands that this is stupid way of thinking: people will continue to get upset with one another. And although it's obvious that we should all strive to be pleasant human beings, there's nothing necessarily unjust about expressing your strong dislike for someone. Rather, it's the act of denigration-via-classification embodied by these terms that makes them so odious. This is also correct, I think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the comparison to racist language is problematic. It seems to me that as a society we've pretty much decided that acknowledging racial differences is inappropriate except in very specific circumstances. It sounds a little weird when you put it that way, but I think it's essentially what we've done and that it's basically a good idea -- a custom that pushes human behavior in positive directions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not clear to me that a similar societal decision has been made with respect to gender differences. I say this primarily because most people continue to think it's fine to use gendered pronouns. And if that's all right, I don't necessarily see an inherent problem with gendered pejoratives (though certainly there can be circumstances surrounding their use that are profoundly problematic -- the practical case against the word &amp;quot;bitch&amp;quot; is quite strong, I think). Heroine/hero, she/he, bitch/dick. There's a low-resolution take on the continuum. The fact that only the last pair would strike most people as objectionable makes me think that we're facing the situation I talked about above: wishing that people wouldn't get angry with one another and use harsh language. That's a fine thing to wish for, but I don't think it's got much to do with social justice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other possibility, of course, is that we should be objecting to gendered pronouns with positive or neutral affect (e.g. heroine, she) as well, just the same as we don't use different words for valorous people of different races. I think this is probably correct, but I also think it's probably not a position that most of the people engaging in this debate would find appealing enough on an intuitive level to embrace. Come to think of it, resistance to the social project of eliminating gendered pronouns could easily be the thing that eventually earns the &amp;quot;cultural conservative&amp;quot; trophy for my generation (take heart, though, future young people: we'll be dead before you know it).&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"/></entry><entry><title>studies in musical jerkishness</title><link href="/2009/12/03/studies-in-musical-jerkishness/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-12-03T09:38:00-05:00</published><updated>2009-12-03T09:38:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2009-12-03:/2009/12/03/studies-in-musical-jerkishness/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I still have a whopping seventeen minutes to go until I need to head to the morning's first meeting (I am told there will be pastry), but Twitter means that I &lt;em&gt;already&lt;/em&gt; have compelling internet content to share. To wit!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://virtualista.posterous.com/this-is-not-a-fugazi-montage-0"&gt;Fugazi were dicks&lt;/a&gt;. I realize this was part of the …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I still have a whopping seventeen minutes to go until I need to head to the morning's first meeting (I am told there will be pastry), but Twitter means that I &lt;em&gt;already&lt;/em&gt; have compelling internet content to share. To wit!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://virtualista.posterous.com/this-is-not-a-fugazi-montage-0"&gt;Fugazi were dicks&lt;/a&gt;. I realize this was part of the appeal, even as I simultaneously realize that (having not been a part of the Fugazi fanbase at the time of their relevance) I shouldn't claim to fully understand their appeal. Still, forget the humorlessness, the stories about straight-edge-inspired violence, the earnest para-anarchist nonsense. Just listen to the self-satisfied incredulity in that stage banter (banter admittedly being entirely the wrong word in this case). It's hard to listen to it without cringing for ever having been young.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;div class="first line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.avclub.com/dc/articles/john-davis-defends-his-nonguilty-pleasures,35822/"&gt;John Davis&lt;/a&gt;, on the other hand, proves himself to be kind of a sweetheart, even as he correctly identifies the flaws in the musical abominations that he's decided to stick up for, seemingly because he simply rejects the idea of negativity entirely. I mean, &lt;em&gt;The Pina Colada Song&lt;/em&gt;? That's bold. But it's also sort of strangely big-hearted, and makes me tempted to compare Davis to my friend Chris, which Chris doesn't like because he worries that people with beards all look the same to the rest of us, and that's prejudice.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;There is one problem with Davis' interview, though, and it leaves me in the awkward position of needing to stick up for Dan Snyder. Davis makes the same claim as &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Daniel_Snyder#Six_Flags_theme_park"&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;!--  --&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Snyder eliminated the popular Mr. Six character from Six Flags commercials &lt;sup&gt;[citation needed]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Citation desperately needed! Snyder bought the park in 2005, and I'm certain I've seen Mr. Six dancing away his bankruptcy worries since then. More importantly, it should go without saying that the character was never popular, and rarely even tolerable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="misc"/></entry><entry><title>Gunsmoke!</title><link href="/2009/09/27/gunsmoke/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-09-27T20:59:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-09-27T20:59:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2009-09-27:/2009/09/27/gunsmoke/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Probably the greatest part of the intersection between the late Sunday Chinatown bus and iPhone ownership is the ability to listen to WAMU's weekly installment of &lt;em&gt;The Big Broadcast&lt;/em&gt; without any distractions or even alternatives (thanks, non-functioning reading lights!).&amp;nbsp; Tonight's episode of &lt;em&gt;Gunsmoke&lt;/em&gt; was particularly strong.&amp;nbsp; Not because of any …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Probably the greatest part of the intersection between the late Sunday Chinatown bus and iPhone ownership is the ability to listen to WAMU's weekly installment of &lt;em&gt;The Big Broadcast&lt;/em&gt; without any distractions or even alternatives (thanks, non-functioning reading lights!).&amp;nbsp; Tonight's episode of &lt;em&gt;Gunsmoke&lt;/em&gt; was particularly strong.&amp;nbsp; Not because of any particularly great plot twists or character work.&amp;nbsp; But &lt;strong&gt;man&lt;/strong&gt;, that is how you write a death scene.&amp;nbsp; Also: Matt Dillon makes a compelling case for preventive detention!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm pretty sure that this is the same recording of the episode, though admittedly the radio station seems to have some tape hiss-eliminating filters that make the all-important moments of silence actually silent.&amp;nbsp; Still, worth a listen -- just scour iTunes for the &amp;quot;Dolby B&amp;quot; switch; I'm sure it's in there somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can find a 40M version &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://gunsmoke.libsyn.com/index.php?post_id=291840"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and a hissier (but smaller) version &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.archive.org/download/OTRR_Gunsmoke_Singles/Gunsmoke_53-02-28_045_Trojan_War.mp3"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"/></entry><entry><title>how else can you explain carbon fiber?</title><link href="/2009/07/14/how-else-can-you-explain-carbon-fiber/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-07-14T10:34:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-07-14T10:34:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2009-07-14:/2009/07/14/how-else-can-you-explain-carbon-fiber/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;During my Artomatic shift on Saturday I finished Charles Stross's &lt;em&gt;The Atrocity Archives&lt;/em&gt;, the first in a series of scifi novels that I heard of via Paul Krugman's blog, of all places. The book's conceit is appealing: certain mathematical constructions possess mystical powers — often dangerous ones. Our humble protagonist is …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;During my Artomatic shift on Saturday I finished Charles Stross's &lt;em&gt;The Atrocity Archives&lt;/em&gt;, the first in a series of scifi novels that I heard of via Paul Krugman's blog, of all places. The book's conceit is appealing: certain mathematical constructions possess mystical powers — often dangerous ones. Our humble protagonist is part of a highly specialized, highly secret, and highly bureaucratic arm of the British government devoted to suppressing such dangerous technology. It's Lovecraft + spy thriller + ironic office comedy — brazenly so, to the point where the author breaks down his influences in an irritating postscript essay. Still, it was an enjoyable read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an unexpected bonus (though I probably should have seen it coming), the book's villains include a cadre of Nazi occultists, the sorts of guys who'd love to see a restoration of the Reich, but who, if that doesn't work out, would be perfectly content to settle for the apocalypse. If you've heard me prattle on about Hellboy you know that crazed Nazi sorcerors are among my all-time favorite pulp bad guys (seriously: how much more villainy can you ask of a villain?). So this was a pleasant way for the book to turn out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It got me thinking, though, that there must be some source text that discusses the Nazis' bizarre forays into the occult which has influenced people like Charles Stross, Mike Mignola, and anyone else who's penned a story about Hyperborea, the Spear of Destiny or other WWII-era mystical weirdness. So naturally I started plopping search terms into Amazon, hoping to find a definitive account of the aforementioned malevolent hoodoo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm still looking, but have at least stumbled on an interesting tangent: judging by the name, it's entirely possible that the Nazis' secret occult society escaped the war, laid low, and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.amazon.com/s?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;tag=mozilla-20&amp;amp;index=blended&amp;amp;link_code=qs&amp;amp;field-keywords=thule&amp;amp;sourceid=Mozilla-search"&gt;is now manufacturing car luggage&lt;/a&gt;. More as this story develops.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"/></entry><entry><title>bike lawyers</title><link href="/2009/06/25/bike-lawyers/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-06-25T10:25:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-06-25T10:25:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2009-06-25:/2009/06/25/bike-lawyers/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/sbma44/488788138/"&gt;&lt;img alt="do you think he wears a cape?" class="right" src="http://farm1.static.flickr.com/212/488788138_a86b3a0197.jpg" style="width: 375px; height: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;It's great that &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.tucsonbikelawyer.com/"&gt;this guy&lt;/a&gt; is specializing in cases from cyclists who've been in accidents. But it isn't really necessary. Believe me: if you get a police report filed about your accident (and of course you should — nothing makes an insurance agent happier), personal injury scumbags will wriggle out of …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/sbma44/488788138/"&gt;&lt;img alt="do you think he wears a cape?" class="right" src="http://farm1.static.flickr.com/212/488788138_a86b3a0197.jpg" style="width: 375px; height: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;It's great that &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.tucsonbikelawyer.com/"&gt;this guy&lt;/a&gt; is specializing in cases from cyclists who've been in accidents. But it isn't really necessary. Believe me: if you get a police report filed about your accident (and of course you should — nothing makes an insurance agent happier), personal injury scumbags will wriggle out of the woodwork and plop themselves onto your voicemail almost immediately. When it happened to me I found it pretty annoying, but I suppose it's nice to know that cyclists' rights will be protected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But a legal jihad against drivers won't change anything. At this point I'm convinced that the only way to make cities bike-friendly is to put fellow travelers (so to speak) into positions of power, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://nymag.com/news/features/56794/"&gt;like they've done in NYC&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"/></entry><entry><title>important questions</title><link href="/2009/06/06/important-questions/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-06-06T12:17:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-06-06T12:17:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2009-06-06:/2009/06/06/important-questions/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Emily and I both read and enjoyed &lt;em&gt;World War Z&lt;/em&gt; at the beach. Emily enjoyed it enough to ask that &lt;em&gt;The Zombie Survival Guide&lt;/em&gt; be included among her birthday loot, and it was probably the spirit of that book that led us to discuss the technical specifics of vampire abatement …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Emily and I both read and enjoyed &lt;em&gt;World War Z&lt;/em&gt; at the beach. Emily enjoyed it enough to ask that &lt;em&gt;The Zombie Survival Guide&lt;/em&gt; be included among her birthday loot, and it was probably the spirit of that book that led us to discuss the technical specifics of vampire abatement strategies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, no consensus could be reached, so it falls to you, internet, to weigh in on the feasibility of killing a vampire by driving one of the following objects through its heart:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Painted wood (latex/oil/lacquer (e.g. a pool cue))&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Particle board&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Frozen sawdust and water (&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dsc.discovery.com/fansites/mythbusters/articles/what-is-pykrete.html"&gt;see also&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A cone of tightly-wrapped paper&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Posit that sufficient force is available to overcome problems related to each material's sharpness — we are killing these vampires in a laboratory setting, and for the sake of this argument can safely dismiss practical concerns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emily felt strongly that the wood's semantic status was the primary factor at work, leaving her convinced that option one was the only viable method of disposing of the undead. I disagree completely: I think there must be a chemical mechanism at work, which leads me to expect that methods two and three would unquestionably work, and that method four stands a good chance as well. But I have grave concerns about the use of laminated wood, and frankly am surprised that more vampire fiction doesn't make use of actually-that-stake-was-painted-now-I'm-going-to-bite-you-(SURPRISE!) trope that it makes possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What say you, internet? Remember to show your work.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"/></entry><entry><title>PHB</title><link href="/2009/04/27/phb/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-04-27T12:18:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-04-27T12:18:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2009-04-27:/2009/04/27/phb/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;With apologies to my MBA-possessing friends: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.abc.net.au/rn/backgroundbriefing/stories/2009/2526727.htm"&gt;the case against MBAs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not that the degree's really worthless, of course. As the above-linked transcript acknowledges, it's an admission ticket to certain spheres of money and power. And the introduction to financial and economic concepts that the associated coursework provides is something I …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;With apologies to my MBA-possessing friends: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.abc.net.au/rn/backgroundbriefing/stories/2009/2526727.htm"&gt;the case against MBAs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not that the degree's really worthless, of course. As the above-linked transcript acknowledges, it's an admission ticket to certain spheres of money and power. And the introduction to financial and economic concepts that the associated coursework provides is something I frequently wish I had. But while I won't say that I outright &lt;em&gt;dismissed&lt;/em&gt; any resumes because of it — that wouldn't be very responsible of me — seeing the degree on a programmer's resume has definitely prompted me to record a mental strike against them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In that case it's because I was specifically looking looking for focused technicians. But speaking more broadly, I think the folks quoted in the above-linked transcript are right when they discuss how the brand of generalism afforded by a business education — as distinct from the type produced by a liberal arts education — can be pretty grating to the rest of us, particularly when it's wielded by someone unaware of its limitations. Fortunately, nearly all of the MBAs I know are quick to acknowledge those limits; most of them &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; have an education in something substantial; and none of them, so far as I know, willingly read management books.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anti-business sentiment is obviously at its high water mark right now; other than our normal societal baseline of simmering anti-authoritarianism, we shouldn't expect it to last. But for anyone who's worked under a hapless b-school acolyte, the last few months have been something of a golden age. That they're producing radio programs embodying this resentment (rather than just NBC sitcoms) seems noteworthy.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"/></entry><entry><title>rebranding already?</title><link href="/2009/04/04/rebranding-already/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-04-04T11:46:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-04-04T11:46:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2009-04-04:/2009/04/04/rebranding-already/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image1" class="center" src="http://www.manifestdensity.net/skitch/n%2B1_hipster_thing-20090404-114613.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gag me with a spoon from some little hole in the wall after-hours place in the LES that was supposed to just serve falafel but actually it started to have these awful high school bands sometimes and if you knew the guy he'd sell you big paper cups of Turkish …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image1" class="center" src="http://www.manifestdensity.net/skitch/n%2B1_hipster_thing-20090404-114613.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gag me with a spoon from some little hole in the wall after-hours place in the LES that was supposed to just serve falafel but actually it started to have these awful high school bands sometimes and if you knew the guy he'd sell you big paper cups of Turkish beer and when I tell people this story now I usually say it turned into a Hot Topic because that's funnier but actually I just started hating how young everyone there seemed to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh! Before I forget, I hope you'll join me for my own symposium: &amp;quot;What was the feckless D.C.-based web developer who complains too much?&amp;quot; I mean can you &lt;em&gt;believe&lt;/em&gt; those guys? So lame! Anyway, details to follow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NON-SARCASTICALLY:&lt;/strong&gt; A &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.popmatters.com/pm/post/the-death-of-the-hipster-panel/"&gt;thoughtful after-action report&lt;/a&gt; on the aforementioned affair. Via &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://blogstretch.blogspot.com"&gt;Amanda&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"/></entry><entry><title>I do love conspiracies</title><link href="/2009/03/17/i-do-love-conspiracies/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-03-17T17:49:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-03-17T17:49:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2009-03-17:/2009/03/17/i-do-love-conspiracies/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image1" class="right" src="/static/2009/03/17/illuminati-20090317-183138.png" /&gt;Now that Ezra's &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.prospect.org/csnc/blogs/ezraklein_archive?month=03&amp;amp;year=2009&amp;amp;base_name=obligatory_journolist_post&amp;amp;49"&gt;terrible secret has been revealed&lt;/a&gt;, it seems safe to say that the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.politico.com/news/stories/0309/20086.html"&gt;Politico article&lt;/a&gt; does a pretty piss-poor job of making JournoList sound like a dire liberal conspiracy. It did leave me wondering about another point, though: whether the availability of this sort of back channel is …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image1" class="right" src="/static/2009/03/17/illuminati-20090317-183138.png" /&gt;Now that Ezra's &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.prospect.org/csnc/blogs/ezraklein_archive?month=03&amp;amp;year=2009&amp;amp;base_name=obligatory_journolist_post&amp;amp;49"&gt;terrible secret has been revealed&lt;/a&gt;, it seems safe to say that the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.politico.com/news/stories/0309/20086.html"&gt;Politico article&lt;/a&gt; does a pretty piss-poor job of making JournoList sound like a dire liberal conspiracy. It did leave me wondering about another point, though: whether the availability of this sort of back channel is one of the factors that's led to the blogosphere's diminished vibrancy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's an obvious advantage to moving the social and argument-refining functions of online conversation to a venue where participants aren't exposed to the risks of misinterpretation, prudishness or unreasonably high expectations. Opting for a listserv post instead of a trackback means no public castigation for stupid mistakes and no worrying about an occasional thoughtless (or just really funny) remark getting you in trouble with your employer. And, as Ezra points out, it's better to have wary experts offer their wisdom in private than not at all. Besides, it's not like participants are giving up much by foregoing the contributions of the slack-jawed commentariat during this process (aside: I remain baffled by well-meaning web triumphalists' calls for the use of technology to enable more direct participation in the policy process — have they spent &lt;em&gt;any&lt;/em&gt; time in blog comment sections?).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's hard to begrudge anyone this sort of professional conservatism, particularly when their industry is in turmoil. I certainly engage in similar behaviors when I find them advantageous. But it does seem likely to me that there's a homogenizing effect that comes from blog-labor-saving devices like mailing lists and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.memeorandum.com/"&gt;memeorandum&lt;/a&gt;. As a fan of these writers I'm glad for anything that makes their work easier, but as a member of the reading public I have to admit: it's kind of a drag to know that the blogosphere's efforts to improve itself have led to its audience being protected from so much interesting content.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"/></entry><entry><title>we make art not money</title><link href="/2009/03/05/we-make-art-not-money/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-03-05T17:53:00-05:00</published><updated>2009-03-05T17:53:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2009-03-05:/2009/03/05/we-make-art-not-money/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;On the off chance that you missed it, let me encourage you to go read &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://yglesias.thinkprogress.org/archives/2009/03/missing_productivity_and_the_rise_of_social_production.php"&gt;Matt's post about our economic shift toward producing wealth that doesn't generate revenue&lt;/a&gt;. This is a topic that fascinates me — I've &lt;a class="reference external" href="/2007/10/10/wealth-but-no-wages/"&gt;poked at&lt;/a&gt; it &lt;a class="reference external" href="/2007/04/20/giant-nazi-robots/"&gt;before&lt;/a&gt;, but of course Matt's take is considerably smarter and more …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On the off chance that you missed it, let me encourage you to go read &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://yglesias.thinkprogress.org/archives/2009/03/missing_productivity_and_the_rise_of_social_production.php"&gt;Matt's post about our economic shift toward producing wealth that doesn't generate revenue&lt;/a&gt;. This is a topic that fascinates me — I've &lt;a class="reference external" href="/2007/10/10/wealth-but-no-wages/"&gt;poked at&lt;/a&gt; it &lt;a class="reference external" href="/2007/04/20/giant-nazi-robots/"&gt;before&lt;/a&gt;, but of course Matt's take is considerably smarter and more rigorous than any conclusions I've ever reached. His perspective also happens to be cheerier than my own — I remain somewhat pessimistic about the ultimate economic consequences of these changes, even as I find myself looking forward to their effect on our society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The good news, though, is that I don't actually know anything about economics, so for now let's all just assume that everything will be fine.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"/></entry><entry><title>more backlogged blogging</title><link href="/2009/03/04/more-backlogged-blogging/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-03-04T13:43:00-05:00</published><updated>2009-03-04T13:43:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2009-03-04:/2009/03/04/more-backlogged-blogging/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Small complaints that I will file here instead of on Twitter:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;Installing MS Office 2008 seems to have affected the default line height of text on this blog when viewed in my browser. I know, you think I'm imagining it — but consider the fact that all text disappeared from the …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Small complaints that I will file here instead of on Twitter:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;Installing MS Office 2008 seems to have affected the default line height of text on this blog when viewed in my browser. I know, you think I'm imagining it — but consider the fact that all text disappeared from the browser during the installation process (and only came back when I restarted Firefox). Weird, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;Russian dressing seems to me to just be a flimsy attempt to approximate cheese while keeping reuben sandwiches kosher. This is understandable, but we shouldn't let cultural traditions that are relevant for only a small subset of the population hold the rest of us back from scientific progression in the field of sandwiches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;(It's true, of course, that you can find non-kosher reubens, but I still feel that the historical burden of religion has prevented the quest for a superior reuben condiment from receiving the attention it deserves.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content><category term="misc"/></entry><entry><title>mojo rising</title><link href="/2009/02/13/mojo-rising/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-02-13T11:39:00-05:00</published><updated>2009-02-13T11:39:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2009-02-13:/2009/02/13/mojo-rising/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm a day late, but still want to congratulate the folks at EchoDitto and the MJ web team for successfully launching the new &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.motherjones.com"&gt;Mother Jones.com&lt;/a&gt;. I worked on the new MoJo site for my last few months at &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.echoditto.com"&gt;EchoDitto&lt;/a&gt;, and leaving the project incomplete was one of the major …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm a day late, but still want to congratulate the folks at EchoDitto and the MJ web team for successfully launching the new &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.motherjones.com"&gt;Mother Jones.com&lt;/a&gt;. I worked on the new MoJo site for my last few months at &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.echoditto.com"&gt;EchoDitto&lt;/a&gt;, and leaving the project incomplete was one of the major qualms I had about leaving — I got to work with a lot of cool clients at ED, but it's hard to think of one I was happier about than Mother Jones. I know it's been an at-times painful process (it always is), but it's great to see what I left behind turned into the new site.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"/></entry><entry><title>elsewhere!</title><link href="/2009/02/09/elsewhere/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-02-09T23:49:00-05:00</published><updated>2009-02-09T23:49:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2009-02-09:/2009/02/09/elsewhere/</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://internetfoodassociation.com/"&gt;Beerventures at the IFA&lt;/a&gt;. Then someone says he doesn't like my writing and I curse at him! Ah, to live a life of letters.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"/></entry><entry><title>more self-evident declarations</title><link href="/2009/01/29/more-self-evident-declarations/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-01-29T09:19:00-05:00</published><updated>2009-01-29T09:19:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2009-01-29:/2009/01/29/more-self-evident-declarations/</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;You know whose tumblr is good? Keith Gessen's &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://keithgessen.tumblr.com/post/71632658"&gt;tumblr&lt;/a&gt; is &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://keithgessen.tumblr.com/post/72551274"&gt;good&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"/></entry><entry><title>things that should be obvious</title><link href="/2009/01/28/things-that-should-be-obvious/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-01-28T15:49:00-05:00</published><updated>2009-01-28T15:49:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2009-01-28:/2009/01/28/things-that-should-be-obvious/</id><content type="html">&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Left_4_dead"&gt;Left 4 Dead&lt;/a&gt; is really fun. Charles and I have been merrily making zombie heads explode for the last two nights. Thanks, Emily!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://pygmalioninablanket.blogspot.com/2009/01/curious-case-of-why-im-going-to-murder.html"&gt;Pygmalion in a Blanket is extremely, ludicrously funny&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</content><category term="misc"/></entry><entry><title>Chick lit</title><link href="/2009/01/06/chick-lit/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-01-06T21:41:00-05:00</published><updated>2009-01-06T21:41:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2009-01-06:/2009/01/06/chick-lit/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We live in a pretty Jehovah's-Witness-heavy neighborhood, but I mostly don't mind. Sure, it means the occasional well-meaning pair of Sunday visitors will find me groggily staring at them, potentially shirtless. But that's mostly their problem — I'm perfectly happy to see them. Besides, you never know when you'll find yourself …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We live in a pretty Jehovah's-Witness-heavy neighborhood, but I mostly don't mind. Sure, it means the occasional well-meaning pair of Sunday visitors will find me groggily staring at them, potentially shirtless. But that's mostly their problem — I'm perfectly happy to see them. Besides, you never know when you'll find yourself wishing you had a few dozen copies of &lt;em&gt;The Watchtower&lt;/em&gt; on hand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best side effect, though, are the hand-addressed notes I get in the mail, which contain handwritten notes, which contain printed tracts, and all of which contain numerous spelling and grammatical errors. Still, they're preferable to the ones I used to find placed under my windshield wipers back when I had the car with &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://flickr.com/photos/sbma44/89423228/in/set-72057594051841686/"&gt;the awful front-end damage&lt;/a&gt;; those would encourage me to seek help for my alcoholism (lucky guesses don't count!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, here's the latest one I've received. In most respects it's pretty unremarkable, but does make a case for Bible study that I don't remember encountering before: that it will protect you from &lt;em&gt;zombies and/or ghosts&lt;/em&gt;. Possibly also draculas; I'm not sure, it's been a while since Sunday School.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/sbma44/3175013187/"&gt;&lt;img alt="god promises freedom from zombies!" class="center" src="http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3257/3175013187_eaa81e7aa9_o.jpg" style="width: 500px; height: 464px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"/></entry><entry><title>ShamWow, indeed</title><link href="/2009/01/06/shamwow-indeed/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-01-06T09:23:00-05:00</published><updated>2009-01-06T09:23:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2009-01-06:/2009/01/06/shamwow-indeed/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Look, I don't know what &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://pygmalioninablanket.blogspot.com/2009/01/guess-whos-back-to-work-thats-right-you.html"&gt;you&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://blogstretch.blogspot.com/"&gt;guys&lt;/a&gt; have against Vince or &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.shamwow.com/ver4/index.asp"&gt;ShamWow&lt;/a&gt;, the revolutionary new absorption concept that is sweeping — well, if not the nation, then at least the parts of it that watch TBS at 1am. But this mean-spiritedness has got to stop. Yes, it's clear that Vince had …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Look, I don't know what &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://pygmalioninablanket.blogspot.com/2009/01/guess-whos-back-to-work-thats-right-you.html"&gt;you&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://blogstretch.blogspot.com/"&gt;guys&lt;/a&gt; have against Vince or &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.shamwow.com/ver4/index.asp"&gt;ShamWow&lt;/a&gt;, the revolutionary new absorption concept that is sweeping — well, if not the nation, then at least the parts of it that watch TBS at 1am. But this mean-spiritedness has got to stop. Yes, it's clear that Vince had been awake for at least 50 hours when that commercial was filmed. And yes, he is an &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vince_Offer"&gt;ex-Scientologist who sued Anna Nicole Smith for breach of contract&lt;/a&gt; in relation to his failed gross-out comedy movie (the New York Times called it &amp;quot;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://query.nytimes.com/gst/fullpage.html?res=9805EFDF1F31F93BA15756C0A96F958260&amp;amp;scp=1&amp;amp;sq=underground+comedy+movie&amp;amp;st=nyt"&gt;a monument to ineptitude and self-delusion&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what's the alternative? This is a subject that Charles, Emily and I have discussed at length. Vince may not be perfect — he's just a human being, as flawed and beautiful as any of us — but at least he has the guts to stand up to Billy Mays and the grasping tentacles of his infomercial syndicate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I'll be the first to acknowledge Mr. Mays' impressive achievements. But his time has passed; it's clear that these days, his heart's not in it. Worse, his &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.asseenontvvideo.com/487/Zorbeez.html"&gt;Zorbeez project&lt;/a&gt; is a transparent attempt to destroy Vince and the ShamWow, no matter the cost (how else can one explain his proffer of a $60 value for a mere $14.99?!). Doesn't America deserve a fresh new face to sell us oddly-shaped cooking implements and citrus-based cleaning products? Can we really sanction the sort of anticompetitive behavior that Mr. Mays represents?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I say yes! And no! Respectively! Vince may not deserve your love, but when, every night, his shaking hands remove that headset — in that moment he at least deserves your respect. And your order, of course. Call now.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"/></entry><entry><title>one for me, one for you</title><link href="/2009/01/05/one-for-me-one-for-you/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-01-05T09:17:00-05:00</published><updated>2009-01-05T09:17:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2009-01-05:/2009/01/05/one-for-me-one-for-you/</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Guess who I've been shopping for this season...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/sbma44/3170803692/"&gt;&lt;img alt="20090105_amazon" class="center" src="http://farm4.static.flickr.com/3119/3170803692_29ec3edc62_o.jpg" style="width: 500px; height: 265px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"/></entry><entry><title>IFA</title><link href="/2008/11/12/ifa/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-11-12T20:18:00-05:00</published><updated>2008-11-12T20:18:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2008-11-12:/2008/11/12/ifa/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was remiss in not posting this earlier: a bunch of friends have started up &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://internetfoodassociation.wordpress.com/"&gt;The Internet Food Association&lt;/a&gt;, and have been nice enough to ask me (end Emily, and probably other people you know) to contribute to it. If you think you might enjoy hearing me hold forth pretentiously …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was remiss in not posting this earlier: a bunch of friends have started up &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://internetfoodassociation.wordpress.com/"&gt;The Internet Food Association&lt;/a&gt;, and have been nice enough to ask me (end Emily, and probably other people you know) to contribute to it. If you think you might enjoy hearing me hold forth pretentiously about beer, go subscribe to the feed.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"/></entry><entry><title>the Post kills some spammers</title><link href="/2008/11/12/the-post-kills-some-spammers/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-11-12T12:10:00-05:00</published><updated>2008-11-12T12:10:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2008-11-12:/2008/11/12/the-post-kills-some-spammers/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's no secret that &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://twitter.com/cshirky/status/998786410"&gt;the newspaper industry is in trouble&lt;/a&gt;. Still, give our hometown paper credit for trying new business models. Last week we saw the Post &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dcist.com/2008/11/05/special_edition_washington_post_to.php"&gt;move strongly into the &amp;quot;collectible knick-knack&amp;quot; market&lt;/a&gt;. This week? &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/11/12/AR2008111200658_pf.html"&gt;They're trying their hand at becoming a network security firm / law enforcement agency&lt;/a&gt; (this …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's no secret that &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://twitter.com/cshirky/status/998786410"&gt;the newspaper industry is in trouble&lt;/a&gt;. Still, give our hometown paper credit for trying new business models. Last week we saw the Post &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dcist.com/2008/11/05/special_edition_washington_post_to.php"&gt;move strongly into the &amp;quot;collectible knick-knack&amp;quot; market&lt;/a&gt;. This week? &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2008/11/12/AR2008111200658_pf.html"&gt;They're trying their hand at becoming a network security firm / law enforcement agency&lt;/a&gt; (this via &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://twitter.com/tbridge/status/1002184031"&gt;Tom Bridge&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Snark aside, this really is a pretty impressive accomplishment for a journalist. Brian Krebs' reporting led directly to a major spam colocation facility getting knocked offline by its upstream bandwidth providers. The result is reportedly a staggering &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://voices.washingtonpost.com/securityfix/2008/11/major_source_of_online_scams_a.html"&gt;75% overnight drop in net-wide spam&lt;/a&gt;. That won't last, of course, but it's still awfully impressive. (Incidentally, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.zunta.org/blog/archives/2006/02/18/interposse/"&gt;this isn't the first time&lt;/a&gt; that the Post has caused trouble for botnet operators.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not to diminish Krebs' accomplishment, but the ease with which this was done — a civilian making some phone calls, basically — also hints at the lameness of our law enforcement agencies' online efforts. This was a U.S. company that was plainly harboring illegal activity. Krebs spoke to some security researchers who let him know about it, then he called the folks providing the malefactors' network connections. Those providers said &amp;quot;wow! you're right!&amp;quot; and pulled the plug. It took time, initiative, and cleverness (the threat of Krebs' bully pulpit helped, no doubt), but it didn't take any warrants or indictments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the people nominally charged with prosecuting these sorts of crimes are — what? Posing as sexy teens in chatrooms? Fretting about cyberterrorism? It was, admittedly, the Army, not law enforcement, that published the recent &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.breitbart.com/article.php?id=081025182242.js2g2op8&amp;amp;show_article=1"&gt;asinine report examining Twitter's capacity for supporting terrorists' activities&lt;/a&gt;. Still, that mindset seems to be pervasive: people just don't get very excited about going after online criminals who steal money and productivity. Instead electronic crime needs to be blown up into an existential threat — it's about terrorists! Or hostile foreign governments! Or sexual predators! What it really is is a waste of time and money.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="misc"/></entry></feed>