<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Tom Lee - music, pop culture</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"/><link href="/feeds/music-pop-culture.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>/</id><updated>2007-11-25T13:20:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>give-a give-a give-a Garmin</title><link href="/2007/11/25/give-a-give-a-give-a-garmin/" rel="alternate"/><published>2007-11-25T13:20:00-05:00</published><updated>2007-11-25T13:20:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2007-11-25:/2007/11/25/give-a-give-a-give-a-garmin/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I woke up about fifteen minutes ago and turned the Redskins game on. Since then the following entities have used &amp;quot;The Carol of the Bells&amp;quot; to try to sell me things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Garmin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wal-mart&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hyundai&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Verizon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hyundai, again&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, I don't really mind having beloved parts of our shared culture …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I woke up about fifteen minutes ago and turned the Redskins game on. Since then the following entities have used &amp;quot;The Carol of the Bells&amp;quot; to try to sell me things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Garmin&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Wal-mart&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hyundai&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Verizon&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hyundai, again&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general, I don't really mind having beloved parts of our shared culture appropriated by the great campaign to sell me injection-molded plastic from Shengzhou. But I am going to have to insist on a little more variety. Why so much &amp;quot;Carol of the Bells&amp;quot;? I suppose it's got &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.stlyrics.com/lyrics/homealone/carolofthebells.htm"&gt;secular lyrics&lt;/a&gt;, which discourages the religious crazies from writing letters about how Jesus dislikes crass materialism and would prefer that we save our money for war with Iran. But mostly I think it's because it's one of the most lonely, haunting holiday songs, if not because of how it sounds then at least because it was used to that effect in &lt;em&gt;Home Alone&lt;/em&gt;. This makes people think about sitting alone in the fading light of a winter day, left to wonder where their family is. Wouldn't you rather spend that time carefully reading the manual to your new GPS unit?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whatever happened to all those Gap ads where shame-faced musicians would listlessly plod through rocked-up carols? I need some more of those. I know Gap's been facing some financial trouble, but I'd be willing to write my congressman about a federal bailout if only they'd promise to get, say, My Chemical Romance to tear through an emo version of Handel's Messiah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At any rate, here's the only version of &amp;quot;Carol of the Bells&amp;quot; that I actually want to see on my television:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's even better than &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://youtube.com/watch?v=87wGHfAi17Q&amp;amp;feature=related"&gt;the version of &amp;quot;We Three Kings&amp;quot; with the swingin' camels&lt;/a&gt;. I &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.google.com/search?q=%22moonwalking%20camels%22"&gt;could've sworn&lt;/a&gt; those camels moonwalked, but YouTube disagrees.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="music, pop culture"/></entry><entry><title>the international language of spookiness</title><link href="/2007/10/31/the-international-language-of-spookiness/" rel="alternate"/><published>2007-10-31T17:58:00-04:00</published><updated>2007-10-31T17:58:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2007-10-31:/2007/10/31/the-international-language-of-spookiness/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image1" class="center" src="http://myskitch.com/sbma44/dnevnoy_dozor__2006_-20071031-175523.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/Torrentfreak/~3/177397467/"&gt;Torrentfreak says&lt;/a&gt; that &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0409904/"&gt;Day Watch&lt;/a&gt; is the number one DVD rip on the internet. Weird! Not so much because it reflects non-US internet use (there's a reason LiveJournal is still around, after all), but because Emily and I downloaded an English-subtitled version back in August that sure &lt;em&gt;looked&lt;/em&gt; like a …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image1" class="center" src="http://myskitch.com/sbma44/dnevnoy_dozor__2006_-20071031-175523.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/Torrentfreak/~3/177397467/"&gt;Torrentfreak says&lt;/a&gt; that &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0409904/"&gt;Day Watch&lt;/a&gt; is the number one DVD rip on the internet. Weird! Not so much because it reflects non-US internet use (there's a reason LiveJournal is still around, after all), but because Emily and I downloaded an English-subtitled version back in August that sure &lt;em&gt;looked&lt;/em&gt; like a DVD rip. What gives?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While I'm mentioning potential Hallomedia (and before my chance completely slips by), give this track a listen — it's the best of a well-intentioned but mostly-awful &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.solcofn.com/Halloween.htm"&gt;Halloween mashup compilation&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.solcofn.com/media/Son%20of%20Monster%20Mash/7.%20Halloween%20with%20morrissey%20-%20Cheekyboy.mp3"&gt;Cheekyboy – Halloween with Morrissey&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.informationleafblower.com"&gt;Kyle&lt;/a&gt; is &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; spending Halloween with Morrissey. This is the next best thing.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="music, pop culture"/></entry></feed>