<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Tom Lee - personal, tech</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"/><link href="/feeds/personal-tech.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>/</id><updated>2008-04-02T13:51:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Virgin America: still evil, but now defeatable</title><link href="/2008/04/02/virgin-america-still-evil-but-now-defeatable/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-04-02T13:51:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-04-02T13:51:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2008-04-02:/2008/04/02/virgin-america-still-evil-but-now-defeatable/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Alright, a workaround. Clearing cookies didn't work. Switching browsers didn't work. What did work was clearing cookies and then sending my traffic through a SOCKS proxy server on the west coast. After doing so I was able to get the fare that had been &lt;a class="reference external" href="/2008/04/02/thanks-virgin-america/"&gt;quoted to me, then snapped away …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Alright, a workaround. Clearing cookies didn't work. Switching browsers didn't work. What did work was clearing cookies and then sending my traffic through a SOCKS proxy server on the west coast. After doing so I was able to get the fare that had been &lt;a class="reference external" href="/2008/04/02/thanks-virgin-america/"&gt;quoted to me, then snapped away&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conspiracy-minded (e.g. me) will conclude that Virgin America keeps a list of IP addresses and, based on your fare-browsing activity, gradually increases prices in an effort to make you snap up a ticket before it gets any more expensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more sane among you will recognize that the West coast is three hours behind me, and that the fare increase may be related to the time of day at which I was shopping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Either way, jerking around your users in this manner — the way the entire airline industry does — is sleazy behavior. If you're booking airfare and can send your packets through a western time zone, I recommend doing so.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="personal, tech"/></entry><entry><title>the war is over</title><link href="/2008/03/20/the-war-is-over/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-03-20T13:34:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-03-20T13:34:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2008-03-20:/2008/03/20/the-war-is-over/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ben Franklin is frequently quoted as having said &amp;quot;Beer is proof that God loves us and wants us to be happy.&amp;quot; Let's extend a bit further the use of consumer goods as a tool for fathoming the inscrutable motives of the omnipotent: the cable company DVR is proof that Comcast …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ben Franklin is frequently quoted as having said &amp;quot;Beer is proof that God loves us and wants us to be happy.&amp;quot; Let's extend a bit further the use of consumer goods as a tool for fathoming the inscrutable motives of the omnipotent: the cable company DVR is proof that Comcast hates you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Charles and I have had a lot of audiovisual excitement over the past few months; the Comcast DVR was &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://twitter.com/calamityjake/statuses/774194863"&gt;a low point&lt;/a&gt;. You might think that the &amp;quot;last&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;exit&amp;quot; buttons would each behave in a consistent manner regardless whether you're in the &amp;quot;On Demand&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;Settings&amp;quot; menus, but you'd be wrong. You might think that a device aimed at people who've just blown a lot of money on a fancy new TV wouldn't employ a bargain basement upconverter that leaves everything rife with MPEG artifacts, but you'd be wrong. You might think that you wouldn't have to look at advertisements every time you try to search a schedule of shows you've already paid for, but — wait, how naive &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; you?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.yovanoff.com"&gt;Jason&lt;/a&gt; let me know that &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.woot.com"&gt;Woot&lt;/a&gt; was offering a great deal on refurbished Tivo HDs and I jumped on it. Yesterday Comcast sent a guy over to install the requisite cable card, and I've been happily BOOPing and BABOOPing since. Man, is it great. Yeah, it's a little more sluggish than the DirecTivo we used to have. But it's comforting just the same. And, crucially, I no longer feel like a malevolent machine intelligence is sitting under my TV, whiling away its endless sentence in Ikea prison by subjecting me to subtle psychological torture. &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chain_of_Command_(Star_Trek:_The_Next_Generation)"&gt;THERE ARE FOUR (front panel) LIGHTS!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="personal, tech"/></entry><entry><title>xbox live</title><link href="/2008/01/07/xbox-live/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-01-07T11:01:00-05:00</published><updated>2008-01-07T11:01:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2008-01-07:/2008/01/07/xbox-live/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As part of the holiday season's string of irresponsible purchases I picked up an Xbox 360. I haven't been playing very much so far, and what I have been playing is pretty exclusively Halo 3. But it seems likely that Charles and I will acquire some other digital entertainments in …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;As part of the holiday season's string of irresponsible purchases I picked up an Xbox 360. I haven't been playing very much so far, and what I have been playing is pretty exclusively Halo 3. But it seems likely that Charles and I will acquire some other digital entertainments in the future, so if you're on Xbox Live you should add us to your friends list regardless of how you feel about sort-of-lame first person shooters set in decidedly lame, transparently derivative sci-fi universes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sigh. I miss Quake 3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At any rate, our gamertag is &amp;quot;Club Loser&amp;quot;, which is not at all coincidentally what we called Jeff's videogame-filled basement during middle and high school. Come teach this n00b a lesson.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="personal, tech"/></entry><entry><title>fun with lightbox (and booze!)</title><link href="/2006/10/26/fun-with-lightbox-and-booze/" rel="alternate"/><published>2006-10-26T01:50:00-04:00</published><updated>2006-10-26T01:50:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2006-10-26:/2006/10/26/fun-with-lightbox-and-booze/</id><summary type="html">&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;I visited Emily in Philadelphia last weekend — conveniently enough, she and her neighbors had all decided to throw a party on Saturday. The apartments all adjoin a nice brick courtyard, providing a pretty prime party location. The food was great, the booze was plentiful, and talk eventually turned to the …&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;I visited Emily in Philadelphia last weekend — conveniently enough, she and her neighbors had all decided to throw a party on Saturday. The apartments all adjoin a nice brick courtyard, providing a pretty prime party location. The food was great, the booze was plentiful, and talk eventually turned to the the Flickr API and how to use microcontrollers to train cats to use the toilet (this was not a theoretical conversation). And there was mulled cider. C'mon, admit it: that's pretty good.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Anyway, it was a lot of fun. And as you might imagine, there are pictures. But I wouldn't be doing justice to a party at which I discussed the Flickr API with multiple people if I didn't do &lt;em&gt;something&lt;/em&gt; weird with the photoset. So check it out: I've written a handy wrapper function in PHP that lets me quickly generate thumbnail galleries. Even better, they make use of the excellent &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.huddletogether.com/projects/lightbox2/"&gt;Lightbox2 project&lt;/a&gt;. Go ahead — click on one of the thumbnails for web 2.0-y goodness. It works pretty well for me, although to exit picture-viewing mode I seem to have to click above or below the photo — clicking to its right or left seems relatively flakey.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE:&lt;/strong&gt; Replaced my own code with a WP plugin after moving from MT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[flickr]set:72157594345290445[/flickr]&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="personal, tech"/></entry></feed>