<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Tom Lee - photos</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"/><link href="/feeds/photos.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>/</id><updated>2007-10-31T15:52:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>also, there was Halloween</title><link href="/2007/10/31/also-there-was-halloween/" rel="alternate"/><published>2007-10-31T15:52:00-04:00</published><updated>2007-10-31T15:52:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2007-10-31:/2007/10/31/also-there-was-halloween/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Right, Halloween: it's already happened, as far as I'm concerned. I'm exhausted, haven't been to the gym in ages, and have a ton of work to finish. I intend to nod approvingly as Charles hands out the massive quantities of candy that he bought, but my holiday celebrations occurred last …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Right, Halloween: it's already happened, as far as I'm concerned. I'm exhausted, haven't been to the gym in ages, and have a ton of work to finish. I intend to nod approvingly as Charles hands out the massive quantities of candy that he bought, but my holiday celebrations occurred last Saturday. I think I'm even skipping out on a fun-sounding bar outing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But last weekend was pretty great. Here's a shot of me as Dr. Doom, looking disoriented:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/sbma44/1808541769/"&gt;&lt;img alt="Doom, disoriented" class="center" src="http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2028/1808541769_4360610e5c.jpg" style="width: 500px; height: 375px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://flickr.com/photos/48199512&amp;#64;N00/1793946986/in/set-72157602766722812/"&gt;here's&lt;/a&gt; a shot of me fighting Galactus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few things learned during the costume construction process:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;I think Dr. Doom probably makes his own outfits. If you find yourself in possession of a lot of green fabric, an enthusiasm for diabolical technology and little to no sewing skill, a Doomesque cape and tunic combo is a not-unlikely result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;Dr. Doom's &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.thesmoothdj.com/DrDoom_Head.jpg"&gt;enthusiasm for goblets&lt;/a&gt; is born of necessity: it's really hard to hold onto a beverage while wearing gauntlets. Cupping your drink from beneath is really the only viable strategy. The fact that it looks good when paired with a menacing glower is just a happy coincidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/2007/10/11/part-of-my-halloween-costume/"&gt;Negative ion generators&lt;/a&gt; are a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.afrotechmods.com/cheap/negativeiongenerator/pikashoe7.htm"&gt;nice&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://phrets.com/electrifried/"&gt;idea&lt;/a&gt;, but they're also likely to stop working pretty quickly. And you need to think seriously about electrical isolation if you want to build up any kind of charge — ancient sneakers spraypainted silver (and paired with a cape that occasionally drags) are not the best way to keep voltage from leaking into the ground. I managed to give a few people pinprick shocks before the whole thing stopped working, but it mostly served to gently electrocute my right foot. Overall, it was a bit of a disappointment (although thankfully not a very expensive one).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I got some late advice from Dan Rutter of DansData.com, which may be useful for aspiring Dooms:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;You might like to try buying one of those &amp;quot;shocking&amp;quot; lighters or pens&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;that're all over eBay and joke shops these days; they're basically&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;just a little Tesla coil inside, I think, and it ought to be quite&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;easy to hack one into a shock-glove.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;(A friend of mine made a rather higher powered version of the same&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;thing years ago, and installed it in a small project box with&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;external contacts, a button, and a label that said &amp;quot;DO NOT PRESS&amp;quot;.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Needless to say, people picked it up, and pressed the button, and&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;sometimes then smashed themselves in the face with the box. :-)&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sounds promising. Next year: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electro_%28comics%29"&gt;Electro&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At any rate, here are the rest of my photos from the evening. As you might notice, there are kind of a lot of shots of a jack o'lantern sitting in front of a smoke machine's output hose. That's because this is &lt;em&gt;totally awesome&lt;/em&gt; and should enthrall the lot of you the way it does me. Some people will tell you that on Saturday night I could often be found stumbling around the shrubs, fiddling with the smoke machine. More responsible accounts of the evening will reflect the fact that A) it takes a lot of work to maintain an optimally foggy environment for the enjoyment of all and B) it's pretty hard to navigate a garden while wearing a cape and cardboard armor regardless of how many beers you've just consumed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[flickr]set:72157602811270206[/flickr]&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="photos"/></entry><entry><title>part of my Halloween costume</title><link href="/2007/10/11/part-of-my-halloween-costume/" rel="alternate"/><published>2007-10-11T13:17:00-04:00</published><updated>2007-10-11T13:17:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2007-10-11:/2007/10/11/part-of-my-halloween-costume/</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/sbma44/1544175236/"&gt;&lt;img alt="part of my Halloween costume" class="center" src="http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2085/1544175236_ab1a06d1b2.jpg" style="width: 500px; height: 375px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Can you guess what it is? Winner gets to not be subjected to it. And no fair guessing if I've already told you.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="photos"/></entry><entry><title>more in sadness than in anger</title><link href="/2007/05/01/more-in-sadness-than-in-anger/" rel="alternate"/><published>2007-05-01T17:13:00-04:00</published><updated>2007-05-01T17:13:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2007-05-01:/2007/05/01/more-in-sadness-than-in-anger/</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Pretty pathetic:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/sbma44/480440804/"&gt;&lt;img alt="more in sadness than in anger" class="center" src="http://farm1.static.flickr.com/229/480440804_d8cf8a5b03_o.jpg" style="width: 564px; height: 471px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="photos"/></entry><entry><title>new header</title><link href="/2007/04/23/new-header-2/" rel="alternate"/><published>2007-04-23T14:38:00-04:00</published><updated>2007-04-23T14:38:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2007-04-23:/2007/04/23/new-header-2/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Courtesy of a Saturday visit to the National Arboretum (or Arbotreeum, as one cellphone-using patron near us called it). It's pretty nice out there, and easy to get to on the weekend thanks to the X6 bus. In fact, it's so pleasant that you can easily forget how close you …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Courtesy of a Saturday visit to the National Arboretum (or Arbotreeum, as one cellphone-using patron near us called it). It's pretty nice out there, and easy to get to on the weekend thanks to the X6 bus. In fact, it's so pleasant that you can easily forget how close you are to the Washington Times building.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They've got a bunch of plants &amp;amp; stuff, I guess, but my botanical photography skills are pretty poor. This seemed worth showing, though: DC's state tree. It's surprisingly non-crappy, especially compared to, say, Indiana. Now &lt;em&gt;there's&lt;/em&gt; a sorry-ass tree.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/sbma44/470180314/"&gt;&lt;img alt="DC's state tree" class="center" src="http://farm1.static.flickr.com/201/470180314_4997a77f71.jpg" style="width: 375px; height: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="photos"/></entry><entry><title>californiaaaaa</title><link href="/2007/03/27/californiaaaaa/" rel="alternate"/><published>2007-03-27T15:31:00-04:00</published><updated>2007-03-27T15:31:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2007-03-27:/2007/03/27/californiaaaaa/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Let's not leave things on a down note. You know what I haven't posted yet? Photos of California. So here they are — the best ones, anyway. The full set of at-least-vaguely-redeemable photos can be found &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/sbma44/sets/72157600030591614/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wish I'd taken more shots of my friends, any of my relatives, and …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Let's not leave things on a down note. You know what I haven't posted yet? Photos of California. So here they are — the best ones, anyway. The full set of at-least-vaguely-redeemable photos can be found &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/sbma44/sets/72157600030591614/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wish I'd taken more shots of my friends, any of my relatives, and fewer pitcures of natural splendor — pictures of the first two are usually pretty fun, and pictures of the latter are usually kind of a letdown next to the real thing. But there are a few decent pics in there that at least hint at how astoundingly beautiful &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.nps.gov/pore/"&gt;Point Reyes&lt;/a&gt; is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But of course the highlight of the trip wasn't any of the touristy crap, but rather just getting the chance to see folks I hadn't in a while. It was really good to meet up with &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.mp3.com/users/Jon47/profile.php"&gt;Jon&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.jeffnye.org"&gt;Jeff&lt;/a&gt;, Marie and Paul, and to meet Paul's girlfriend. And seeing Noree, Ron, Jeb and Mimi was wonderful. I really can't thank Jeff &amp;amp; Marie and Noree &amp;amp; Ron enough for putting us up. Berkeley is a pretty great location for a California vacation home base, it turns out. Not only because it's walkable and close to the BART, but also because &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.yelp.com/biz/8xJosknJdcPGPUQ4Pod99w"&gt;co-op pizza&lt;/a&gt; is GREAT pizza. You can really taste the collectivism — delicious, delicious collectivism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[flickr]set:72157600030915186[/flickr]&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="photos"/></entry></feed>