<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Tom Lee - politics</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/feeds/politics.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>https://tomlee.wtf/</id><updated>2010-01-12T12:12:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>in which my ignorance of finance is revealed</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2010/01/12/in-which-my-ignorance-of-finance-is-revealed/" rel="alternate"/><published>2010-01-12T12:12:00-05:00</published><updated>2010-01-12T12:12:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2010-01-12:/2010/01/12/in-which-my-ignorance-of-finance-is-revealed/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Not to me, anyway.&amp;nbsp; But I think that perhaps I could just use some further explanation from people smarter than myself about how the financial system works.&amp;nbsp; So consider this a plea for help -- one that I would've issued over Twitter, if Twitter's character limit was 2300% larger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Not to me, anyway.&amp;nbsp; But I think that perhaps I could just use some further explanation from people smarter than myself about how the financial system works.&amp;nbsp; So consider this a plea for help -- one that I would've issued over Twitter, if Twitter's character limit was 2300% larger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, the problem: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2010/01/11/AR2010011103892.html?hpid=topnews"&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; makes the case that the Federal Reserve has been having a very profitable year:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Fed will return about $45 billion to the U.S. Treasury for 2009, according to calculations by The Washington Post based on public documents. That reflects the highest earnings in the 96-year history of the central bank. The Fed, unlike most government agencies, funds itself from its own operations and returns its profits to the Treasury.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The numbers are good news for the federal budget and a sign that the Fed has been successful, at least so far, in protecting taxpayers as it intervenes in the economy -- though there remains a risk of significant losses in the future if the Fed sells some of its investments or loses money on its stakes in bailed-out firms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[...]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much of the higher earnings came about because of the Fed's aggressive program of buying bonds, aiming to push interest rates down across the economy and thus stimulate growth. By the end of 2009, the Fed owned $1.8 trillion in U.S. government debt and mortgage-related securities, up from $497 billion a year earlier. The interest income on those investments was a major source of Fed profits -- though that income comes with risks, as the central bank could lose money if it later sells those securities to reduce the money supply.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Fed also made money on its emergency loans to banks and other firms and on special programs to prop up lending, such as one that supports credit cards, auto loans, and other consumer and business lending. Those programs impose interest and fees on participants, with the aim of ensuring that the Fed does not lose money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, okay, some of this makes sense: the emergency loan programs involve third parties and can, in fact, produce profit via interest on the loans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But two questions.&amp;nbsp; First: as the article states, these earnings will go back to the Treasury, which will be &amp;quot;good news for the federal budget&amp;quot; -- except that much of the earnings are attributed to gains from purchased federal debt -- bonds paid out by the Treasury.&amp;nbsp; So, uh, how is this &amp;quot;profit&amp;quot; not completely circular?&amp;nbsp; I suppose that perhaps it represents money that we thought we had spent but hadn't.&amp;nbsp; Still, the Post's presentation of the issue seems very strange.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second: what is the article talking about, anyway? Not to toot my own project's horn &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; much, but we've got &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.subsidyscope.com/bailout/federal-reserve/"&gt;this nifty visualization of fed holdings&lt;/a&gt; based on their weekly H.4.1 reports, and it's just not the case that the fed has increased the amount of Treasury securities it holds.&amp;nbsp; There was a dip, but we're basically back at 2007 levels.&amp;nbsp; The fed's portfolio has gotten much larger thanks to the bailout, but the real story looks to be its still-expanding investment in mortgage-backed securities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm just the tech guy, so I hesitate to go much further out on this limb.&amp;nbsp; But I think Neil Irwin could've done a lot more to distinguish between Treasuries and MBSes, and what they mean for the Fed's holdings.&amp;nbsp; Help me Ryan Avent, you're my only hope!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MORE:&lt;/strong&gt; The &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://blogs.reuters.com/felix-salmon/2010/01/12/the-feds-earnings/#comments"&gt;first comment&lt;/a&gt; on Felix Salmon's coverage of this article is helpful: basically, this is good news because it's not bad news.&amp;nbsp; Perhaps it's a bit silly to think of profit from Treasury securities as a windfall for the government, but at least the Fed managed to keep prices from collapsing, which could've easily happened.&amp;nbsp; I'm still confused by how the article presents its thesis, though.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics"/></entry><entry><title>you can also write 'yes please' under 'sex'</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2009/06/19/you-can-also-write-yes-please-under-sex/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-06-19T11:42:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-06-19T11:42:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2009-06-19:/2009/06/19/you-can-also-write-yes-please-under-sex/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Okay, yes, Michele Bachmann &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://washingtontimes.com/news/2009/jun/17/exclusive-minn-lawmaker-fears-census-abuse/"&gt;refusing to participate in the census&lt;/a&gt; is a bit kooky. But I'm sympathetic. I started participating in the Census survey of household employment a few weeks ago (SPOILER ALERT: I still have a job). The very next day I began receiving unusually high numbers of calls …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Okay, yes, Michele Bachmann &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://washingtontimes.com/news/2009/jun/17/exclusive-minn-lawmaker-fears-census-abuse/"&gt;refusing to participate in the census&lt;/a&gt; is a bit kooky. But I'm sympathetic. I started participating in the Census survey of household employment a few weeks ago (SPOILER ALERT: I still have a job). The very next day I began receiving unusually high numbers of calls from phone surveys. Pepco, private companies, and who knows how many other sample-seekers who I hung up on before identifying. It's leveled off a bit since, but there was a pronounced effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know, I know: they're not allowed to sell my information. It's probably just coincidence. I mean, malfeasance by the government or its agents? The very idea is ludicrous!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet I remain convinced by the experience. And so I understand where Michele is coming from. If they're willing to sell my phone number, is it &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; so outlandish to think that the ACORN agents administering the census will be secretly sizing up respondent families' fitness in order to facilitate the involuntary harvesting of organs (and their subsequent redistribution to welfare recipients) under the coming socialized medicine dystopia? Of course not. Stay strong, Michele.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics"/></entry><entry><title>had a few too many manhattans</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/11/12/had-a-few-too-many-manhattans/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-11-12T20:21:00-05:00</published><updated>2008-11-12T20:21:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-11-12:/2008/11/12/had-a-few-too-many-manhattans/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://meganmcardle.theatlantic.com/archives/2008/11/manhattan_no_more.php"&gt;This post of Megan's&lt;/a&gt;, which details why calls for &amp;quot;another Manhattan Project&amp;quot; are dumb, is quite good. I'll go ahead and suggest that calls for &amp;quot;another Apollo Program&amp;quot; are generally even dumber — they're the same thing, except the speaker doesn't have enough guts to be willing to bring the A-bomb …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://meganmcardle.theatlantic.com/archives/2008/11/manhattan_no_more.php"&gt;This post of Megan's&lt;/a&gt;, which details why calls for &amp;quot;another Manhattan Project&amp;quot; are dumb, is quite good. I'll go ahead and suggest that calls for &amp;quot;another Apollo Program&amp;quot; are generally even dumber — they're the same thing, except the speaker doesn't have enough guts to be willing to bring the A-bomb to mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this got me thinking about the circumstances under which these sorts of projects can work. Here's my stab at it. These sorts of national greatness problems need:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;... to be primarily an engineering problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;... to not contain the words &amp;quot;... and be economically viable&amp;quot;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;... to have been solved at a smaller scale, or to seem solvable on the basis of some compelling math.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;... to not be about finding a solution to a biological problem, unless that problem can be solved by wiping out a non-microscopic organism.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;... to be undertaken out of concern that another country might get a leg up on us if we don't succeed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously this is based on a small set of data points. Basically: we've built the atom bomb, gone to the moon, dug a big canal, built a bunch of roads, and run a number of impressive (and impressively expensive) science experiments. We almost certainly &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; wipe out malaria (almost did!), or develop cellulosic ethanol/Jimmy Carter's &amp;quot;synthetic oil&amp;quot;, but we either don't really want to or think it might be a waste of money. And we definitely haven't cured cancer or AIDS, despite trying pretty hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There've been more than forty State of the Union speeches since Kennedy said we were moonward-bound, so I'm sure I'm missing at least that many calls for ambitious national initiatives. But this is the basic lay of the land, I think: you've got to pick something that seems genuinely urgent, and which is hard but not too hard. It's simple when you put it that way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you might imagine, I'm rooting for China to announce that they're building a space elevator.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics"/></entry><entry><title>College Republicans</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/10/24/college-republicans/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-10-24T14:31:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-10-24T14:31:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-10-24:/2008/10/24/college-republicans/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My professional journalist friends are professionally obligated to, well, be professional. Although this precept serves them and their readers well nearly all of the time, I think it will prevent them from analyzing the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://kdka.com/local/attack.McCain.Bloomfield.2.847628.html"&gt;Ashley Todd affair&lt;/a&gt; with the thoroughness it deserves. So, unencumbered as I am by such considerations …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My professional journalist friends are professionally obligated to, well, be professional. Although this precept serves them and their readers well nearly all of the time, I think it will prevent them from analyzing the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://kdka.com/local/attack.McCain.Bloomfield.2.847628.html"&gt;Ashley Todd affair&lt;/a&gt; with the thoroughness it deserves. So, unencumbered as I am by such considerations, let me try to clarify the lesson that should be drawn from all this: College Republicans are the fucking scum of the earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I say this not to insult Republicans in general. I disagree with members of the GOP about a lot of things, but recognize that nearly all of them are perfectly good, reasonable people. But in my experience, folks who become involved in the party's machinery at a young age seem to be intensely despicable at a much higher rate than their more mature fellow travelers. I was hesitant to be skeptical of Todd's account, at first — skepticism is not generally an appropriate way to respond to the claims of a victim of violent crime. But if the picture was sort of suspicious, Todd's campus affiliations left me feeling even more dubious about her story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;College is a time for quixotic idealism. That's not to say that young people can't earnestly hold conservative beliefs, of course. But if a person is passionately pro-life or nutty for Nozick, he or she is, at that age, much more likely to become involved in an advocacy organization that tries to further those ends directly — it's easy to find such organizations on a college campus, after all. Normal people get involved in politics by first caring about an issue, then realizing that the best way to achieve their ends is to organize their efforts under the umbrella of a larger party. That doesn't happen all at once, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Who opts to instead immediately begin working for a demographically unpopular political party, where your chief activities will involve writing little-noticed op-eds and arranging speaking honoraria for recently disgraced administration officials? Often, the answer seems to be those with a Machiavellian enthusiasm for reaching the levers of power. These are not good people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why don't I think the same criticism thing applies to the young Democrats? Well, to an extent I'm sure it does. But I think it's probably easier to be a starry-eyed College Democrat. You can participate in various organizational efforts motivated by an idealistic conception of participatory democracy — registering new voters, that sort of thing. There will be a lot more of you, too, making participation more appealing to the sorts of people who want to get laid rather than the sorts of people who want to screw others — you'll be surrounded by more normal people, in other words. You'll also probably have less funding per capita and, by virtue of your numbers, more internal tension and examination, making it harder to twist inward into a tight little coven of aspiring conspirators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But of course I'm speculating here. Besides, there's no reason to get defensive; hijinks like those of Todd and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.dailyprincetonian.com/archives/2007/12/14/news/19743.shtml"&gt;Francisco Nava&lt;/a&gt; speak for themselves. Maybe the College Democrats are every bit as despicable as their Republican counterparts. But if they are, then they seem to at least be a bit more competent about it. Give them credit for that. There are few things more pathetic than a liar who's not yet adept at her craft. Someone who tries to inflame racial tensions to further her political ends is one of those things, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE:&lt;/strong&gt; Tim writes to remind me that not all College Republicans are horrible people. Well, alright. I overstated things a bit. But my point remains: fewer young people are attracted to the organization than to its Democratic equivalent, and to some extent they come for different reasons. Some of those reasons are not healthy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few others things. First, credit where due: much of the conservative blogosphere has from the start approached this story in a restrained and thoughtful manner. Second, those saying that Todd's refusal of medical attention was a clue to the hoax are wrong — I've refused police offers of medical attention after getting hit by a car (twice, in fact). If something bad has happened to you and you're pretty sure you're okay, sometimes you just want to go home (if you haven't got health insurance and are unsure who'd be footing the bill, this goes double). Third, Todd seems to now be alleging a history of mental health problems. Depending on how this claim turns out, my feelings about the hoax may become very muddy indeed. The territory where &amp;quot;couldn't help it&amp;quot; begins is murky, and, from a practical standpoint, not necessarily coextensive with &amp;quot;should be excused&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics"/></entry><entry><title>enough! and then, somewhat more than enough</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/10/20/enough-and-then-somewhat-more-than-enough/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-10-20T16:10:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-10-20T16:10:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-10-20:/2008/10/20/enough-and-then-somewhat-more-than-enough/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Michael Pollan was on Fresh Air a moment ago. It's part of his world/public radio tour in support of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/10/12/magazine/12policy-t.html?partner=permalink&amp;amp;exprod=permalink"&gt;Farmer In Chief&lt;/a&gt;, last week's NYT Magazine article asking the next president to adopt better agricultural policies. I heard him giving pretty much the same spiel on a Philadelphia-area NPR …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Michael Pollan was on Fresh Air a moment ago. It's part of his world/public radio tour in support of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/10/12/magazine/12policy-t.html?partner=permalink&amp;amp;exprod=permalink"&gt;Farmer In Chief&lt;/a&gt;, last week's NYT Magazine article asking the next president to adopt better agricultural policies. I heard him giving pretty much the same spiel on a Philadelphia-area NPR station over the weekend, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't want to quibble with the man's larger crusade, but he keeps making one particular point that really bugs me. Pollan is fond of pointing out that since 1960 the average American household's spending on food has dropped as a share of income, from 18 percent to 10.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm pretty sure this is dumb. Or half, dumb, anyway. I'm sure food &lt;em&gt;has&lt;/em&gt; gotten cheaper in absolute terms, and that those savings have been paid for in animal suffering and environmental destruction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it's also the case that household income tends to increase faster than the rate of inflation, while human nutritional requirements do not. &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Median_household_income#Median_household_income_and_the_economy"&gt;Wikipedia says that real median income has increased about 30% since 1967&lt;/a&gt;. Unless I'm missing something, that means that if a family used to spend $1800 on food, today they spend $1300 — not $1000, as Pollan implies. If median household income data was available for 1960, rather than 1967, you can bet that the differential would be smaller still. And if you consider the fact that household size has &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.msnbc.msn.com/id/14942047/"&gt;declined from 3 to 2.6 people&lt;/a&gt; since 1967, the gap shrinks even more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, the picture is much more complicated than just a dollar amount. I'm sure we eat out a lot more, eat more processed food, eat more meat, pay more for specialty food and less for staples, and generally eat in ways that support Pollan's thesis. But this particular argument about income is a bit dishonest, and I wish he'd quit using it. Nutritional needs do not scale with income.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a pet peeve of mine with economic arguments about consumption in general: they tend not to pay any attention to the limits of human biology. This is why I'm similarly suspicious of estimates of exploding per capita bandwidth consumption. Yes, our bandwidth needs will continue to increase. But the human nervous system has its own bandwidth limits, too. Maybe there'll be one more video resolution revolution — HDTV2, let's say (pending the invention of a more confusing acronym). But to go beyond that will require video walls — they look cool in &lt;em&gt;Total Recall&lt;/em&gt;, but why would you pay for something larger than your field of view? — or three-dimensional holo-whatnots. I'm sure the latter will be popularized eventually, but I'll probably be pretty old and confused by then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The human fovea has a finite number of neurons, and we're already pretty good at keeping them busy. Personally, I think that household bandwidth use is likely to level off sometime in the next decade or two — there's only so much data that a human body can use. Our bandwidth expenses as a percentage of income will then start to fall, both because the growth in demand has slowed and because income continues to rise, but also because the resource itself will continue to get cheaper as technology improves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That won't constitute proof that we aren't spending &lt;em&gt;enough&lt;/em&gt; on bandwidth, though. It'll just mean that we've found some other stuff to spend our new money on, rather than simply ramping up our budget linearly. (My guess: hyper-ipods.)&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics"/></entry><entry><title>this blog goes negative</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/10/09/this-blog-goes-negative/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-10-09T11:04:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-10-09T11:04:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-10-09:/2008/10/09/this-blog-goes-negative/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My friend V made this video and asked me to pass it along:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scary! And of course it's hard to argue with the basic point that Sarah Palin is less qualified to run the country than the average Model UN participant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The video implicitly makes another, more subtle point, too …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My friend V made this video and asked me to pass it along:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Scary! And of course it's hard to argue with the basic point that Sarah Palin is less qualified to run the country than the average Model UN participant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The video implicitly makes another, more subtle point, too: &lt;em&gt;Vladimir Putin may be a vampire&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="20081009_putinvampire.jpg" class="center" src="/static/2008/10/09/20081009_putinvampire.jpg" style="width: 480px; height: 312px;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Write your own &amp;quot;blood for oil&amp;quot; joke — I'm too terrified to do it.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics"/></entry><entry><title>what?</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/10/08/what/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-10-08T11:18:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-10-08T11:18:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-10-08:/2008/10/08/what/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm not a regular reader of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://corner.nationalreview.com/"&gt;Corner&lt;/a&gt;, but I've found myself stopping by after each debate to enjoy a bit of schadenfreude. And, with apologies to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.brianbeutler.com"&gt;Brian&lt;/a&gt; — this is &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.google.com/search?q=site%3Abrianbeutler.com%20corner%20bashing"&gt;his gig&lt;/a&gt; — it really just makes &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://corner.nationalreview.com/post/?q=MjQxM2YzM2U5YTk1YjE0ODQyNWI5NmIzMTA2ZjFkZjA="&gt;no goddamn sense&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Saturday Night Live recently did a terrific sketch on the bailout …&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm not a regular reader of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://corner.nationalreview.com/"&gt;Corner&lt;/a&gt;, but I've found myself stopping by after each debate to enjoy a bit of schadenfreude. And, with apologies to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.brianbeutler.com"&gt;Brian&lt;/a&gt; — this is &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.google.com/search?q=site%3Abrianbeutler.com%20corner%20bashing"&gt;his gig&lt;/a&gt; — it really just makes &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://corner.nationalreview.com/post/?q=MjQxM2YzM2U5YTk1YjE0ODQyNWI5NmIzMTA2ZjFkZjA="&gt;no goddamn sense&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Saturday Night Live recently did a terrific sketch on the bailout bill in Congress. Shortly afterward, the sketch â€” which had been available on NBC's website â€” disappeared. The sketch mocked a wealthy couple who profited off subprime mortgages named Herb and Marion Sandler, and it turns out there really is a wealthy couple named Herb and Marion Sandler who made billions off of subprime loans, and speculation was that offending the real Sandlers was the reason for pulling the sketch.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;So now the sketch is back up, without any mention of the Sandlers. But as the L.A. Times notes, what's really curious is that the re-edited sketch removed any satirical references to Barney Frank's involvement in creating the economic crisis:&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;In the original skit Sandler addresses Frank, saying, &amp;quot;And thank you Congressman Frank as well as many Republicans for helping block Congressional oversight of our corrupt activities.&amp;quot;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;To which Frank replies enthusiastically, &amp;quot;Not at all!&amp;quot;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's all gone. I'd love to hear an explanation for that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, here's an explanation: when you edit a character out of a scene, it's awkward to leave in lines that have other actors interacting with that now-nonexistent character. I realize this may seem like kind of a technical point, but I assure you that even those of us who are not professional screenwriters can, with diligence, grasp the dramaturgical logic underlying NBC's decision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've got no opinion of the decision to edit out the Sandlers, incidentally. Aside from the Barney Frank impression it was a pretty lousy sketch anyway — making it shorter is a generally good idea.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics"/></entry><entry><title>nucular proliferation</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/10/03/nucular-proliferation/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-10-03T15:53:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-10-03T15:53:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-10-03:/2008/10/03/nucular-proliferation/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Once again, I pretty much lost track of the debate by its end — I was typing furiously and drinking too fast. But I guess I agree that Palin seemed to be merely a bit dim, rather than so cartoonishly stupid that you'd hesitate to trust her with solid food.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Once again, I pretty much lost track of the debate by its end — I was typing furiously and drinking too fast. But I guess I agree that Palin seemed to be merely a bit dim, rather than so cartoonishly stupid that you'd hesitate to trust her with solid food.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She did regress in at least one respect, though: her pronunciation. She managed to say the word &amp;quot;nuclear&amp;quot; perfectly correctly during her convention speech. But last night she adopted the &amp;quot;nucular&amp;quot; formulation favored by grade school boys and our current president. Here, check it out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/static/2008/10/03/palin-speech-nuclear.mp3"&gt;Palin at the RNC – Nuclear, clearly&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="/static/2008/10/03/palin-debate-nucular.mp3"&gt;Palin at the Debate – Nucular contamination&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few ways to react to this. &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.unfogged.com/archives/week_2008_09_28.html#009273"&gt;Wolfson linked&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://itre.cis.upenn.edu/~myl/languagelog/archives/001134.html"&gt;this piece at Language Log&lt;/a&gt; today, which perceptively notes that:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Ordinary people, faced with what are for them deviant, &amp;quot;wrong&amp;quot;, bits of language, see nothing but a mistake, period. They are resistant to the linguist's idea that there could be a rationale for the &amp;quot;mistake&amp;quot;, even a system to it, or that, in fact, the very same thing could result from different sources or represent different systems. (This attitude presents a tough challenge when we teach beginning linguistics courses -- not only when we talk about dialects, but also when we talk about language acquisition. One of the hardest lessons for many students is that instead of saying what's wrong, what people &amp;quot;can't&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;won't&amp;quot; do, they should be describing what people *do*, and making hypotheses about *why* they do that.)&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, this is stupid. It's nuclear. Everybody knows that. Perhaps someday the situation will become sufficiently muddy that a postmodern assessment of the word's pronunciation will become appropriate. But we're not there yet. Right now if you press people — even those who say nucular — most will grudgingly admit that there is a correct pronunciation of the word, and that it doesn't rhyme with &amp;quot;tubular&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, it's worth pointing out that linguistics is dumb and the classes I had to take about it in college were awful. So there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No, I prefer to subscribe to a theory along &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://people.ischool.berkeley.edu/~nunberg/nucular.html"&gt;these lines&lt;/a&gt;: namely, that the choice to use the &amp;quot;nucular&amp;quot; pronunciation is increasingly a deliberate one, at least among politicians. I suspect that it's going to eventually become a sign of party allegiance on the right, a little piece of deliberate ignorance designed to subtly defame members of the &amp;quot;Democrat Party&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only other explanation I can think of for the discrepancy in Palin's pronunciation is that her convention speech was spelled out on the teleprompter (which she &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://corner.nationalreview.com/post/?q=NTY3MTI3MzhmNzhmNGJlYmIwOTYzMTNmZjA4ZDk3MTE="&gt;didn't&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://corner.nationalreview.com/post/?q=ZjM5NjhhMDYwZDgwYWRlNWFhZTUzMTEyZTk5YjBjY2E="&gt;use&lt;/a&gt;, mind you!) FO-NET-I-KAL-LEE. I suppose that's plausible enough — you can take your pick between that or the deliberate mispronunciation explanation. As it so often does when examining modern conservative behavior, it's a toss up between stupidity and malevolence.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics"/></entry><entry><title>okay, so the AFL-CIO guy</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/10/03/okay-so-the-afl-cio-guy/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-10-03T00:56:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-10-03T00:56:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-10-03:/2008/10/03/okay-so-the-afl-cio-guy/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This video is making the progressive blogospheric rounds:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's good! But I've gotta say: if you grew up going to a church with a halfway-competent minister — someone with some charisma and some time spent in seminary — this clip is going to sound pretty familiar. That's not to diminish it, but …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This video is making the progressive blogospheric rounds:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's good! But I've gotta say: if you grew up going to a church with a halfway-competent minister — someone with some charisma and some time spent in seminary — this clip is going to sound pretty familiar. That's not to diminish it, but the cadence and patterns are amazingly similar to what I listened to every Sunday growing up. This guy's got talent, no doubt, and his message is an indisputably important one. But it's a well-trodden form. I guess I just want to point out that if you find this experience particularly moving, you can probably enjoy it on a weekly basis a few blocks from your house. It'll be a bit more Jesus-y, but the delivery and rhetorical structure will be just as satisfying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I say all this as a kid who grew up Presbyterian. The Frozen Chosen! I can only imagine the firestorm that a Baptist with some book-learnin' could bust out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ALSO:&lt;/strong&gt; This speech happened on July 1. Weird.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics"/></entry><entry><title>EMP Recognition Day</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/10/02/emp-recognition-day/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-10-02T17:04:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-10-02T17:04:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-10-02:/2008/10/02/emp-recognition-day/</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.heritage.org/Research/HomelandSecurity/wm2063.cfm"&gt;This has to be a joke&lt;/a&gt;. To seriously propose this would reveal a level of idiocy even greater than we've seen among recent vice presidential candidates. That, or a brazen and desperate desire to hand billions of dollars to defense contractors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.brianbeutler.com/2008/10/words_fail/"&gt;Via Brian&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics"/></entry><entry><title>we really are doomed</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/09/12/we-really-are-doomed/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-09-12T11:34:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-09-12T11:34:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-09-12:/2008/09/12/we-really-are-doomed/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://radaronline.com/exclusives/2008/09/john-mccain-lies.php"&gt;Alex Balk&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why does John McCain tell so many lies? Because lying works! If you didn't read &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://radaronline.com/exclusives/2008/09/the-fbi-infiltrates-american-organizations.php"&gt;that AP analysis we mentioned earlier&lt;/a&gt;, you really should. It makes the very instructive point that even if the press actually does its job and shows that the lies John McCain and his …&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://radaronline.com/exclusives/2008/09/john-mccain-lies.php"&gt;Alex Balk&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why does John McCain tell so many lies? Because lying works! If you didn't read &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://radaronline.com/exclusives/2008/09/the-fbi-infiltrates-american-organizations.php"&gt;that AP analysis we mentioned earlier&lt;/a&gt;, you really should. It makes the very instructive point that even if the press actually does its job and shows that the lies John McCain and his surrogates tell are, real, honest-to-God lies, it doesn't make a difference. Noting how the media had debunked many strands in the giant web of lies the McCain team has put out over the last two weeks, the article goes on to admit that it doesn't really matter:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Major news outlets have written such fact-checking articles for years. &amp;quot;But in the last two election cycles, the very notion that the facts matter seems to be under assault,&amp;quot; said Michael X. Delli Carpini, an authority on political ads at the University of Pennsylvania's Annenberg School for Communication. &amp;quot;Candidates and their consultants seem to have learned that as long as you don't back down from your charges or claims, they will stick in the minds of voters regardless of their accuracy or at a minimum, what the truth is will remain murky, a matter of opinion rather than fact.&amp;quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, real-life evidence. Check out this comment, from a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://blog.wired.com/27bstroke6/2008/09/the-many-faces.html"&gt;Wired post&lt;/a&gt; about the various Palin spoofs — it's whole point is to catalog parodies, and it's quite explicit about this!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Hi,&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;just a question:&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://sarahpalin.typepad.com/"&gt;http://sarahpalin.typepad.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;is this real??? I read and read and have a very hard time struggling with the idea that she is really this dumb that she can write this.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Come on, War with Russia, Creationism, Anti-Abortion, but admitting to ban and steal books from the libraryfor those reasons? that's not at all a sane woman. Please answer: how are u sure it's her blog??&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Thanx&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have read a lot of comments like this over the past few weeks. And while they're sort of funny, they're also deeply depressing. I suppose that says as much about my sense of humor as it does about the electorate. But one of those things results in awkward moments at parties, while the other will ultimately lead to the death of thousands, if not millions, if not the destruction of the entire planet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doomed, I say!&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics"/></entry><entry><title>nothing to see here</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/09/04/nothing-to-see-here/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-09-04T11:31:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-09-04T11:31:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-09-04:/2008/09/04/nothing-to-see-here/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My internet energies remain committed elsewhere, but I would like to at least register a couple of cranky complaints about the commentary surrounding Palin:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To everyone asserting that the Democrats just don't get it, and that only you, the author, have a privileged insight into what makes real Americans so …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My internet energies remain committed elsewhere, but I would like to at least register a couple of cranky complaints about the commentary surrounding Palin:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To everyone asserting that the Democrats just don't get it, and that only you, the author, have a privileged insight into what makes real Americans so gosh-darn &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; — and they're going to love Sarah Palin! — please, shut the fuck up. You're just guessing, you out-of-touch elitist, exactly the same way that I am. Show me some polls. Even if you dismiss the fact that the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.editorandpublisher.com/eandp/news/article_display.jsp?vnu_content_id=1003844485"&gt;early&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.freep.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20080903/NEWS15/80904002"&gt;returns&lt;/a&gt; don't agree with your analysis, you should temper your statements with the realization that the odds of the vice presidential pick having a significant impact on the race's outcome are very, very small.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To those using Twitter for non-humorous political analysis: you should probably stop. This applies doubly for Democrats who employ it to compliment Republican machinations in an attempt to paint themselves as bold, contrarian truth-tellers in the tradition of — what, Alan Colmes? The instantaneous, abbreviated nature of the medium makes this a tough act to pull off; you'll usually just come off sounding credulous and reactionary. The good news is that if you're reading this you're almost certainly not who I have in mind. But really: if you want to play contrarian, do it in a macroblog format. That will at least afford you enough characters to express your dumb observations in a clever-sounding way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whew! I sure am cantankerous this morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ALSO:&lt;/strong&gt; Somewhat less emphatically, let me add that I (predictably) don't really buy the argument that going after Palin will prompt a meaningful backlash. In terms of media narratives, sure — but nobody should care about that. The &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://matthewyglesias.theatlantic.com/archives/2007/11/smear_me_once.php"&gt;depressing truth&lt;/a&gt; seems to be that the first mover advantage overwhelms the final result of most societal deliberations.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics"/></entry><entry><title>Sarah Palin tall</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/08/29/sarah-palin-tall/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-08-29T16:51:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-08-29T16:51:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-08-29:/2008/08/29/sarah-palin-tall/</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://sarahpalin.typepad.com/"&gt;Get to know your new vice presidential candidate&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(This post's title shamelessly stolen from &amp;#64;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://twitter.com/lgibson"&gt;lgibson&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics"/></entry><entry><title>sympathy for the devil</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/07/23/sympathy-for-the-devil/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-07-23T13:19:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-07-23T13:19:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-07-23:/2008/07/23/sympathy-for-the-devil/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image1" class="center" src="/static/2008/07/23/skitched-20080723-135202.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm surprised to hear myself say it, but after reading &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dcist.com/2008/07/23/novak_hits_pedestrian_its_not_joe_w.php"&gt;Martin's writeup&lt;/a&gt; I feel a little bad for Bob Novak, who hit a pedestrian with his car this morning. It sounds like it was only a matter of time: the comments are just getting started, but so far about 10 …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image1" class="center" src="/static/2008/07/23/skitched-20080723-135202.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm surprised to hear myself say it, but after reading &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dcist.com/2008/07/23/novak_hits_pedestrian_its_not_joe_w.php"&gt;Martin's writeup&lt;/a&gt; I feel a little bad for Bob Novak, who hit a pedestrian with his car this morning. It sounds like it was only a matter of time: the comments are just getting started, but so far about 10% are from people reporting incidents where Novak almost hit them, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But like I said, I feel bad for the guy. Bob and I go way back. When I was a little kid I used to watch the McLaughlin Group with my dad. I don't remember much from that experience besides McLaughlin's plaid Christmas jacket and the paternally-instilled lesson that Novak was a Very Bad Man. The situation became clearer during senior year of high school, when my government teacher would fulfill his educational duty by showing us taped episodes of &lt;em&gt;Crossfire&lt;/em&gt;. It was an exciting time: Bill Press pioneered the disoriented, exasperated style of liberalism that would later help America ignore Al Gore; and the program itself was just beginning to metastasize into the odious force that Jon Stewart would eventually banish to another dimension. But the most remarkable spectacle was happening across the table from Press, where Robert Novak exuded pure reptilian malevolence with the sort of ease that made you want to stand up and applaud. When he tried to smile the entire class would physically recoil.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But now, looking back, I realize that Novakian evil isn't anything to fear. I didn't know it at the time, but the McLaughlin Groupies who should have been inspiring bone-chilling terror were Fred Barnes and Mort Kondracke. They were the true harbingers, the types of guys whose ilk might lobby for offshore drilling on the strength of an invitation to an oil magnate's daughter's super sweet sixteen; or who might accidentally launch missiles while trying to play Snood, then refuse to feel bad about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what if Novak outs the occasional CIA agent or runs down the occasional pedestrian? His is a totally comprehensible evil. And, for what it's worth, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.radaronline.com/features/2008/07/hated_pundits_chris_matthews_keith_olbermann_bill_oreilly_an_4.php"&gt;this Radar feature&lt;/a&gt; indicates that he's a perfectly nice old man, who delights staffers at every office holiday party with jigs played upon his famous golden fiddle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My point is that Washington knows how to deal with his type: when we've had a few too many missing pedestrians and/or wars, the town's bravest men descend into the secret Masonic catacombs below and, confronting the beast with hemlock and holy water, force him to dissolve into shrieks and a foul, sulfurous mist. At this point the Washington Times prints a note indicating that Mr. Novak will be on vacation until the next solstice, and everyone declares themselves more or less satisfied.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's the way things work around here, and it's a system we're comfortable with. Seeing misfortune befall ol' Bob seems like an imbalance, and that makes me sad. If I get my choice of foe I'll take reptilian evil over reptile-sized brains any day.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics"/></entry><entry><title>greenness, easiness thereof; christ I wish there was another possible title</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/06/09/greenness-easiness-thereof-christ-i-wish-there-was-another-possible-title/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-06-09T00:15:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-06-09T00:15:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-06-09:/2008/06/09/greenness-easiness-thereof-christ-i-wish-there-was-another-possible-title/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ezra &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.prospect.org/csnc/blogs/ezraklein_archive?month=06&amp;amp;year=2008&amp;amp;base_name=saucy_ignorant_contrarianism"&gt;links approvingly&lt;/a&gt; to a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://thinkprogress.org/wonkroom/2008/06/07/wired-ignorant-libertarianism/"&gt;Wonk Room post&lt;/a&gt; complaining about &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.wired.com/science/planetearth/magazine/16-06/ff_heresies_intro"&gt;Wired's new environmentalist-baiting issue&lt;/a&gt;, which, among other things, decries green enthusiasm for organic farming as detrimental to the more important cause of reducing greenhouse emissions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The author, Paulina Borsook, doesn't challenge the article's contention that organic farming is less productive …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ezra &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.prospect.org/csnc/blogs/ezraklein_archive?month=06&amp;amp;year=2008&amp;amp;base_name=saucy_ignorant_contrarianism"&gt;links approvingly&lt;/a&gt; to a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://thinkprogress.org/wonkroom/2008/06/07/wired-ignorant-libertarianism/"&gt;Wonk Room post&lt;/a&gt; complaining about &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.wired.com/science/planetearth/magazine/16-06/ff_heresies_intro"&gt;Wired's new environmentalist-baiting issue&lt;/a&gt;, which, among other things, decries green enthusiasm for organic farming as detrimental to the more important cause of reducing greenhouse emissions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The author, Paulina Borsook, doesn't challenge the article's contention that organic farming is less productive than conventional farming. But she finds fault with the Wired article because its carbon calculation fails to include a number of factors: carbon emitted transporting fertilizer, pesticides and hormones; the carbon capital costs of the companies that supply them; and carbon impact of increased healthcare costs stemming from the consumption of non-organic food.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of these critiques are legitimate. Some of them are pretty silly. None of them are quantitative in any way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's easy to see why. Seriously, how many fewer medical expenses will an average individual incur if they eat organic food versus non-organic food? No, no cheating: I said &amp;quot;seriously&amp;quot;. No hunches allowed. You have to actually cite data and do the math. Good luck. I'd be impressed if you even manage to come up with a plausible justification for your answer's order of magnitude.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Doing this stuff is impossibly difficult, as is amply demonstrated every time someone tries to figure out the comparatively narrowly-defined problem of biofuels' net energy balance. This is the first problem: literally every human endeavor consumes energy — and of course, it's very hard to reduce any action in civilization to just one step. It's tough to figure out how much energy something took, very tough to accurately guess, and nearly impossible to know how much carbon it took to generate that energy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This came up when I was out in San Francisco for work (a trip that was unambiguously environmentally awful, I'll be the first to admit). Over beers Michael told a story about a passenger on his flight jealously guarding his trash, refusing to surrender it to the flight attendants unless they promised it would be recycled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it's not that easy, right? Last I heard, metal is unambiguously beneficial to recycle; glass takes more energy to recycle than it's worth; and plastic — well, who knows? It probably depends on the type of plastic and where the recycling plant is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or take the great &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://blogs.nature.com/news/thegreatbeyond/2008/05/get_your_greendex.html"&gt;coffee cup debate&lt;/a&gt;: if a given ceramic mug is likely to get less than a thousand uses, you're better off drinking from a styrofoam cup. Probably, anyway. I'm sure it depends on your dishwasher, or its settings. Or if you don't have a dishwasher. Or the detergent you buy. And probably how far you are from the water pumping station, right? Maybe how much rain your area gets, or has gotten this year, or what floor you live on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which is the other problem: as individuals it seems like we all pretty much live within the margin of error on these questions. It adds up over the population, of course, but for one person it's nearly impossible to know what the right thing to do is. There are unambiguous things, of course: don't leave the water running when you brush your teeth, and minimize electricity use, and don't leave your car idling. Although sometimes even &lt;em&gt;those&lt;/em&gt; wind up ambiguous: I've heard that restarting a car takes about as much gas as running it for a minute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then, I probably heard that from someplace like Wired. So who knows? This is the real problem, the meta-problem: while the only people with an incentive to really figure this out are academics, the only people with an incentive to &lt;em&gt;talk&lt;/em&gt; about it are those who sell ad space to people targeting an audience that likes green content or an audience that likes counterintuitive content (both detestable in their own ways). And the press is more than comfortable enough with their anecdotes and innumeracy to continue publishing hunches they had while shopping at Whole Foods, as if a half-day's worth of googling and algebra was sufficient to untangle the world's unimaginably complicated economic and energy-use web (a pursuit that I admit I've &lt;a class="reference external" href="/2007/10/15/if-only-we-could-drink-gasoline/"&gt;indulged&lt;/a&gt; in myself — but at least nobody paid me for it).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of which is to say that until we actually tax or cap or otherwise price carbon, Borsook's counterargument is just as silly as the Wired piece. We'll all keep doing our best, but it's inevitably going to be lame and probably ineffective until we've got some reliable, unignorable signals from which to make decisions. Until then I don't know what to do besides make my best guesses, muddle through, and rededicate myself to an overwhelming sense of defeatist liberal guilt.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics"/></entry><entry><title>herd shift</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/05/07/herd-shift/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-05-07T09:06:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-05-07T09:06:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-05-07:/2008/05/07/herd-shift/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So where can I sign up for more timely updates from the media conspiracy? I'm imagining an email list. Or maybe a dashboard widget with Growl notifications telling me when and how to unfairly marginalize the Ron Paul campaign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I went to bed last night, MSNBC had begun expressing …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So where can I sign up for more timely updates from the media conspiracy? I'm imagining an email list. Or maybe a dashboard widget with Growl notifications telling me when and how to unfairly marginalize the Ron Paul campaign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I went to bed last night, MSNBC had begun expressing doubts about Senator Clinton's prospects. But that was it! By this morning the floodgates had opened and suddenly everyone is willing to acknowledge what has been true for weeks: that there's really no way for her to catch up that doesn't involve people taking to the streets. It really is striking, bizarre, and a bit frightening to see how suddenly, uniformly and arbitrarily this change occurred. The most generous interpretation is that after one or two people risked embarrassment by acknowledging the actual situation, everyone else felt free to adopt the new storyline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without the fourth estate to help it play make-believe, I guess it's unlikely that the Clinton campaign is long for this world. That's fine by me. But I'm still a little bitter: I'd gotten pretty good at writing rote, despairing &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dcist.com/2008/05/07/morning_roundup_252.php"&gt;morning roundup&lt;/a&gt; introductions about the primary campaign's interminability. When I woke up this morning and rescanned the headlines I had to throw away a rather clever paragraph. Sucks!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So please: a little more warning next time the media conspiracy suddenly and arbitrarily shifts direction — those of us at the distant bottom of the org chart would really appreciate it. Maybe you guys could set up a Google Calendar or something.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics"/></entry><entry><title>stupid is cheap</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/04/09/stupid-is-cheap/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-04-09T10:29:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-04-09T10:29:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-04-09:/2008/04/09/stupid-is-cheap/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;So I guess that Glenn Greenwald and Megan are having a fight over what stories the media covers. This seems a little odd, but I guess she yelled at him, so now his commenters are yelling at her. And while I don't want to align myself with the people who …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So I guess that Glenn Greenwald and Megan are having a fight over what stories the media covers. This seems a little odd, but I guess she yelled at him, so now his commenters are yelling at her. And while I don't want to align myself with the people who comment on her site, who tend to be (for one reason if not another) some of the worst people on the planet, it's worth remembering just how lousy the metrics data Megan &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://meganmcardle.theatlantic.com/archives/2008/04/a_great_business_opportunity.php"&gt;refers to&lt;/a&gt; can be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://idolator.com/tunes/corporate-rock-still-sells/who-arbitrates-arbitron-328449.php"&gt;Consider this admittedly irritatingly-formatted conversation about the Arbitron ratings&lt;/a&gt;. Basically: over the last decade or so Arbitron, the one big radio ratings agency, recorded the declining popularity of rock radio, and stations like DC's own WHFS were shuttered (boo!). Then Arbitron developed a new technology that passively monitors what people listen to instead of relying on them to accurately report their listening habits. It turned out that rock radio was considerably more popular than anyone thought — rock listeners were just unusually bad at filling out Arbitron's surveys. With that factor removed, rock stations are now once again popping up in cities that have rolled out the new monitoring technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, while I certainly don't want to imply that listening to Smash Mouth correlates with intelligence, in general I think it's probably true that it's harder to collect tracking metrics on the sorts of educated, sophisticated consumers that Greenwald's commenters presumably consider themselves to be. Their time will tend to be more valuable, meaning your ratings company will be able to afford to buy less of it. And they may have less time to consume media, meaning there's less collectible data available per capita — even if you don't have to pay for it. They also may be quicker to notice that you're tracking or otherwise inconveniencing them and take steps to stop you. Show of hands — how many people are reading this with Adblock Plus installed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From listening to Emily talk about her work it's clear that avoiding sampling error is hard enough when the attempt is made in a rigorous, well-funded academic setting. And of course the situation here is considerably worse. Ratings companies like Nielsen, Arbitron and the like have a financial incentive to sample poorly (or as poorly as they can get away with). And, from my cursory understanding of their industry (I read DCRTV! I tell clients which web analytic reports to buy!), it doesn't seem as though the firms sell themselves with their highly scientific methods so much as they sell themselves by being the only game in town.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it doesn't seem totally outrageous to me to suggest that metrics-driven editorial decisions may favor idiotic stories even more than the economists' magical intersecting lines say they should. I think the internet has helped reverse this trend, but America is still probably being fed stupider content than it ought to be. And, lest you think I'm just creating elaborate justifications for my own tastes' supremacy, keep in mind that I say all this as a guy who ordered a pay-per-view wrestling event less than a month ago.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics"/></entry><entry><title>sure it's sleazy, but it holds to a proud tradition of sleaze</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/03/06/sure-its-sleazy-but-it-holds-to-a-proud-tradition-of-sleaze/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-03-06T14:11:00-05:00</published><updated>2008-03-06T14:11:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-03-06:/2008/03/06/sure-its-sleazy-but-it-holds-to-a-proud-tradition-of-sleaze/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Look, I like Barack Obama, too. I hope he wins the nomination and becomes our next president. But &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.dailykos.com/storyonly/2008/3/5/14345/50395/126/469746"&gt;this stuff&lt;/a&gt; about the Clinton campaign altering videotape of him to make him seem blacker is just crazy. Have we all really never seen a political ad before? Here, allow me to …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Look, I like Barack Obama, too. I hope he wins the nomination and becomes our next president. But &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.dailykos.com/storyonly/2008/3/5/14345/50395/126/469746"&gt;this stuff&lt;/a&gt; about the Clinton campaign altering videotape of him to make him seem blacker is just crazy. Have we all really never seen a political ad before? Here, allow me to summarize the art form for you:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Grainy, black and white footage of Candidate A, stretched extra-wide or extra-tall. The camera slowly zooms in on Candidate A's lips, which move in slow motion but without sound.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;NARRATOR: Candidate A says he's for [good things]. But according to [somewhat reputable news source] on [date] he said [nuanced opinion]. Maybe that's why [neutral-sounding fringe group] called Candidate A &amp;quot;[outrageous smear]&amp;quot;.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;em&gt;(brief pause)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;NARRATOR: Candidate A. [misleading interrogatory]?&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cut to wide shot of Candidate B. He is standing in a sunlit alpine valley, surrounded by adorable woodland creatures and an assemblage of attractive, multicultural children. They look up to him expectantly, hoping to absorb the wisdom of their elders so that they, too, might grow up and take their rightful places in the glorious unfolding story that is AMERICA.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Candidate B: I'm Candidate B, and I approved this message because [something other than &amp;quot;I owe private industry many favors&amp;quot;].&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is how things go. You jack up the contrast, distort the image, slow it down and screw around with the colors because it makes your opponent look generically creepy — not because it accentuates particular racial attributes. For some reason the kossacks are pretending that nobody has ever run video of their opponent through a filter. They're either &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://althouse.blogspot.com/2008/03/why-are-letters-nig-on-childs-pajamas.html"&gt;insane&lt;/a&gt;, dishonest, or haven't been paying any attention at all. This graphical sniping is common enough that &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.snpp.com/episodes/2F02.html"&gt;it's been parodied on The Simpsons&lt;/a&gt;, for pete's sake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE:&lt;/strong&gt; More from &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.washingtonmonthly.com/archives/individual/2008_03/013281.php"&gt;Kevin Drum&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.factcheck.org/elections-2008/did_clinton_darken_obamas_skin.html"&gt;FactCheck.org&lt;/a&gt;. I hadn't realized that the evidence being cited was coming from different video sources, and that one of them is &lt;em&gt;YouTube&lt;/em&gt;, for chrissakes. It's simply impossible to meaningfully identify the sort of subtle trickery that's being alleged when the quality of the evidence is so poor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that in mind, a few good litmus tests to apply before opining on these matters: can you succinctly define &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gamma_correction"&gt;gamma correction&lt;/a&gt;? Have you ever had to figure out what &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Color_space"&gt;color space&lt;/a&gt; an image is using? Does &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://spyder.datacolor.com/index_us.php"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; look at all familiar? If so, then by all means speak your mind. If not, allow me to gently suggest that you have some wikipedia-reading to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that, get me digital stills from the debate and the ad that were recorded on the same hardware. Only then will it be possible to identify the alleged manipulation as genuinely existing — at which point my previous objections about the likely lack of racial malice surrounding the manipulation will resume applying. Seriously: this is laughably weak stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics"/></entry><entry><title>to say nothing of the mummy threat</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/02/26/to-say-nothing-of-the-mummy-threat/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-02-26T11:11:00-05:00</published><updated>2008-02-26T11:11:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-02-26:/2008/02/26/to-say-nothing-of-the-mummy-threat/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Sure, harvesting the organs of executed criminals &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://matthewyglesias.theatlantic.com/archives/2008/02/bitter_harvest.php"&gt;sounds&lt;/a&gt; like pleasant and morally unproblematic work. But Matt is ignoring the lessons of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Body_Bags_%28TV_Movie%29"&gt;John Carpenter Presents Body Bags&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Treehouse of Horror IX&lt;/em&gt;, and, in a somewhat broader sense, &lt;em&gt;Nightmare on Elm Street&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Idle Hands&lt;/em&gt;, Jessica Alba's upcoming movie &lt;em&gt;The Eye&lt;/em&gt; and any …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Sure, harvesting the organs of executed criminals &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://matthewyglesias.theatlantic.com/archives/2008/02/bitter_harvest.php"&gt;sounds&lt;/a&gt; like pleasant and morally unproblematic work. But Matt is ignoring the lessons of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Body_Bags_%28TV_Movie%29"&gt;John Carpenter Presents Body Bags&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Treehouse of Horror IX&lt;/em&gt;, and, in a somewhat broader sense, &lt;em&gt;Nightmare on Elm Street&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;Idle Hands&lt;/em&gt;, Jessica Alba's upcoming movie &lt;em&gt;The Eye&lt;/em&gt; and any number of other supernaturally-themed transplant films (some of them no doubt inspired by real events).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In general postmortem recidivism is a topic that's too often left unacknowledged by the prison reform movement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE:&lt;/strong&gt; The Nabob &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://pygmalioninablanket.blogspot.com/2008/02/to-say-nothing-of-revengeful-zombie.html"&gt;reminds me&lt;/a&gt; of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0101492/"&gt;Body Parts&lt;/a&gt;, an argument for my thesis that I had inexplicably ignored. If the Q. wasn't already E.D.-ed, surely it must now be considered so.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics"/></entry><entry><title>hindsight</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/02/13/hindsight/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-02-13T12:11:00-05:00</published><updated>2008-02-13T12:11:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-02-13:/2008/02/13/hindsight/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I meant to talk about the new evidence that biofuels are a bad idea when &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.brianbeutler.com/2008/02/corn_woes/"&gt;Brian first wrote about it&lt;/a&gt;, but I forgot. Today &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://matthewyglesias.theatlantic.com/archives/2008/02/flipflop_needed.php"&gt;Matt mentioned it&lt;/a&gt;, and I was reminded that virtually everyone is ignoring a key aspect of the biofuel land use debate. If I may quote the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I meant to talk about the new evidence that biofuels are a bad idea when &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.brianbeutler.com/2008/02/corn_woes/"&gt;Brian first wrote about it&lt;/a&gt;, but I forgot. Today &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://matthewyglesias.theatlantic.com/archives/2008/02/flipflop_needed.php"&gt;Matt mentioned it&lt;/a&gt;, and I was reminded that virtually everyone is ignoring a key aspect of the biofuel land use debate. If I may quote the beginning of the cover story in the current issue of the excellent &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.brewingnews.com/mid-atlantic/"&gt;Mid-Atlantic Brewing News&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Blame drought in Australia and rain in Europe. Blame increased interest in ethanol as an energy source.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Even blame the growing popularity of beer in China.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Those—and more—are reasons to expect higher beer prices in 2008, and why some brewers will be unable to make some beers no matter how strong the consumer demand. Craft brewers face what more than one calls &amp;quot;a perfect storm&amp;quot; of higher costs and reduced availability for both the hops and malt used to make their beers.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&amp;quot;Prices are going to go up... there's just no doubt about it,&amp;quot; predicts Jim Busch of Downingtown, Pa.'s Victory Brewing Co. &amp;quot;And some brands will disappear. Other brands will just totally change in their character.&amp;quot;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&amp;quot;Brewer owners are going to have to raise their prices,&amp;quot; agrees Russian River Brewing Co. founder and brewer Vinnie Cilurzo in Santa Rosa, Calif., &amp;quot;just to stay in business.&amp;quot;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&amp;quot;I think this year will be, to use the Chinese curse phrase, 'interesting,'&amp;quot; comments Hugh Sisson, president of Baltimore's Clipper City Brewing Co.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The threat is real, people. You know &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://beeradvocate.com/beer/profile/3620/2898/"&gt;Tupper's Hop Pocket&lt;/a&gt;, right? Well, not this year you won't — ingredient prices have made it not viable to produce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, to summarize: changing global climate; baseless biofuel enthusiasm; and the terrifying prospect of a nation's worth of people who look different from use dragging themselves out of poverty — all of these forces are conspiring to make your favorite brand of beer marginally more expensive and/or taste a little less like pine needles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And what are our prospective presidential nominees doing about this looming crisis? Nothing. There was only one man prepared to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.dennis4president.com/go/issues/a-sustainable-future/"&gt;stop global climate change&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.desmoinesregister.com/apps/pbcs.dll/article?AID=/20071106/NEWS09/711060402"&gt;approach biofuels with appropriate skepticism&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.cfr.org/publication/14759/candidates_on_us_policy_toward_china.html#261"&gt;exact merciless economic punishment upon the Chinese&lt;/a&gt; for drinking beer (instead of attending to human rights). That's right — it was &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.satyamag.com/nov03/beerintro.html"&gt;Dennis Kucinich: the Beer Candidate&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately for our nation's future, this truth has become apparent too late. Hell, I would've done my best to support a Department of Peace with a straight face if only he'd explicitly pledged to keep beer prices low. I used to think it was just the former that couldn't occur without the latter; now I see that it works both ways.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics"/></entry></feed>