<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Tom Lee - politics, tech</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/feeds/politics-tech.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>https://tomlee.wtf/</id><updated>2009-10-29T11:58:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>let's get specific</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2009/10/29/lets-get-specific/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-10-29T11:58:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-10-29T11:58:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2009-10-29:/2009/10/29/lets-get-specific/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Tim &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://timothyblee.com/?p=1476"&gt;points out&lt;/a&gt; that Vint Cerf's advocacy for network neutrality doesn't mean that every venerable internet expert agrees with it.&amp;nbsp; True!&amp;nbsp; Google for &amp;quot;Dave Farber&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;Bob Kahn&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;net neutrality&amp;quot; and you'll find plenty of articles... from 2007.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this debate has stagnated.&amp;nbsp; People are continuing to act …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Tim &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://timothyblee.com/?p=1476"&gt;points out&lt;/a&gt; that Vint Cerf's advocacy for network neutrality doesn't mean that every venerable internet expert agrees with it.&amp;nbsp; True!&amp;nbsp; Google for &amp;quot;Dave Farber&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;Bob Kahn&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;net neutrality&amp;quot; and you'll find plenty of articles... from 2007.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this debate has stagnated.&amp;nbsp; People are continuing to act as if the FCC's plan is a complete unknown. This enables the lazy &amp;quot;evil corporation/incompetent government&amp;quot; frame that we all know and love. At one point this was at least semi-appropriate.&amp;nbsp; People -- including those like Cerf, Farber and Kahn -- made guesses about what was likely to happen, largely based on their own position along the regulation/markets ideological spectrum. &amp;quot;The government is trying to outlaw QoS!&amp;quot; &amp;quot;The ISPs are going to charge for Google!&amp;quot;&amp;nbsp; Both of these positions were hyperbolic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But look, there's a difference now: the FCC has announced its &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.openinternet.gov/read-speech.html#book5"&gt;NN principles&lt;/a&gt;, to thundering... well, there hasn't been much reaction, actually.&amp;nbsp; Everyone's just pretending that nothing happened and sticking to their guns.&amp;nbsp; &amp;quot;The principles are too vague!&amp;quot; they cry, even though those principles say that allowances will be made for necessary network management, that throttling heavy users will be okay, that malware can be filtered, that copyright law can be enforced, and that managed services can be developed and sold.&amp;nbsp; That wipes out a significant swath of the ISPs' objections.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet no one seems to have noticed. &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://voices.washingtonpost.com/posttech/2009/10/computer_science_professor_dav.html"&gt;Here's Farber responding to the new principles&lt;/a&gt; -- he doesn't particularly object to them, he just thinks they're too vague and that they might make ISPs wary of trying to innovate (as if the research costs to network management are so great that the potential for work product to be shot down makes it impractical; please, this is &lt;em&gt;software&lt;/em&gt;).&amp;nbsp; He also says they'll lead to a bunch of lawsuits, though he simultaneously says we should instead rely on the DOJ and FTC to handle this (in a rule-free environment!), which makes just about no sense to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I digress.&amp;nbsp; Look: the FCC has put some of its cards on the table.&amp;nbsp; Not all!&amp;nbsp; Rulemaking still needs to occur (if it didn't, opponents would be even more outraged).&amp;nbsp; But the agency &lt;em&gt;has&lt;/em&gt; signaled that it's not actually going to do the incredibly idiotic things that neutrality opponents claimed it would. Those people need to acknowledge this fact, and come up with a clarified set of objections. What is it, exactly, that the FCC's stated plans are going to stop you from doing? Right now I'm just seeing a bunch of now-irrelevant FUD; some talk about how great a monopolistic IPTV market would be; and some hand-waving about &amp;quot;new business models&amp;quot;, which I take to be a synonym for &amp;quot;rent-seeking&amp;quot;.&amp;nbsp; It's time to admit that the FCC isn't the one being vague.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics, tech"/></entry><entry><title>after Twitter</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2009/07/02/after-twitter/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-07-02T16:01:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-07-02T16:01:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2009-07-02:/2009/07/02/after-twitter/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.google.com/search?q=site%3Atechliberation.com%20%22tim%20lee%22"&gt;Tim&lt;/a&gt; was nice enough to write &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://twitter.com/binarybits/status/2393230558"&gt;a tweet&lt;/a&gt; endorsing &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.prospect.org/cs/articles?article=the_cost_of_hashtag_revolution"&gt;my article about the potential downside of Twitter's emerging political importance&lt;/a&gt;. But he noted that I didn't say much about what the alternatives are — fair enough! As I said to him in response, I was only too happy to have word …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.google.com/search?q=site%3Atechliberation.com%20%22tim%20lee%22"&gt;Tim&lt;/a&gt; was nice enough to write &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://twitter.com/binarybits/status/2393230558"&gt;a tweet&lt;/a&gt; endorsing &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.prospect.org/cs/articles?article=the_cost_of_hashtag_revolution"&gt;my article about the potential downside of Twitter's emerging political importance&lt;/a&gt;. But he noted that I didn't say much about what the alternatives are — fair enough! As I said to him in response, I was only too happy to have word limits save me from having to propose a solution. Even though I think the situation is unfortunate, at this point I suspect that there isn't much to be done about Twitter's rising political relevance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, y'know, time heals all wounds. I am convinced that Twitter's import as a cultural hub will decline. Twitter won't go away entirely, mind you — it's a genuine medium unto itself — but I think its true legacy is likely to be a frankly unbelievable extension, evolution and popularization of the capabilities represented by SMS. Multicast? Common use of symbolic delimiters like &amp;#64; and #? Widespread institutional adoption? Two years ago, if you'd asked Verizon when SMS would be used this way, they'd have laughed in your face. Now the marketplace is going to demand this functionality — if not from Twitter, then from someone else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as I said, I think the conversations happening on Twitter will become less relevant, and the medium less vibrant. Actually, I'm beginning to think that this is an iron law of online mediums. &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.apt11d.com/2009/07/the-blogosphere-20.html"&gt;This post&lt;/a&gt; (via &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://meganmcardle.theatlantic.com/archives/2009/07/when_blogs_were_young.php"&gt;Megan&lt;/a&gt;) helped focus my thinking a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's how it goes. First, a network achieves viability — enough people are using it to send non-&amp;quot;hello world&amp;quot; messages that the community can sustain itself. Next, users experiment, publishing and republishing content that they find compelling. The system amounts to a collaborative filter, and the quality and novelty of the results are surprisingly good. At this point people begin to notice and discuss the potential for the network to have greater relevance — and, inevitably, those who don't understand that participation in the filtering activity is non-negotiable begin whining about taking the medium seriously when they see so much trivial content on it. Despite this carping, more users join the network and its value and potential importance begin to be more widely understood. At this point users change how they identify content worth publishing or republishing: rather than the first-order &amp;quot;how compelling is this?&amp;quot; they begin using the second-order &amp;quot;how compelling will other people find this?&amp;quot; Although they were excellent and determining what they thought was interesting and appropriate, they're comparatively terrible at determining what other people will like. Quality declines (&amp;quot;I blogged: del.icio.us links for 2009-07-02&amp;quot;). Worse, as users continue to try to shirk their collaborative filtering responsibilities, experimental uses of the medium are discouraged or otherwise become less viable. The system ossifies, and soon enough everyone is sick of having to check Facebook. Time for a new no-pressure medium for goofing off with your early-adopter friends. Rinse, repeat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't want to oversell the preceding — I'm pretty sure that Clay Shirky accidentally scribbles more profound sociological observations about the internet during the course of searching for a working ballpoint pen at the bank. But this is my understanding of the situation, and by now I think we have enough data points to conclude that most, if not all online social networks achieve viability, blossom and stagnate (it may still be entirely possible to run a viable business during the stagnation phase, I should point out).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It'll happen to Twitter, too — it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; happening. So let's start talking now about what conditions we should demand of the next medium-of-the-moment before we start moving our political institutions onto it. My suggestion for a place to start: open, free, and likely to remain so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="/2009/03/17/i-do-love-conspiracies/"&gt;This&lt;/a&gt; is somewhat related — it's an example of what I mean by people withdrawing from the collaborative filtering process.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics, tech"/></entry><entry><title>more hand-wringing over Twitter: now with a borrowed sense of legitimacy!</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2009/06/29/more-hand-wringing-over-twitter-now-with-a-borrowed-sense-of-legitimacy/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-06-29T12:05:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-06-29T12:05:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2009-06-29:/2009/06/29/more-hand-wringing-over-twitter-now-with-a-borrowed-sense-of-legitimacy/</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Phoebe was nice enough to ask me to develop my queasiness over Twitter's political ascendancy into an article for the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.prospect.org"&gt;Prospect&lt;/a&gt;. If you're interested, you can find it &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.prospect.org/cs/articles?article=the_cost_of_hashtag_revolution"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics, tech"/></entry><entry><title>more on Twitter and Iran</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2009/06/16/more-on-twitter-and-iran/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-06-16T09:47:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-06-16T09:47:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2009-06-16:/2009/06/16/more-on-twitter-and-iran/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/matthewyglesias/~3/e8u1l1-DB80/technology-and-political-change.php"&gt;Yglesias&lt;/a&gt; links to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.themonkeycage.org/2009/06/what_if_we_twittered_the_revol.html"&gt;Farrell&lt;/a&gt;; both are worth reading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's still not clear to me the extent to which technology is enabling intramural communication among the protesters, as opposed to simply serving as a broadcast medium between a few of them and the west. I'm very curious to find out, though …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://feedproxy.google.com/~r/matthewyglesias/~3/e8u1l1-DB80/technology-and-political-change.php"&gt;Yglesias&lt;/a&gt; links to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.themonkeycage.org/2009/06/what_if_we_twittered_the_revol.html"&gt;Farrell&lt;/a&gt;; both are worth reading.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's still not clear to me the extent to which technology is enabling intramural communication among the protesters, as opposed to simply serving as a broadcast medium between a few of them and the west. I'm very curious to find out, though, and have a few emails out to people running proxies asking how much activity they're seeing from plausibly Iranian IPs. At least one has committed to figuring this out; we'll see if he follows through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; increasingly clear: the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://andrewsullivan.theatlantic.com/.a/6a00d83451c45669e201157119dc65970b-800wi"&gt;idea that you can change the world from your computer has a strong allure&lt;/a&gt;. From the various alleged DoS attacks underway* to the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://twitter.com/cshirky/status/2187031862"&gt;wrangling&lt;/a&gt; over &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://reinikainen.co.uk/2009/06/iranelection-cyberwar-guide-for-beginners/"&gt;hashtags and profile data&lt;/a&gt; (based on what seems to be pretty tenuous speculation about the regime's filtering plans and abilities), a lot of narcissism is masquerading as activism. But then, this is the internet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;* These seem virtually certain to be counterproductive — how exactly does damaging digital communication empower the side without the TV stations in an information war? How are targets even being identified, except via the diktat of trusted-but-unverified Twitter users?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE:&lt;/strong&gt; Austin Heap, who seems to be running the biggest clearinghouse for #iranelection proxies, has &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://blog.austinheap.com/2009/06/16/why/"&gt;written an update&lt;/a&gt; sharing some stats. He's apparently filtering source IP (seemingly using &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.countryipblocks.net/country-blocks/select-formats/"&gt;this list&lt;/a&gt;) and reports 2000 connections/second. Modern browsers reuse connections for multiple HTTP requests, so that's nothing to sneeze at. I've asked him whether he's comfortable generating some stats on where the outbound traffic is going.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WELL, HELL:&lt;/strong&gt; If the professional diplomats at the State Department &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.reuters.com/article/rbssTechMediaTelecomNews/idUSWBT01137420090616"&gt;thinks that Twitter is vital resource for Iranian protesters&lt;/a&gt;, I suppose I can't really argue otherwise. But it doesn't make me any happier about a privately-owned technology becoming a vital part of the infrastructure supporting political activity. I should add that Twitter as a company has been nothing but praiseworthy, from how they rescheduled their downtime to the openness represented by their API. But there are limits to any for-profit enterprise's goodwill. I would feel a lot more comfortable if #iranelection was occurring on a decentralized network (and yes, I realize there are immense technological hurdles to such a thing being practical).&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics, tech"/></entry><entry><title>I only favor internet triumphalism when it's about non-proprietary tech</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2009/06/15/i-only-favor-internet-triumphalism-when-its-about-non-proprietary-tech/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-06-15T16:45:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-06-15T16:45:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2009-06-15:/2009/06/15/i-only-favor-internet-triumphalism-when-its-about-non-proprietary-tech/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Look, I know I have a dog in this fight — as much as I like Twitter, I really, &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; bristle at the idea of a communication medium being coronated as essential while it's still a proprietary product of a single company (which hasn't yet set pricing!). I know I'm biased …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Look, I know I have a dog in this fight — as much as I like Twitter, I really, &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; bristle at the idea of a communication medium being coronated as essential while it's still a proprietary product of a single company (which hasn't yet set pricing!). I know I'm biased. But still, c'mon: you can't tell me that people aren't a bit overeager to write &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://politics.theatlantic.com/2009/06/its_too_easy_to_call.php"&gt;this story&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think there's reason for skepticism about Ambinder's claims. My understanding is that &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.google.com/hostednews/afp/article/ALeqM5jSPlmVgh-SfeEO9WhpOVG6Slnu0w"&gt;cell service has been disrupted in Tehran since Saturday evening&lt;/a&gt;, and that net access to Twitter from Iran is blocked, making it only possible to access the site through a shifting set of proxy servers — a task that requires both technical expertise and which is typically impractical to do on a mobile device. Ambinder's vision of furtive Twitter revolutionaries users collaboratively helping one another dodge #machinegunnests seems like wishful thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It does seem unquestionable that Twitter has enabled the coverage of the events in Iran to proceed with an immediacy that's novel to the medium. Partly this is simply because Twitter is currently enjoying a lot of excitement and attention from journalists; partly it's because the medium really does enable the centralized distribution of information on a time scale that was previously impractical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when all is said and done, the centralization means it's still relatively brittle when faced with a government keen on blocking it. Again: how are Iranians supposed to have been using the service? Yes, clearly &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.h3x.no/2009/06/14/iranians-on-twitter-during-the-june-clashes/"&gt;some are&lt;/a&gt;. But how many, really? While it's been a fascinating way for all of us to learn what's going on in Iran, I still doubt that enough people in Iran have access to the site for it to be significantly enabling or shaping events there. Maybe I'm wrong. We'll see.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics, tech"/></entry><entry><title>the uncannily inefficient Valley</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2009/06/14/the-uncannily-inefficient-valley/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-06-14T14:16:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-06-14T14:16:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2009-06-14:/2009/06/14/the-uncannily-inefficient-valley/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yglesias is fond of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://yglesias.thinkprogress.org/archives/2009/06/how-to-fix-bank-compensation.php"&gt;suggesting&lt;/a&gt; Silicon Valley's compensation model as a good alternative to the one that led the finance industry into distaster. The idea is that by using stock options to connect compensation to the long-term performance of a company rather than to its quarterly or yearly performance, we …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yglesias is fond of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://yglesias.thinkprogress.org/archives/2009/06/how-to-fix-bank-compensation.php"&gt;suggesting&lt;/a&gt; Silicon Valley's compensation model as a good alternative to the one that led the finance industry into distaster. The idea is that by using stock options to connect compensation to the long-term performance of a company rather than to its quarterly or yearly performance, we can make short-term risk-taking less lucrative than intelligent stewardship of a firm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sounds like a pretty good idea, and very well may be. But it's worth pointing out a couple of things: first, this may just be an apples and oranges sort of situation. It may not be the case that the sort of compensation structures available to a penniless startup are practically applicable to an enormous financial behemoth. I'm admittedly no expert, but I can imagine there may be problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second — and this I can say with somewhat more confidence — the performance of the software industry is not such an inspirational success story that emulating it should be assumed to be a good idea. Spend three months reading TechCrunch or its equivalent; if you can make it through that time without killing yourself, you'll realize that Silicon Valley is incredibly inefficient, wasting vast sums of money on overhyped ideas that are stupid, unnecessary or just commercially impractical. There are very, very few firms that have created genuinely original technologies — technologies that Harry Turtledove would like to write about, technologies that may conceivably never have been invented if their creators' parents hadn't met. The bulk of the industry is made up of the proverbial million monkeys sitting at a million MacBooks; occasionally some Javascript comes out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some friends of mine have created a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://tractorlizard.com/"&gt;fake web startup&lt;/a&gt;. On their homepage (or twitter feed) you can find a simple mad-lib that changes every time you reload the page, and which goes like this: &amp;quot;[VAGUE, POSITIVE GERUND] [TECHNOLOGY A] with [TECHNOLOGY B].&amp;quot; This really is how the industry operates: through the mind-numbing combinatorial exhaustion of whatever technologies Google, Amazon, Adobe, Sun and a very few brilliant open-source developers can come up with. Some of this is valuable, even necessary economic activity. But a lot of it is just speculative activity which benefits no one other than the people directly involved — and which is ultimately a waste of resources. This should sound wearyingly familiar by now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, it's not all their fault. The real problem is that software development is really easy — you need almost no capital, and there's an incredible wealth of existing technology that can be utilized. The bottlenecks to innovative commercial activity in the software realm are frequently external. These limits can be technological but not software-related (phone cameras needed to get good enough to read barcodes), cultural (Facebook couldn't exist until college students were wired enough to adopt it) or political (only a firm of Google's size and import could start scanning books and comfortably expect to find a way out of the orphan works problem without being sued into oblivion). And of course it's just generally tough to start a successful business (I think I can confidently say that the average internet startup is based on a somewhat stupider idea than the average non-internet startup, but I have no idea which is actually more likely to fail). I'm sympathetic to these guys: certainly, I can understand the impulse to paint yourself a visionary who creates fundamentally new possibilities, rather than as mere skilled craftsman using tools handed down from others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But still, it's hard to look at the amount of investor money wasted on the web industry and conclude that its compensation practices are ones that should be emulated — particularly given that those practices &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.mercurynews.com/ci_12530080"&gt;are being abandoned&lt;/a&gt; now that &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://knowledge.wharton.upenn.edu/article.cfm?articleid=1465"&gt;the accounting gimmick that enabled them has been ended&lt;/a&gt;. Maybe it's preferable to have a lot of middle-class programmers blowing through investor money instead of a relatively few upper class finance executives doing the same — I suppose it &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; a more progressive transfer — but that's all that Silicon Valley's recent history seems to promise. The way to neutralize the villains of this bubble may not be to make them more like the villains of the last bubble.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics, tech"/></entry><entry><title>Barack Obama does not want to be your Facebook friend</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2009/01/20/barack-obama-does-not-want-to-be-your-facebook-friend/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-01-20T16:47:00-05:00</published><updated>2009-01-20T16:47:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2009-01-20:/2009/01/20/barack-obama-does-not-want-to-be-your-facebook-friend/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Given that I'm a Professional Internet Guy, it's probably not wise for me to spend as much time as I do telling people that the web is less important than they think. But guys, seriously: the web is less important than you think — especially the new administration's use of the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Given that I'm a Professional Internet Guy, it's probably not wise for me to spend as much time as I do telling people that the web is less important than they think. But guys, seriously: the web is less important than you think — especially the new administration's use of the web.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.kottke.org/09/01/the-countrys-new-robotstxt-file"&gt;Kottke's analysis of the new robots.txt file at whitehouse.gov&lt;/a&gt; is the latest and most ludicrous example of our collective fascination with everything the Obama team does online. When placed on a webserver, a robots.txt file determines what sections of a website are ignored by search engines and other services that employ web crawling scripts. The Bush administration had a lengthy robots.txt file; the Obama administration does not. When someone bothers to point this out, they're trying to imply that Obama will be less secretive than Bush. It's a cute point to make, but c'mon — are we really supposed to believe that this means something? Does that mean, then, that the Obama administration's &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HTTP_ETag"&gt;ETag&lt;/a&gt;-enabled HTTP headers signal its commitment to energy conservation? Does the administration's use of Microsoft IIS prove that the Obama campaign's embrace of open source technologies was meaningless? No and no. It's just a goddamn website. The president is obviously not involved in these sorts of mundane engineering decisions; but more broadly, it's almost always a mistake to look for symbolism in such decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, I doubt that Kottke would claim to be making a serious point. In this regard, the online reaction to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.change.gov"&gt;change.gov&lt;/a&gt; was much sillier. As that site launched and evolved, I saw a lot of folks expressing sentiments like this: &amp;quot;Look how high issue X has been voted on change.gov! In the age of the web, how long can politicians afford to ignore the will of the people?!&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it comes to change.gov, the answer to this question is pretty clearly &amp;quot;indefinitely&amp;quot;. Seriously: does anyone really think something was accomplished by voting marijuana legalization into the third-most-popular spot? That lots of people would like to smoke weed legally and are willing to say so — so long as saying it costs them no time, money or liberty — that's not exactly a direct-democratic revelation. Nor does it represent some sort of wisdom-of-crowds, well-informed policy prescription that deserves respect. I'm in favor of marijuana legalization, but the idea that the expression of this preference on change.gov is worthy of political attention is laughable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the thing: the executive branch is pretty important, and it has been for a while. For this reason, various institutions supporting the interchange of information between the presidency and the public have evolved, from the White House Press Corps to the Gallup poll to, um, the legislative branch. This process actually works pretty well — it's not as if the president finds himself scratching his head, saying, &amp;quot;Gosh, I wonder what would be popular with the public?&amp;quot; The additional information-lubrication that technology can bring to bear on this problem will offer very slight benefits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now of course, you can say that the will of the people isn't sufficiently respected by our political institutions. But representing public opinion online isn't going to make it magically attract any more official notice than it does in other formats. In fact, decreasing the cost of expressions of policy preference arguably serves to &lt;em&gt;reduce&lt;/em&gt; the attention they receive. Consider how much value congressional offices place on phone calls versus paper mail or email. A hint: the harder and less form-letter-ready the medium, the more likely the staffer/glorified-CSR you deal with will be to make a tic mark on your behalf in the office tally for HR-whatever. How much attention do you think your opinion is going to garner when you give voice to it by clicking on an AJAX thumbs-up button? How much do you think it &lt;em&gt;deserves&lt;/em&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll go further: to whatever extent the Obama administration &lt;strong&gt;is&lt;/strong&gt; paying attention to change.gov, they're making a mistake. I mean, look, it's a nice idea. But if it's anything other than a cynical PR exercise, it's also a basically undemocratic empowerment of a particular constituency on the basis of the arbitrary criterion of Web 2.0-iness — which is admittedly better than gender or skin color, but still. &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://techdirt.com/articles/20080423/220819935.shtml"&gt;I thought this rankled when Comcast did it on Twitter&lt;/a&gt;, and I think it does here, too — although not as much, since the web is less of a niche forum than Twitter (and despite &amp;quot;what to do about Iraq?&amp;quot; probably being a more important question than &amp;quot;why aren't my HD channels working?&amp;quot;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one genuinely noteworthy aspect of all this online business is the direct line of communication it provides from the president to the public. Again, the import of this has been overstated: for all of its shortcomings, in most cases the media's coverage of the administration will be more useful to the public than the administration's presentation of itself. In the same way that you might visit the Toyota website when shopping for a car but give greater consideration to more disinterested sources of information like Consumer Reports, there's only so much attention that the public will — or should — pay to what the administration has to say for itself. The one big exception to this is the not-infrequent case where the media's market-determined forms preclude the efficient communication of information to the public, as when a nuanced sentiment from a speech is reduced to a sound bite. The president's online presence can offer a solution to this problem, achieving the (relatively few) advantages of a state media organ without any of the market- and opinion-distorting downsides.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But again: let's not overstate things. It's great that this capability exists; it's great that whitehouse.gov has gotten a new coat of paint. But these capabilities &lt;em&gt;have&lt;/em&gt; existed for a while now, and nobody's given a shit. The president's weekly radio address has been on iTunes &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://macdailynews.com/index.php/weblog/comments/6556/P100/"&gt;since 2005&lt;/a&gt; — how often have you found yourself listening to it at the gym? It's naive to think that the internet is going to supplant all the existing ways we have for the government to listen to the public; and it's silly to think that the public is going to remain keenly interested in what the government has to say just because Obama's hired someone who knows CSS. This is all useful stuff, but it's not going to revolutionize our society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The web is great and I'm glad our institutions are getting online. And the internet is changing — and already has changed — politics. But the real revolution here lies in the ways that technology makes it easier for people to organize into groups — groups that can then make their members' opinions heard through the traditional levers we have for affecting our government. Don't let me dissuade anyone from signing the urgent online petitions in their inboxes. But — so far, at least — all of the online attempts to completely disintermediate our democracy have been hopeless — even when they haven't also been hopelessly lame.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics, tech"/></entry><entry><title>the SoapBlox soap opera</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2009/01/08/the-soapblox-soap-opera/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-01-08T09:28:00-05:00</published><updated>2009-01-08T09:28:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2009-01-08:/2009/01/08/the-soapblox-soap-opera/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've been watching the SoapBlox saga, and its coverage, with morbid fascination — my interest and the vehemence of my reaction to it all are probably a sign of the increasingly provincial nature of my expertise, I suppose, and that's a little depressing. But still, I feel compelled to point out …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've been watching the SoapBlox saga, and its coverage, with morbid fascination — my interest and the vehemence of my reaction to it all are probably a sign of the increasingly provincial nature of my expertise, I suppose, and that's a little depressing. But still, I feel compelled to point out that most of the reaction to it is idiotic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the story: DailyKos runs on a system called Scoop. It's kind of a monstrosity, but large swaths of the netroots are used to it, terrified of change, and have consequently convinced themselves that the system they started using first happens to be technically superior to all the ones they encountered thereafter. This isn't a novel delusion by any means; most of us do it all the time, myself included.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One developer decided there were some things he didn't like about Scoop and elected to rewrite it in a different language. You can find the project announcement &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.dailykos.com/story/2005/3/27/61120/4863"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and it should immediately set off warning bells:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;There's no indication that he's envisioning his efforts as an open source project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;He clearly hasn't bothered to learn much about Scoop, given that he misidentifies the language it's written in as PHP rather than Perl. If he'd opened a single source file, he could not have made this mistake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;div class="first line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;He said this:&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;I am not a language snob. I know all languages have their place. And I see php as the language for a small to medium sized operation. Java is an Enterprise solution and a complete, robust language, capable of interacting with just about anything computer.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;If we want to take blogs to the next level, we have to take our blogging software to the next level.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;This is the kind of meaningless bullshit that salespeople say when they know nothing about anything except that they have something written in Java that they'd like to sell. Java's great, it's fine, but PHP powers sites like Digg and Facebook, so don't tell me it can't run your blog about Rhode Island politics. Perl, can, too — obviously it powers dKos and other Scoop sites, but it also manages to keep Slashdot afloat. It's not the loveliest language around, and aside from Scoop and Movable Type, web development has pretty much moved on to faster and/or cleaner languages. But it can clearly get the job done.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Also: &amp;quot;capable of interacting with just about anything computer&amp;quot;? What does that even mean?&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;His email address is &lt;em&gt;pacified69&amp;#64;yahoo.com&lt;/em&gt;. Come on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite this, the sorry state of Scoop hosting and the netroot throngs in its thrall seem to have been enough to push jScoop to some success as a proprietary host for political communities. The hosted effort was branded as SoapBlox, it acquired a few machines, and it charged reasonable rates. Then it got hacked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven't seen the code; it's not open source. And it's been years since I wrote any Java, so I might not be able to make heads or tails of it even if I did see it. But my guess is that the author didn't just reinvent the wheel in terms of Scoop, but also in terms of forms processing, sanitizing input, session handling and who knows what else. Some vulnerability was left exposed, and someone took advantage of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hey, we all make mistakes. Bugs happen. But it's our responsibility to make sure that our mistakes happen in places that are unlikely to lead to catastrophic problems. That means building on other people's work. Googling for existing projects and reading old mailing list archives is less fun than firing up TextMate and starting to type, but you've just gotta grit your teeth and do it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of SoapBlox's servers went offline, and the dev abruptly declared defeat. The users were understandably freaked out. Unfortunately, that's leading them to make some bad judgments. Here, from a Kos diary entitled &amp;quot;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.dailykos.com/story/2009/1/7/121323/7371/193/681191"&gt;Why SoapBlox Matters&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
SoapBlox includes all the major features of a community blog -- namely, user diaries and other community-building features. These features are NOT readily available in any other software platform WordPress, MoveableType and others make it exceedingly difficult to do things like diaries and frontpage promotions, and SoapBlox makes it easy.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This just isn't true. There are plenty of projects that can match the requirements of SoapBlox's users. I've used Drupal a lot, and can say with confidence that it offers the diary, threaded-commenting, rating, voting and front-page-promotion features that seem to be at the heart of Scoop. And hey, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://scoop.kuro5hin.org/comments/2006/6/1/41757/36255/9#9"&gt;this guy seems to like it&lt;/a&gt;. SoapBlox doesn't matter because of its software; it matters because of the bloggers and diarists that use it. Writing blog software is much, much easier than running a successful online political community. There's plenty of software out there, and the SoapBlox community ought to set its priorities accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right now parts of the netroots are rallying around SoapBlox, trying to get it back online in a sustainable way. This speaks well of them, but it's a mistake. This one-off of a project should never have been trusted with anything worth saving. Who knows what other exploits lurk in its codebase? Or what business problems might take it offline in the future? You can say that opensourcing the project will help resolve these problems, but that's only true if you can also find developer manpower willing to continue reinventing this particular wheel. Frankly, you're not going to find high-quality talent that's willing to donate its time to a cause this pointless.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.techpresident.com/blog/entry/33526/soapblox_burnout_points_to_vulnerability_in_left_s_infrastructure"&gt;TechPresident suggests another path&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Options now for SoapBlox include [...] wrapping the platform into the services offered by one of the bigger progressive tech firms like Blue State Digital, EchoDitto, or Advomatic.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking as a someone who until recently worked at EchoDitto, and whose boss is now one of Blue State's founders, this is also a stupid idea. If one of these firms wants to do this work for free, then sure, the SoapBlox bloggers should jump at the chance. But hiring a consultancy is an option that's vastly more expensive than what's needed by these sites — sites which are, frankly, not particularly sophisticated from a technical or design perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's what I would suggest. First, make sure the SoapBlox admin is content to keep the sites up, at least temporarily. Second, find a college-age technical wunderkind who's interested in politics and willing to work for cheap. These guys are a dime a dozen — I used to be one myself. Third, convince him to write an exporter for the SoapBlox data that puts it in a standardized format. Hooking into &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://code.google.com/p/google-blog-converters-appengine/"&gt;this project&lt;/a&gt; (found via &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://del.icio.us/al3x"&gt;al3x&lt;/a&gt;) might not be a bad idea. Getting the data into a portable form is the priority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, find someone at a consultancy like one of the aforementioned ones who's willing to help you figure out your requirements and specifications for a new suite of software. The simplest, best option is probably to just run Scoop. It's what you want anyway; might as well stop nosing around it. I'm not intimately familiar with Scoop, but a quick look at its installation procedure makes it look like the complexity of installing and running it has been vastly overstated. If you don't do that (or just want to help get the netroots off Scoop — a noble cause), then I'd suggest a hard look at Drupal and maybe Wordpress MU, or maybe Slashcode if for some reason you want to head toward Perl-land. You may have to get someone to develop a custom module or two to make the solution maximally Scoop-y, and you'll certainly need someone who knows their way around the system to help configure it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But given where the aesthetic bar has been set, this is not a particularly tough problem, and it shouldn't cost that much money. If this community can afford to send people to Netroots Nation or the DNC, it can surely afford a minor investment in its critical infrastructure. Oh, and one more thing: when users inevitably raise a hue and a cry because the order of links on the sidebar has changed, or because they have to reconfirm their email address, or because of some other stupid thing, you should ignore them. They just want attention. Learning new systems and habits is a pain, but not nearly so painful as continuing to limp along in a system that never should have been used in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics, tech"/></entry><entry><title>the pirate threat is overstated (with the possible exception of ghost pirates)</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/10/08/the-pirate-threat-is-overstated-with-the-possible-exception-of-ghost-pirates/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-10-08T13:22:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-10-08T13:22:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-10-08:/2008/10/08/the-pirate-threat-is-overstated-with-the-possible-exception-of-ghost-pirates/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Julian is &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://arstechnica.com/articles/culture/dodgy-digits-behind-the-war-on-piracy.ars"&gt;killin' it over at Ars&lt;/a&gt; — be sure to check out his latest. It's not exactly surprising that the content industry would lie about the economic impact of piracy, but it's fascinating to read Julian's account of how the numbers they quote were born. He's done a real service …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Julian is &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://arstechnica.com/articles/culture/dodgy-digits-behind-the-war-on-piracy.ars"&gt;killin' it over at Ars&lt;/a&gt; — be sure to check out his latest. It's not exactly surprising that the content industry would lie about the economic impact of piracy, but it's fascinating to read Julian's account of how the numbers they quote were born. He's done a real service to us all by hunting this story down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This bit, from near the article's end, raised my eyebrows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
... as Yochai Benkler has argued persuasively, IP is an input to innovation as well as the product of innovation. So under certain very specific conditions, &amp;quot;piracy&amp;quot; can produce net gains. While it seems extremely unlikely that this is the case in the aggregateâ€”IP theft almost certainly does impose net economic costsâ€”simply calculating lost sales and licencing fees, assuming someone could produce a credible figure, would not provide a complete picture of the economic impact of IP infringement. It would give us, at most, one side of the ledger.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Julian is smart to be conservative when making this point, but I suspect that those &amp;quot;very specific conditions&amp;quot; aren't all that specific at all. My hunch is that experience born of unauthorized use of IP provides necessary context to a huge variety of wealth-creating endeavors, even when the unauthorized use doesn't lead directly to the resulting innovation. This could take the form of a mixtape in a touring band's van or an automotive engineer checking out how the other guys built their throttle body; either way, the point is that there's a constant background hum of infringement that's innocuous and absolutely necessary for our society's continued functioning, but which is usually only considered during the drafting of RIAA press releases.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics, tech"/></entry><entry><title>central planning: better for technical standards than for economies</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/02/29/central-planning-better-for-technical-standards-than-for-economies/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-02-29T15:09:00-05:00</published><updated>2008-02-29T15:09:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-02-29:/2008/02/29/central-planning-better-for-technical-standards-than-for-economies/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ryan &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.ryanavent.com/blog/?p=786"&gt;responds&lt;/a&gt; to my last post. I appreciate the thoughtful attention, but I can't say that I agree with much of his post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
I understand what Tomâ€™s saying, but I think heâ€™s missing some key points. He wants to judge a technology in a &amp;quot;pure&amp;quot; world, outside the …&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ryan &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.ryanavent.com/blog/?p=786"&gt;responds&lt;/a&gt; to my last post. I appreciate the thoughtful attention, but I can't say that I agree with much of his post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
I understand what Tomâ€™s saying, but I think heâ€™s missing some key points. He wants to judge a technology in a &amp;quot;pure&amp;quot; world, outside the presence of the market conditions in which it will be sold and used, but you canâ€™t do that. The utility of a technology is inextricably connected to the market conditions in which it will be sold and used. A Beta videotape might clearly be superior on most quality variables, but if a VHS tape is long enough to hold a full-length movie and Beta isnâ€™t, well thatâ€™s important. Saying that length shouldnâ€™t be as important as other variables is pointless; the market didnâ€™t just want &amp;quot;Quality,&amp;quot; it wanted a certain quality.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was careful not to mention Beta/VHS before because Ryan's exactly right: length vs. quality is reasonable decision to have to make, and one that the market is better positioned to make than I am.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But his larger point is wrong. Yes, the utility of a technology can only be judged in relation to the world at large — more precisely, the world as it currently exists. But a technology absolutely can be judged apart from that, in its own timeless, rarified world. Every engineering discipline develops principles and design patterns by which work can be judged. Technical elegance is a real thing, and it really matters. Something designed well will be reusable, will be extensible, will be, as we sometimes say, &amp;quot;futureproof&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the difference between a good and a bad design does not always come with tradeoffs. The components in a DAT cassette deck and a high-end analog cassette deck are pretty similar. DAT has been much less commercially successful. But it is the superior technology. There's just no getting around that. In that case the cost of finding the better solution was time; in other cases it's as simple as giving a damn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&amp;gt;The fact is that in many cases it would be better if those factors were weighted differently.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Emphasis mine. To this, economists will say, &amp;quot;Says who?&amp;quot; But the broader point is this. Tom believes that he can look at a technology and say itâ€™s better or worse than another technology. Economists say he canâ€™t, because Tom doesnâ€™t actually know what the great mass of consumers wants.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll bite: why &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; I feel so confident saying it would be better if the weighting were different? Well, consider the reason why MS-DOS was successful: it was selected for inclusion on IBM's soon-to-be-blockbuster line of microcomputers. There were a number of similar technologies at the time, and it was up to IBM to choose one. Why MS-DOS? Well, depending on which version of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.freeenterpriseland.com/BOOK/KILDALL.html"&gt;the story&lt;/a&gt; you subscribe to, it was because Bill Gates' main competitor was late to a meeting, or his wife wouldn't sign an NDA, or, ironically, because the competing system was &lt;em&gt;too successful in the marketplace&lt;/em&gt; and its owner — not realizing how valuable or market-changing the IBM deal would be — didn't want to sign over his business for what IBM was offering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This all made perfect sense at the time. But now, decades later, what has the result been? It would be wrong to assign all of Microsoft's sins to MS-DOS, but the fact remains that the system was unequivocally technically inferior to other operating systems of the day, as judged by those aforementioned engineering principles. And those principles won out, as they almost always do: limitations of MS-DOS that may not have been immediately apparent became evident as technology advanced, and countless amounts of money and effort had to be expended to come up with workarounds, fixes and kludges. In a word: externalities!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How much did that all cost? I have no idea, but it clearly dwarfs the amounts that were being weighed and judged against one another during the IBM-CP/M-MSDOS deal. There's every reason to believe that, had a superficially similar but fundamentally superior technology to MS-DOS been selected, we would all be better off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now of course I can't say that definitively. Maybe the productivity gains of an all-Unix world would have been so great that we'd have accidentally opened an interdimensional portal to Dinosaur World by now and all been devoured. Or something. But I can say that the selection of an engineered product carries costs that may not be apparent for years — costs that non-experts are in no position to estimate until they occur. And even experts can generally only say &amp;quot;this was built well&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;this was built poorly&amp;quot;. But in many cases that's enough, and it would save us all a lot of money if we listened to those pronouncements more carefully.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, and one more thing: it's probably worth noting that one of the greatest technical (and economic) triumphs in recent memory — TCP/IP and the suite of other protocols and standards that powers the internet — was designed by having a bunch of really smart engineers get together, execute an RFC process and then issue an ISO standard more or less by fiat. This is not to say that markets can't help us arrive at good solutions — cable vs. DSL vs. FiOS is a good example of such a market working (or would be if the regulatory picture weren't so complicated). But it ought to be acknowledged that markets are not always an optimal tool for making technical decisions. In fact there are now pseudo-centralized organizations that take responsibility for many of the technical standards that power our world, and nearly all engineers agree that we're vastly better off for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE:&lt;/strong&gt; Tim, who knows considerably more about this than I do, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.techliberation.com/archives/043402.php"&gt;corrects my history&lt;/a&gt; and explains that TCP/IP &lt;em&gt;did&lt;/em&gt; triumph through competition with other protocols. Fair enough! But I think the point stands: even when there is a &amp;quot;competition&amp;quot; stage in drafting a net technology spec — and this is an important function of the RFC process, so there ought to be — it's still true that the selection of the winning ideas/specs is largely isolated from the consumer economy, and with good reason. In cases where the consumer economy inserts itself in the process — e.g. when Microsoft uses its marketshare to undercut the W3C — most people agree that the end result is detrimental. Openness and the winnowing of ideas is important, but when the decisions involve infrastructure the process needs to be restricted to those with some expertise.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics, tech"/></entry><entry><title>IP piracy is just like terrorism (and vice versa)</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2007/10/02/ip-piracy-is-just-like-terrorism-and-vice-versa/" rel="alternate"/><published>2007-10-02T12:34:00-04:00</published><updated>2007-10-02T12:34:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2007-10-02:/2007/10/02/ip-piracy-is-just-like-terrorism-and-vice-versa/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Two other things occurred to me about that bird-supplied &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.senate.gov/~govt-aff/index.cfm?Fuseaction=Hearings.Detail&amp;amp;HearingID=441"&gt;testimony before the Senate&lt;/a&gt;, so I'll share them quickly and then return to hi-tech frivolity. Apologies in advance for seeming to presume that I know things about terrorism; clearly, I don't. I do know things about the internet, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that's …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Two other things occurred to me about that bird-supplied &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.senate.gov/~govt-aff/index.cfm?Fuseaction=Hearings.Detail&amp;amp;HearingID=441"&gt;testimony before the Senate&lt;/a&gt;, so I'll share them quickly and then return to hi-tech frivolity. Apologies in advance for seeming to presume that I know things about terrorism; clearly, I don't. I do know things about the internet, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that's the first thing that struck me: how typically internetty it all is. The networks as described in &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/11/16/AR2005111602120.html"&gt;Michael Doran&lt;/a&gt;'s testimony sound very much like other illicit online networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;At any given moment in any given language, only a limited number of sites post original material produced directly by terrorist organizations or by religious authorities to whom the organizations have pledged loyalty. The majority of terrorist websites in operation are either mirrored versions of these existing sites or simply bulletin boards that disseminate material that originated on the websites under the direct control of the terrorist organizations.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;...&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Well, these are websites that are controlled by people who are known to each other and they will post authoritative information on the website and then it will be disseminated out by loyalists all across the Internet.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;On these bulletin boards — these are bulletin boards where they're password protected — certain individuals, their user names will become known as authoritative individuals.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;I'll give you an example. There was this American Johnson who was kidnapped in Saudi Arabia and killed. Within hours of his kidnapping, his wallet with his ID appeared — a photo of it — appeared on this website.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;So from an event like that, you can then conclude that that website is directly connected to the kidnappers and it's an authoritative website.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Then an individual on that website, whenever an al Qaeda-related event would take place would tell you, if you want to see our statement about that event, go to the following address and then you go to that address. Once it's out there and authenticated, then it just spreads like wildfire.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you haven't, go read Jeff Howe's excellent &amp;quot;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.wired.com/wired/archive/13.01/topsite.html"&gt;The Shadow Internet&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot; over at Wired. It describes the surprisingly centralized system that powers nearly all online piracy. There's a collection of &amp;quot;topsites&amp;quot; operating as a darknet — one that's known and accessible only to trusted individuals. Release groups compete within the topsites to see who can provide the best software fastest. From there the releases trickle into increasingly public places on the net: private bittorrent trackers, usenet, and finally public P2P networks. The same sort of tiered content distribution system seems to underpin terrorist website economy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They're similar in other ways, too:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Jihadis — they compete for membership. They don't all like each other. It's not a monolithic organization that everyone supports everyone. They are discrediting and de-legitimizing their competitors online.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This all sounds very familiar. It seems plausible to me that the same dynamic emerges in both cases: an ecosystem of poseurs, parasites and a very few elite operators who can provide the original content that powers the scene. These individuals arrange and rearrange themselves into groups that compete for prestige.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If this analogy is valid, the good news would be that the majority of people involved are hapless, subliterate, and totally useless to the purpose of the scene with which they've associated themselves. Getting groups to pick fights with one another would be relatively easy, and targeting elite users could yield large benefits. Check out how many pirated releases one user (or group of users assuming a single identity) named &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://isohunt.com/torrents/?ihq=aXXo"&gt;aXXo&lt;/a&gt; is responsible for, for instance. For all of our internet-powered talk of network effects, it's still the case that particular individuals can have an outsize effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this analogy would bring bad news, too. Elite members of the piracy scene do what they do purely for the prestige that comes with it, and so are not prone to rationally responding to the risks and rewards introduced by law enforcement. They typically don't make any money from piracy — that's frowned upon — but they persist at their secret hobby despite the years or decades of jail time they face if caught. You'll occasionally hear a Marxist accounting of their pasttime, but it seems that in most cases that's merely a self-serving justification for their prestige-seeking behavior. It's tempting to see parallels between this and the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2005/04/28/AR2005042801315.html"&gt;apparently not-all-that-devout 9/11 hijackers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's another analogy that became apparent to me, too, relating to how the government plans to assess and interdict these groups. The vast majority of online interest in jihad must come to nothing — like punk rock's endorsement of anarchy or hipster use of communist iconography, it's just a standard under which disaffected teenagers can unite. I've had a site &lt;a class="reference external" href="/2007/04/22/nabopoll-is-terrible-software-dont-use-it/"&gt;vandalized&lt;/a&gt; with anti-American/anti-Israel rhetoric before, for instance, but I think it'd be a stretch to call it a political act. And it would clearly be a colossal waste of resources for the IDF or US military to track down the perpetrator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what threat do these sites actually pose? Here's Mr. Doran again:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;The Internet is also a useful tool for recruitment. In addition to other social influences, potential recruits are flooded with propaganda, training manuals, and religious justification for joining the jihad via the Internet.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;It is difficult to say how much direct recruitment takes place on the Web. While it is likely that direct invitations to take party in terrorist organizations are usually delivered face to face, there is no doubt that the Web plays an important role in indoctrinating recruits before they are drawn in directly. Probably for this reason, extremist will not attempt to recruit overtly for violent action, but will instead legitimate the actions of terrorists and encourage readers to support the jihad however they can.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Terrorist websites, chat rooms, and other forums make use of the Internet for fundraising. These websites often use the argument that every Muslim has a duty to support jihad but that participation on the ground is not required of everyone. The appeal for financial support alone is a method of permitting an individual to feel that they have done their duty as a Muslim but do not need to change their life in order to join the actual fight.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Terrorist use of the Internet also includes operational training. Would-be terrorists can find training information in the use of small arms, mortars, rockets and artillery, guidance on where to fire at U.S . military vehicles in order to inflict the greatest damage, sniper training and detailed instructions about the construction of improvised explosive devices, suicide vests, et cetera. Training is also available for guidance on how, when and where to cross the borders of Iraq to join the jihad and how to avoid detection as a jihadist.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it's difficult to quantify the specific damage being done by these sites — we know there's fundraising, but don't have numbers for it (or at least none impressive enough to present to a Senate committee). We know that the sites probably lower the cost of recruitment for terrorist groups, but can't say by how much or whether the supply of offline recruits is sufficiently constrained for it to make much of a difference. And we know that some training information is available online, but don't know whether this is actually used to perpetrate violence or whether it's more akin to the ASCII copy of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anarchist%27s_Cookbook"&gt;Anarchist Cookbook&lt;/a&gt; that my friends and I nervously &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Xmodem"&gt;XMODEMed&lt;/a&gt; to one another in middle school and then never, ever used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In short, we know these sites are bad but can't say exactly &lt;em&gt;how&lt;/em&gt; bad (although if this was a budget hearing the answer would probably be &amp;quot;very&amp;quot;). What are we going to do about it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
We've got to do everything we can as quickly as we can to disrupt their websites when appropriate and necessary and compete with them for the attention of those who frequent their sites. We need to monitor their sites constantly for information and use them to exploit the visions among different sects and factions. And we need to recruit trolls who can sew seeds of doubt in the different extremists' websites and chat rooms. Obviously in the end, we need to develop the ability to shut down these sites when they represent an actual danger to us.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And here's &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.healthsystem.virginia.edu/internet/ciag/who_we_are/steering_committee/cilluffo.cfm"&gt;Frank Cilluffo&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&amp;quot;Honey pots&amp;quot; offer one way to achieve these goals. Among other things, they could allow us to better understand how local political grievances may become appropriated by the larger extremist movement, which in turn could help us drive wedges and blast open existing fault lines between and among factions.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.bigchampagne.com/"&gt;Monitoring&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.afterdawn.com/news/archive/3101.cfm"&gt;poisoning&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.zeropaid.com/news/8877/Gotcha!+New+MPAA+Site+Tries+to+Trick+Users+into+Illegally+Downloading+Movies"&gt;honeypots&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.chillingeffects.org/"&gt;takedowns&lt;/a&gt;. Sound familiar? It's what the media companies have been doing to fight piracy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you know, the results of that effort have been fairly dismal. It's true that the media companies have increased the effort and risk associated with downloading pirated content, but not by much — the return on their investment in services from firms like MediaDefender and Overpeer can't be very good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's hard to say how things would shake out when targeting extremist websites. On the one hand the effort seems likely to be much more expensive: the exchange of information on these sites must be predominantly legal, requiring more detailed scrutiny in order to find actionable offenses. And there are technical considerations that make it easier to automate catching P2P users than it is to catch visitors to a given website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, it seems likely that we could allocate more money for saving American soldiers' lives than we have for saving American executives' lifestyles. The scope (if not the implications) of iSlamofascism is smaller than that of piracy, too, and seems likely to stay that way: hopefully, deep down, the average human enjoys watching Bittorrented episodes of &lt;em&gt;Lost&lt;/em&gt; more than they enjoy killing their fellow man.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, it seems likely to be an expensive effort that produces limited results against a threat that may not actually be all that threatening. As with piracy, the online problem seems likely to abate when the underlying condition is resolved: people don't like paying for mandatory content distribution systems that they don't need, and they like Western meddling in the Middle East even less.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The internet makes communication very cheap — but that's all it does. This lowers some of our enemies' costs. We can re-raise them, but it'll be expensive to do so. And given that the online extremist phenomenon seems to be primarily symptomatic in nature, I think it'd probably be a mistake to divert too many resources to fighting it.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics, tech"/></entry><entry><title>universal seething hatred is a good sign that something's wrong</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2007/07/19/universal-seething-hatred-is-a-good-sign-that-somethings-wrong/" rel="alternate"/><published>2007-07-19T13:25:00-04:00</published><updated>2007-07-19T13:25:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2007-07-19:/2007/07/19/universal-seething-hatred-is-a-good-sign-that-somethings-wrong/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I think Tim's being just a bit disingenuous &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/techliberation/~3/135144554/042577.php"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; when he discusses the relative competitiveness of the cell phone market:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Itâ€™s nonsensical to say thereâ€™s no competition because consumers only choose a wireless carrier once a year (or even once every two years). Most people donâ€™t buy …&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I think Tim's being just a bit disingenuous &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/techliberation/~3/135144554/042577.php"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; when he discusses the relative competitiveness of the cell phone market:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Itâ€™s nonsensical to say thereâ€™s no competition because consumers only choose a wireless carrier once a year (or even once every two years). Most people donâ€™t buy computers, cars, or major appliances more often than that, yet no one claims that makes those industries uncompetitive. If consumers get crappy service during their contracts, they remember this fact and switch to a different carrier at the end of the contract period. And consumers comparison shop before they sign a contract, so phone companies have as much incentive to keep their prices low in a contract-based system as they would in a system without contracts.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's true that purchasing at intervals doesn't rule out competition. But this argument ignores a few salient points about this particular market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nearly all phones are locked, minimizing their resale value. Transferring your contact information between low-to-midrange phones is difficult or impossible. Until recently, you couldn't take your phone number with you (number portability is a much-loved big-government mandate that the carriers fought tooth &amp;amp; nail). Although some carriers let you transfer your contract to someone else without paying an ETF, doing so while retaining your number is more than a little tricky, if not downright impossible. And of course, contracts typically last longer than a mobile phone's window of technological relevance, ensuring that these barriers will be in place until the phone is worth only a fraction of its initial value, needs a new lithium battery, and is generally headed for the donation bin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of these factors inhibit the emergence of a viable market for used cellphones and plans, which in turn allows the carriers to avoid some of the sorts of competitive pressures facing refrigerator and automobile manufacturers. Yes, they have an incentive to keep their prices low in a contract-based system — but only within the bounds of that system. It's as if NFL players collectively agreed to play touch football for a season and used their union's power to freeze out replacement players. There could still be competition, but it wouldn't be nearly as vicious as it would need to be to optimally serve the public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's also this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
The iPhone point also strikes me as especially silly. The iPhone is expensive because itâ€™s a cutting-edge gadget thatâ€™s been on the market less than a month. The fact that some of the cost comes in the form of a 2-year contract, as opposed to an up-front sticker price, is beside the point. If you think the iPhone, 2-year contract and all, is too expensive, buy a different phone. There are plenty to choose from.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the point Ars is making is that the iPhone actually &lt;em&gt;isn't&lt;/em&gt; being subsidized by the contract fees. Consumers are buying the hardware at full retail price &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; being locked into a contract. This puts the lie to the carriers' argument that early termination fees are in place to avoid losses over hardware subsidies — they charge the fees whether there's a subsidy or not (and only one carrier will prorate this fee). Nor do customers have a way of opting out of this fraudulent system of portable phone paternalism. &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://machinist.salon.com/feature/2007/07/18/cell_service_contracts/index.html"&gt;As Farhad Manjoo wrote yesterday&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
You can't offer to pay full price for a handset in exchange for a reduced early-termination fee and an unlocked phone -- no major firm will let you do that. Indeed, in some instances carriers will charge you a fee even when they don't offer you any break on the price of the phone. The iPhone is the primary exhibit: AT&amp;amp;T doesn't subsidize the price of the phone, but you're still locked to a single provider.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm currently facing an ETF from T-Mobile for an account I set up without receiving a handset (I used it for my now-defunct DCist SMS service). In retrospect I should've signed up with a prepaid service. That would've been fine for my application, but these services typically charge more for services and offer less advanced phones. They're designed for customers who are credit risks (or drug dealers!). Unlike in Europe, prepaid is clearly not a viable way to opt out of the contract system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The actual reason the fees are in place is to prevent &amp;quot;churn&amp;quot; — the frequent switching between carriers by customers seeking better service, handsets or prices. Obviously this is a nuisance to carriers, and has real administrative costs. But surely the overhead to customer acquisition and early account termination is less than $150 (and if it is, surely it ought to be pro-rated when a customer has fulfilled part of their contract). No, the carriers are transparently using the fee to introduce friction into the marketplace, allowing them to extend the lifecycle of each generation of technology and spend more time in the pleasantly wide part of the margin that comes once they've paid off their capital investments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's nothing wrong with wanting to post nice fat profits, but I don't see a reason why we should enable this cartel-like activity. Customers will be better served by a faster-moving market. As it stands, customer dissatisfaction remains high across the industry, text messaging rates are going up rather than down and all customers with sub-smartphones remain locked into buying software exclusively from their carriers, despite countless forums filled with people vainly asking how to load mp3s as ringtones. And although the internet &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://consumerist.com/consumer/audio/ted-stevens-wants-to-switch-between-phones-as-i-ride-my-motorcycle-277702.php"&gt;jumped all over Ted Stevens&lt;/a&gt; for wanting a phone that would seamlessly rollover from wifi to cellular to landline access, his request wasn't unreasonable (well, except perhaps for the bit about the motorcycle) — VoIP/cell handing-off is useful technology that's been available for years, but is &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.wifinetnews.com/archives/007735.html"&gt;just barely&lt;/a&gt; showing up in the consumer marketplace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's simply not a very good or competitive market. Everybody hates it, and we ought to fix it. I have no idea whether a more open market would increase the total monthly expense of owning a cell phone. But even if it does, I suspect it would open up a lot of potential for growth of other industries — independent cellphone software, least-cost VoIP routing, third-party ringtones, better handsets, location-based services and who knows what else. Wireless data is a utility, not a retail product. Its market ought to be opened up.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics, tech"/></entry><entry><title>liveblogging globalization</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2007/07/13/liveblogging-globalization/" rel="alternate"/><published>2007-07-13T15:33:00-04:00</published><updated>2007-07-13T15:33:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2007-07-13:/2007/07/13/liveblogging-globalization/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.bunniestudios.com/blog/"&gt;Bunnie Huang&lt;/a&gt; is the man who cracked the Xbox — not once but twice, as he recently revealed himself to be involved with the hypervisor escalation exploit, too. He's an electronics god.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently he's been working on &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.chumby.com/"&gt;Chumby&lt;/a&gt;, a fun alarm clockish gadget that promises to bring widget-like capabilities to your …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.bunniestudios.com/blog/"&gt;Bunnie Huang&lt;/a&gt; is the man who cracked the Xbox — not once but twice, as he recently revealed himself to be involved with the hypervisor escalation exploit, too. He's an electronics god.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently he's been working on &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.chumby.com/"&gt;Chumby&lt;/a&gt;, a fun alarm clockish gadget that promises to bring widget-like capabilities to your bedside table. Part of his duties involve arranging and overseeing the production of the units in China.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He's just begun putting up a series of blog posts about his trip, and they're really fascinating. At the very least, be sure to check out the first one, which has video showcasing the incredible skill and speed of the workers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.bunniestudios.com/blog/?p=183"&gt;Made In China: Getting Started&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.bunniestudios.com/blog/?p=185"&gt;Made In China: Skill&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.bunniestudios.com/blog/?p=187"&gt;Made In China: Dedication&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.bunniestudios.com/blog/?p=190"&gt;Made In China: Feeding the Factory&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.bunniestudios.com/blog/?p=184"&gt;Made In China: Scale&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE:&lt;/strong&gt; I see that BoingBoing linked to these posts, too, and Bunnie's put up a notice saying his site may be inaccessible as a result. Whoops.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE 2:&lt;/strong&gt; Aaaand after further RSS catching-up, I see that son1 &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://bayes.wordpress.com/2007/07/13/potemkin-factories-crazy-story/"&gt;beat me to this&lt;/a&gt; by a mile. Sorry for the redundancy! But hey, everyone agrees: these posts are worth reading.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics, tech"/></entry><entry><title>gerrymandering: the game</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2007/06/19/gerrymandering-the-game/" rel="alternate"/><published>2007-06-19T12:40:00-04:00</published><updated>2007-06-19T12:40:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2007-06-19:/2007/06/19/gerrymandering-the-game/</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.redistrictinggame.com/index.php"&gt;Interesting idea&lt;/a&gt;. Found &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://games.slashdot.org/article.pl?sid=07/06/19/1414220"&gt;via Slashdot&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics, tech"/></entry></feed>