<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Tom Lee - politics, pop culture</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/feeds/politics-pop-culture.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>https://tomlee.wtf/</id><updated>2008-10-23T14:33:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>it's this obscure little radio show</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/10/23/its-this-obscure-little-radio-show/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-10-23T14:33:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-10-23T14:33:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-10-23:/2008/10/23/its-this-obscure-little-radio-show/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Megan &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://meganmcardle.theatlantic.com/archives/2008/10/quiet_in_the_peanut_gallery.php"&gt;doesn't care for Matt Taibbi's takedown of Byron York&lt;/a&gt;, in which Taibbi makes it sound like York has no idea what he's talking about with respect to the financial crisis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, I have no idea about any of this stuff other than feeling vaguely hostile toward Byron York. Still …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Megan &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://meganmcardle.theatlantic.com/archives/2008/10/quiet_in_the_peanut_gallery.php"&gt;doesn't care for Matt Taibbi's takedown of Byron York&lt;/a&gt;, in which Taibbi makes it sound like York has no idea what he's talking about with respect to the financial crisis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, I have no idea about any of this stuff other than feeling vaguely hostile toward Byron York. Still, I was a little uncomfortable when I first read that exchange: Taibbi's scolding about credit default swaps came at a time when a lot of other people on the internet were &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; suddenly speaking knowledgeably about the financial meltdown and the rarified financial instruments to blame for it. That wave of spontaneous expertise seemed to occur suspiciously shortly after the air date of an episode of This American Life that discussed the crisis and CDSes in particular.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which is not to say that TAL is wrong; I listened to that episode, too, and it seemed excellent! But it's been both amusing and off-putting to see so many people brazenly parroting the same single News Source White People Like. I have no idea if this criticism actually applies to Taibbi, but the conversation between him and York certainly made it sound like it could.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE:&lt;/strong&gt; Since Megan kindly linked back to me, I should probably add that while I can't be sure that my speculation about Taibbi's argument is correct, it's &lt;strong&gt;very&lt;/strong&gt; clear that York's pathetic line about Freddie and Fannie is a regurgitated conservative talking point — a particularly lame, objectionable and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://yglesias.thinkprogress.org/archives/2008/09/blaming_fannie_mae.php"&gt;well-debunked&lt;/a&gt; one at that. It seems likely that both sides of that conversation were blindly reciting other people's arguments.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics, pop culture"/></entry><entry><title>Spook Country</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/06/30/spook-country/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-06-30T18:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-06-30T18:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-06-30:/2008/06/30/spook-country/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/product/0425221415/?tag=unrequitednar-20&amp;amp;linkCode=asn&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0425221415"&gt;&lt;img alt="20080630_spookcountry.jpg" class="right" src="/static/2008/06/30/20080630_spookcountry.jpg" style="width: 144px; height: 225px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Last night I finished &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/product/0425221415/?tag=unrequitednar-20&amp;amp;linkCode=asn&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0425221415"&gt;Spook Country&lt;/a&gt;, William Gibson's most recent novel. &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://twitter.com/sbma44/statuses/846412851"&gt;Twittered snark&lt;/a&gt; aside, it's actually quite good — probably the best Gibson novel I've read, although it's mostly a do-over of &lt;em&gt;Pattern Recognition&lt;/em&gt;, and of course will never be as influential or noteworthy as &lt;em&gt;Neuromancer&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's definitely worth a read …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/product/0425221415/?tag=unrequitednar-20&amp;amp;linkCode=asn&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0425221415"&gt;&lt;img alt="20080630_spookcountry.jpg" class="right" src="/static/2008/06/30/20080630_spookcountry.jpg" style="width: 144px; height: 225px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Last night I finished &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.amazon.com/dp/product/0425221415/?tag=unrequitednar-20&amp;amp;linkCode=asn&amp;amp;creativeASIN=0425221415"&gt;Spook Country&lt;/a&gt;, William Gibson's most recent novel. &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://twitter.com/sbma44/statuses/846412851"&gt;Twittered snark&lt;/a&gt; aside, it's actually quite good — probably the best Gibson novel I've read, although it's mostly a do-over of &lt;em&gt;Pattern Recognition&lt;/em&gt;, and of course will never be as influential or noteworthy as &lt;em&gt;Neuromancer&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's definitely worth a read, I think, if only for the unsettling sensation of being unsure whether Gibson has figured out how to relate to the present or if it's just that the present has become more compatible with his style. It's also a book that, when all is revealed, seems well-suited to the particular moment of our 9/11 coping process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I say all of this by way of introducing the following passage (which is spoiler-free, I think, although others might disagree):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&amp;quot;I remember seeing proofs of a CIA interrogation manual, something we'd been sent unofficially, for comment,&amp;quot; the old man said. &amp;quot;The first chapter laid out the ways in which torture is fundamentally counterproductive to intelligence. The argument had nothing to do with ethics, everything to do with quality of product, with not squandering potential assets.&amp;quot; He removed his steel-rimmed glasses. &amp;quot;If the man who keeps returning to question you avoids behaving as if he were your enemy, you begin to lose your sense of who you are. Gradually, in the crisis of self that your captivity becomes, he guides you in your discovery of who you are becoming.&amp;quot;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&amp;quot;Did you interrogate people?&amp;quot; asked Garreth, the black Pelican case under his feet.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&amp;quot;It's an intimate process,&amp;quot; the old man said. &amp;quot;Entirely about intimacy.&amp;quot; He spread his hand, held it, as if above an invisible flame. &amp;quot;An ordinary cigarette lighter will cause a man to tell you anything, whatever he thinks you want to hear.&amp;quot; He lowered his hand. &amp;quot;And will prevent him ever trusting you again, even slightly. And will confirm him, in his sense of self, as few things will.&amp;quot; He tapped the folded paper. &amp;quot;When I first saw what they were doing, I knew that they'd turned the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SERE"&gt;SERE&lt;/a&gt; lessons inside out. That meant we were using techniques the Koreans had specifically developed in order to prepare prisoners for show trials.&amp;quot;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have no idea if the above is true, but it's certainly an interesting idea: that, when it comes to torture, black &amp;amp; white bellicosity is a meme capable of self-preservation, rather than just a manifestation of the torturer's ignorance and imcompetence. Failing to get results, forcing everyone to play their assigned parts with conviction — that's actually the &lt;em&gt;point&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics, pop culture"/></entry><entry><title>sorting out tricky gender equity problems in under four paragraphs</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/06/18/sorting-out-tricky-gender-equity-problems-in-under-four-paragraphs/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-06-18T01:23:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-06-18T01:23:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-06-18:/2008/06/18/sorting-out-tricky-gender-equity-problems-in-under-four-paragraphs/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://kaysteiger.blogspot.com/2008/06/name-changes.html"&gt;Marriage-induced name changes&lt;/a&gt;! Everyone's blogging about it, so allow me to briefly chime in with my brilliant, completely foolproof solution to the problem. First, everyone keeps their name when they get married. That seems kind of obvious. Second, male children take the father's last name and female children take the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://kaysteiger.blogspot.com/2008/06/name-changes.html"&gt;Marriage-induced name changes&lt;/a&gt;! Everyone's blogging about it, so allow me to briefly chime in with my brilliant, completely foolproof solution to the problem. First, everyone keeps their name when they get married. That seems kind of obvious. Second, male children take the father's last name and female children take the mother's last name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this way each parent gets to preserve their family name, giving it to offspring of the gender that said parent secretly believes to rule (at least relative to the inescapable truth that the other sex droolz). Yet nobody has to mess around with hyphens! And, as an added bonus, if the practice ever became popular we'd soon have distinctly female and distinctly male surnames, which I think would be sort of neat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More practically, of course, less-than-total adoption means that this would disadvantage female names. But that's all the more reason to embrace and fiercely espouse my crackpot idea immediately!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WHOOPS:&lt;/strong&gt; How heteronormative of me! Obviously this wouldn't work for same-sex couples. In that case, I suggest alternating kid-by-kid, with first dibs going to the winner of an American Gladiators-style obstacle course. Or, failing that, rock-paper-scissors (3 out of 5).&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics, pop culture"/></entry><entry><title>dances with the proportional syncopation of a spider</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2007/12/13/dances-with-the-proportional-syncopation-of-a-spider/" rel="alternate"/><published>2007-12-13T13:34:00-05:00</published><updated>2007-12-13T13:34:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2007-12-13:/2007/12/13/dances-with-the-proportional-syncopation-of-a-spider/</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/blogspot/bRuz/~3/199554026/2007_12_09_archive.html"&gt;Atrios has lost all credibility&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics, pop culture"/></entry><entry><title>all documentary reviews, all the time</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2007/06/22/all-documentary-reviews-all-the-time/" rel="alternate"/><published>2007-06-22T13:32:00-04:00</published><updated>2007-06-22T13:32:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2007-06-22:/2007/06/22/all-documentary-reviews-all-the-time/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have to be a little delicate about this: I just got back from a preview of an upcoming environmental documentary by a famous former &lt;em&gt;Growing Pains&lt;/em&gt; star/iceberg collision non-survivor. I got to skip out on work to do so — I guess there's a chance we may have some …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have to be a little delicate about this: I just got back from a preview of an upcoming environmental documentary by a famous former &lt;em&gt;Growing Pains&lt;/em&gt; star/iceberg collision non-survivor. I got to skip out on work to do so — I guess there's a chance we may have some sort of involvement with the project's promotion. I really hope we don't. Nevertheless, discretion is the watchword, lest googling reveal the privately-held opinion of this particular worker bee.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The screening occurred at the MPAA's DC headquarters, which I hadn't realized is mere blocks away. It was kind of awesome being in the belly of the beast. Amusingly enough, the theater boasted what I'm pretty sure was an anti-piracy device: a speaker-looking thing just above the screen with a matrix of of dull red points of light spread across its face. I'm pretty sure those were infrared LEDs, and although I suppose there's a slim chance that they were part of an assistive-audio system, it seems a lot more likely that they were providing non-visible illumination. A camera on the lookout for the bright glare of digital cameras' infra-opaque IR filters would be able to spot a phonecam or mini DV rig easily. So good job on protecting your intellectual property, MPAA! Now just work on getting the projection in focus...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for the movie — well, I'll start off by saying that I really liked &lt;em&gt;An Inconvenient Truth&lt;/em&gt;. It was convincing, affecting and cogently presented. It's clear that LD liked it, too — a lot. But his movie is much, much worse. In fact, if anything it seems likely to provide an excuse for people not to take &lt;em&gt;An Inconvenient Truth&lt;/em&gt; seriously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The film consists of a bunch of talking heads who have been sat down and apparently asked what their eco-grievances are. They ramble in varying directions. Comfortable-looking Californians with &amp;quot;executive director&amp;quot; in their titles tell us that other people need to work and consume and generally want less. Neo-hippies tell us that the solutions to our ecological problems really come down to love, man (this was the first point at which the audience laughed). Somber crackpots explain that the real tragedy won't be the necessary elimination of billions from the earth's population, but rather the non-human species we take with us. Self-assured sophists educate us about how defense spending is an insignificant portion of America's GDP and how no study has ever shown any living system not to be in decline. In between all of this, genuine experts offer genuinely interesting thoughts, which are edited together into incoherence: air pollution's effect on childhood asthma prefaces concern about overfishing; deforestation segues into using fungi for heavy metal mitigation. Accompanying it all: a parade of stock footage, much of it at best tangentially related to the subject currently being discussed (we do get a quick, grainy shot of LD in a sweatlodge, though, which is pretty hilarious).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than anything, the problem is the writing. LD can't write effective rhetoric for his monologues — he's like Al Gore, except &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; boring. And the film is horribly disorganized. It's nothing that a freshman writing seminar or two couldn't fix (although it might require a particularly merciless TA). But as it currently stands, watching the film is like listening to an ecologically-focused 90-minute monologue by A.J. Soprano circa the end of season six.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics, pop culture"/></entry><entry><title>Sicko</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2007/06/19/sicko/" rel="alternate"/><published>2007-06-19T10:17:00-04:00</published><updated>2007-06-19T10:17:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2007-06-19:/2007/06/19/sicko/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ezraklein.typepad.com"&gt;Ezra&lt;/a&gt; used his mastery of the healthcare-related arts to wrangle Emily &amp;amp; me a pair of tickets to Michael Moore's new movie, &lt;em&gt;Sicko&lt;/em&gt;. Ezra's going to be seeing it later in the week, I believe, but his his shadow already loomed over the theater: I'm pretty sure I heard someone in …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ezraklein.typepad.com"&gt;Ezra&lt;/a&gt; used his mastery of the healthcare-related arts to wrangle Emily &amp;amp; me a pair of tickets to Michael Moore's new movie, &lt;em&gt;Sicko&lt;/em&gt;. Ezra's going to be seeing it later in the week, I believe, but his his shadow already loomed over the theater: I'm pretty sure I heard someone in the row behind us say his name (although I may have just misheard him asking, &amp;quot;Does this seat recline?&amp;quot;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The movie was pretty good, but having read enough blogospheric health care wonkery to make me officious-while-not-all-that-well-informed, I also couldn't resist picking out aspects of the film's argument that seemed unsatisfying. Among them: it was hard to know what to make of the anecdotes about care being denied; the trip to Cuba seemed likely to be so staged as to be meaningless; there were no real distinctions made between the different idyllic-seeming foreign healthcare systems; discussions of price were limited to foreign stuff being really cheap and our stuff being really expensive; and despite flirtations with the idea, the movie never really talked about preventive care's effect on cost. Overall, it was a little hard to feel confident about drawing any conclusion other than &amp;quot;America should probably be embarrassed&amp;quot;. Maybe Ezra's &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.prospect.org/cs/articles?articleId=12683"&gt;Health of Nations&lt;/a&gt; article left me expecting too much from a movie that bothered to travel to Canada, the UK and France. Instead of highlighting the variations between these countries' systems, we just got a lot of repetition about how nice free health care is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the movie was still effective, and very entertaining — Michael Moore's a funny guy, and he knows how to pluck a heartstring. I think most people will leave the theater angry about our healthcare system and envious of the French, and that's probably about as much as one can reasonably expect. I'll be curious to hear what &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dcist.com/staff.php#dcist_ian"&gt;Ian&lt;/a&gt; (who was also in attendance) and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ezraklein.typepad.com"&gt;Ezra&lt;/a&gt; think.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics, pop culture"/></entry></feed>