<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Tom Lee - politics, science</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"/><link href="/feeds/politics-science.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>/</id><updated>2008-11-19T11:20:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>charts &amp; graphs</title><link href="/2008/11/19/charts-graphs/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-11-19T11:20:00-05:00</published><updated>2008-11-19T11:20:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2008-11-19:/2008/11/19/charts-graphs/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;son1 has written &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://bayes.wordpress.com/2008/11/18/color-me-bad/"&gt;a post&lt;/a&gt; that continues the discussion I began around &lt;a class="reference external" href="/2008/11/08/coloring-your-opinion/"&gt;colors and data visualization&lt;/a&gt;, and I'm jealous of it for two reasons. First, I can't believe I didn't think of and claim that post title for myself, because it's perfect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, he does a much better job of …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;son1 has written &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://bayes.wordpress.com/2008/11/18/color-me-bad/"&gt;a post&lt;/a&gt; that continues the discussion I began around &lt;a class="reference external" href="/2008/11/08/coloring-your-opinion/"&gt;colors and data visualization&lt;/a&gt;, and I'm jealous of it for two reasons. First, I can't believe I didn't think of and claim that post title for myself, because it's perfect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, he does a much better job of getting to the heart of what I was trying to express: that a surprisingly large amount of data visualizations are both correct and question-begging. The choices made by the creator will inevitably influence which conclusions are drawn. That isn't to malign the idea of graphs and charts and maps — at their best they are arguments that contain all component data, and whose accuracy can be easily checked. But they're still arguments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps all this stuff has been said before and better by Tufte, but those books are expensive, dammit.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics, science"/></entry><entry><title>coloring your opinion</title><link href="/2008/11/08/coloring-your-opinion/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-11-08T14:30:00-05:00</published><updated>2008-11-08T14:30:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2008-11-08:/2008/11/08/coloring-your-opinion/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Well, I guess it's time for that &amp;quot;purple America&amp;quot; map from Robert Vanderbei to start making the rounds again. Yglesias has the 2008 edition &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/matthewyglesias/~3/446509415/the_more_things_change.php"&gt;posted over at his site&lt;/a&gt;. The basic idea here is that for all the talk of red and blue America, the political differences between regions are …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Well, I guess it's time for that &amp;quot;purple America&amp;quot; map from Robert Vanderbei to start making the rounds again. Yglesias has the 2008 edition &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/matthewyglesias/~3/446509415/the_more_things_change.php"&gt;posted over at his site&lt;/a&gt;. The basic idea here is that for all the talk of red and blue America, the political differences between regions are actually quite small, and we're really a united nation with a vigorous political discourse, tra la la la. Then we join hands and sing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, you know, fine. There's an element of truth to this, and it's certainly a nice thought. But also true: visualizing information by using a linear red/blue scale is about the worst way possible to make data legible to the human eye. First: our vision is logarithmic. When a photographer drags out his &amp;quot;50% gray&amp;quot; card for measuring lighting, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://photo.net/bboard/q-and-a-fetch-msg?msg_id=000F55"&gt;it's actually 18% gray&lt;/a&gt;. Judging by the triangular key in the corner of Vanderbei's image, he's just taking the percentage of vote totals and translating it flatly to 8 bit color — a 100% Republican district gets an RGB 24-bit value of (255,0,0).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The colors themselves are also a problem. As I'm sure you all remember keenly from &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.zunta.org/blog/archives/2006/04/07/graphic_violenc/"&gt;this post I wrote in 2006&lt;/a&gt;, perceptual image codecs spend more bits on brightness than on color because the color-sensing cones in your eyes have a much lousier dynamic range than the light-sensing rods. We're worse at distinguishing between levels of color than between levels of brightness. And since the percentage of the vote in any given spot on the map should always sum to 100, with negligible green (third party) contributions, the brightness will be relatively uniform (although admittedly not quite due to the perceptual differences between colors — monitor calibration and colorspace begin to enter the picture at this point, and things get just as hideously complex as you might imagine).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(I'll add, somewhat tentatively, that my recollection from college is that &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.glenbrook.k12.il.us/gbssci/Phys/Class/light/u12l2b.html"&gt;the green cone is the most sensitive of the three types in your retina&lt;/a&gt;, making red/blue coding about the least distinguishable color continuum possible. The situation's complicated by your rods' preferential sensitivity to blue wavelengths, though, and the ratio of work done by rods and cones varies with ambient brightness. So I'll resist the temptation to make strong claims on this score.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what does this all mean? Depending on how you look at it, not much. It's not as if Vanderbei has done anything &lt;em&gt;wrong&lt;/em&gt;. It's just that the choices he made will tend to produce a map that, at a glance, implies homogeneity. If, on the other hand, we pull out the red channel, desaturate the blue channel and maximize the contrast of the resulting image (in effect normalizing the values to the full possible dynamic range), we get something very different-looking — but still perfectly accurate, and still non-logarithmic (with the caveat that it gives third-party votes to the Dems). Click the image for a full-sized, easier-to-see version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="/static/2008/11/08/20081108_vanderbei_big-20081108-142429.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image1" class="center" src="/static/2008/11/08/20081108_vanderbei_small-20081108-142538.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yglesias's point that this isn't a huge change between cycles still stands, of course, but the shifts are considerably easier to see this way (and easier still on that &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://yglesias.thinkprogress.org/archives/2008/11/the_mccain_belt.php"&gt;cool New York Times map&lt;/a&gt; that ran on their front page after the election).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's also easy to see that there really &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; very Republican and very Democratic sections of the country. I don't want to overstate my case — obviously this conclusion can be drawn from the color map, too. Still, using a whole bunch of linearly-defined purple pixels is a clever way to latch onto a media cliche, but not necessarily the best way to visualize information. Things are more black and white than they may seem, and certainly less purple.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics, science"/></entry><entry><title>ok, weird</title><link href="/2008/10/25/ok-weird/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-10-25T11:25:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-10-25T11:25:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2008-10-25:/2008/10/25/ok-weird/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I apologize; I'm totally fascinated by this Ashley Todd business. I can't stop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latest development appears to be her claim that she was in some sort of psychogenic fugue state when she scratched the B in her face:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;object width="425" height="344"&gt;&lt;embed src="http://www.youtube.com/v/Li2u10aOWAA&amp;amp;color1=0xb1b1b1&amp;amp;color2=0xcfcfcf&amp;amp;fs=1" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" allowfullscreen="true" width="425" height="344"&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately I am unable to speculate as to the veracity of …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I apologize; I'm totally fascinated by this Ashley Todd business. I can't stop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latest development appears to be her claim that she was in some sort of psychogenic fugue state when she scratched the B in her face:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;object width="425" height="344"&gt;&lt;embed src="http://www.youtube.com/v/Li2u10aOWAA&amp;amp;color1=0xb1b1b1&amp;amp;color2=0xcfcfcf&amp;amp;fs=1" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" allowfullscreen="true" width="425" height="344"&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately I am unable to speculate as to the veracity of such a claim; the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.psychiatryonline.com/content.aspx?aID=9744"&gt;DSM-IV doesn't say anything one way or the other&lt;/a&gt; about sufferers' tendency to send out Twitters containing pre-fugue exposition.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics, science"/></entry><entry><title>today in BLOGS</title><link href="/2008/07/14/today-in-blogs/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-07-14T11:15:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-07-14T11:15:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2008-07-14:/2008/07/14/today-in-blogs/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I guess the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.prospect.org/csnc/blogs/ezraklein_archive?month=07&amp;amp;year=2008&amp;amp;base_name=meet_the_meats"&gt;apparently&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://matthewyglesias.theatlantic.com/archives/2008/07/the_case_for_pork.php"&gt;counterintuitive&lt;/a&gt; idea that pork is among the most efficient meats to produce doesn't strike me as all that strange. Obviously larger animals take more time to reach full size, wasting more energy on metabolic upkeep. But equally obviously there's a certain amount of overhead associated with …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I guess the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.prospect.org/csnc/blogs/ezraklein_archive?month=07&amp;amp;year=2008&amp;amp;base_name=meet_the_meats"&gt;apparently&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://matthewyglesias.theatlantic.com/archives/2008/07/the_case_for_pork.php"&gt;counterintuitive&lt;/a&gt; idea that pork is among the most efficient meats to produce doesn't strike me as all that strange. Obviously larger animals take more time to reach full size, wasting more energy on metabolic upkeep. But equally obviously there's a certain amount of overhead associated with being a mammal that may not scale constantly with the total amount of food that the animal provides. Consider the relationship between volume and surface area — same idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, the pig is generally considered the smartest animal in the barnyard. So if you're looking for a reason to be uneasy about pork consumption, there you go: if you suspect that sentience works on a sliding scale, and if you believe that the moral outrageousness of a given act of violence against an animal is weighted by the animal's level of consciousness, then your pig-slaughter is far more ethically objectionable than ordering a serving of chicken tenders. This strikes me as a much better source of liberal guilt than the difference in carbon footprint between types of meat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other blog news: the New Yorker has made a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.americablog.com/2008/07/new-yorker-cover-shows-oval-office-with.html"&gt;cartoon&lt;/a&gt; and it's not funny. People are... surprised? Anyway, Ezra has the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.prospect.org/csnc/blogs/ezraklein_archive?month=07&amp;amp;year=2008&amp;amp;base_name=that_new_yorker_cover"&gt;smart take&lt;/a&gt;. For now I think we'll just have to cross our fingers that the New Yorker's much-vaunted influence upon the middle-American swing voter zeitgeist has been overstated.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="politics, science"/></entry></feed>