<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Tom Lee - pop culture</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/feeds/pop-culture.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>https://tomlee.wtf/</id><updated>2009-04-14T15:19:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>talk like a pirate day is insufferable, but for entirely different reasons</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2009/04/14/talk-like-a-pirate-day-is-insufferable-but-for-entirely-different-reasons/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-04-14T15:19:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-04-14T15:19:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2009-04-14:/2009/04/14/talk-like-a-pirate-day-is-insufferable-but-for-entirely-different-reasons/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Rob Pegoraro, the Post's technology columnist, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://voices.washingtonpost.com/fasterforward/2009/04/who_are_you_calling_a_software.html"&gt;is looking for alternative names for software theft&lt;/a&gt; that aren't associated with, ahem, maritime terrorism:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;The NYT's always-interesting Freakonomics blog &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://freakonomics.blogs.nytimes.com/2009/04/13/is-it-time-to-rename-digital-piracy/"&gt;raised that question&lt;/a&gt; yesterday. Stephen J. Dubner wrote that &amp;quot;as real-life pirate attacks have gained in intensity, violence, and geopolitical meaning, talking about digital …&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Rob Pegoraro, the Post's technology columnist, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://voices.washingtonpost.com/fasterforward/2009/04/who_are_you_calling_a_software.html"&gt;is looking for alternative names for software theft&lt;/a&gt; that aren't associated with, ahem, maritime terrorism:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;The NYT's always-interesting Freakonomics blog &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://freakonomics.blogs.nytimes.com/2009/04/13/is-it-time-to-rename-digital-piracy/"&gt;raised that question&lt;/a&gt; yesterday. Stephen J. Dubner wrote that &amp;quot;as real-life pirate attacks have gained in intensity, violence, and geopolitical meaning, talking about digital thieves as pirates has come to seem clever to a fault, and inaccurate too.&amp;quot;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;The Business Software Alliance, a trade group devoted to stopping people from using commercial software without paying for it first, does not agree. Also yesterday, the CNet tech-news site reported that a BSA publicist sent an e-mail explicitly comparing thugs hijacking supertankers to software thieves: &amp;quot;Piracy takes many forms, some more violent than others.&amp;quot;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;(Writer Gordon Haff called that e-mail &amp;quot;one of the most tone-deaf and cynically opportunistic PR pitches I've seen for quite some time.&amp;quot;)&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;[...]&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Blogger John Gruber suggests the term &amp;quot;bootlegging,&amp;quot; but I'm not sure about that noun either. To me (a one-time concert reviewer for the Post), it evokes homemade recordings from concerts, an activity that demands individual initiative and, when done right, creativity. Installing a copy of a program on two computers doesn't require much of those qualities.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&amp;quot;Software theft&amp;quot; itself suffers the problem that theft, by definition, involves the victims losing the stolen property [...] That doesn't happen with digital media, where somebody installing a not-paid-for copy of Office doesn't stop your copy, mine or Steve Ballmer's from working. Rather, the key concept here is that somebody has short-circuited a normal business transaction through deceit or trickery. And for that, the most apt definition appears to be &amp;quot;fraud&amp;quot;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fraud is not a good term for this, as the software consumer is not misrepresenting his or herself, and in fact generally has no interaction at all with the software vendor. &amp;quot;Fraud&amp;quot; implies that the victimized party has been manipulated into surrendering something of value under false pretenses. That doesn't really apply to these cases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gruber's suggestion of &amp;quot;bootleggers&amp;quot; is better than &amp;quot;fraud&amp;quot;, but it's unfortunately normative in that most people now consider Prohibition (which is what most people think of when they hear &amp;quot;bootlegging&amp;quot;) to have been an unreasonable imposition by the government — as a result, in this case the terminology would imply that software appropriation is legitimate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A better description would be &amp;quot;freeloaders&amp;quot;, as users of unlicensed proprietary software are extracting value from a system without supporting it themselves. It also has a pun in it, since they're &amp;quot;loading&amp;quot; the software on their machines! Obviously this should count as a major strike against it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though I couldn't resist leaving in an irrelevant quote beating up on them, in the end I have to side with the BSA. Not because &amp;quot;piracy&amp;quot; is a great term for software theft — it's manipulative and inaccurate — but because &lt;em&gt;that's what we have been and will continue to call it&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't mean to just rail against the evolution of language in a reflexive, let's-bitch-about-political-correctness sort of way. But the fact that some people are suddenly feeling guilty for previously having a whimsical attitude toward all things piratical strikes me as pretty silly. Surprise: there are a lot of idioms with horrific literal meanings that we regularly deploy lightheartedly — &amp;quot;highway robbery&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;scared to death&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;thrown under the bus&amp;quot; — these would all be unpleasant things to experience! Tragedy + time = comedy and all that. Enjoying the amusing caricature of piracy that we've developed over the last several decades is not the same thing as dismissing the horrors of real-life piracy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now: who wants to play some Halo 3 tonight? I promise to feel at least little bad when I use the sniper rifle.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="pop culture"/></entry><entry><title>fmylife</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2009/04/07/fmylife/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-04-07T16:42:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-04-07T16:42:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2009-04-07:/2009/04/07/fmylife/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Becks is right: this &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.unfogged.com/archives/week_2009_04_05.html#009718"&gt;FML phenomenon is intolerable&lt;/a&gt;. I don't really agree with her complaint about its negativity being the problem, though. The problem is that it isn't negative &lt;em&gt;enough&lt;/em&gt;. The people participating in this meme are doing it wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The phrase &amp;quot;fuck my life&amp;quot; is a setup for comedy …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Becks is right: this &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.unfogged.com/archives/week_2009_04_05.html#009718"&gt;FML phenomenon is intolerable&lt;/a&gt;. I don't really agree with her complaint about its negativity being the problem, though. The problem is that it isn't negative &lt;em&gt;enough&lt;/em&gt;. The people participating in this meme are doing it wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The phrase &amp;quot;fuck my life&amp;quot; is a setup for comedy about hopelessness, but it's being adopted by people who don't understand either of those things. Most of the entries on &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.fmylife.com"&gt;FML&lt;/a&gt; are about minor inconveniences or embarrassments. #whoops! would be a more apt hashtag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are occasional outliers that begin to get at the point of the exercise (&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.fmylife.com/work/850361"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; is on the right track, though the execution is clunky). But it's clear that most of the entries are from fresh-faced twenty year-olds who rarely, if ever, find themselves using the phrase &amp;quot;alone in an uncaring universe&amp;quot;. For these jokes to work their implications need to stretch further into the future than next week. Otherwise the natural response is, &amp;quot;That's too bad, but I'm sure things will pick up soon.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE:&lt;/strong&gt; I was remiss in not linking to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.en-dash.com/blog"&gt;Jake&lt;/a&gt;'s &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dumbfml.tumblr.com/"&gt;effort to highlight the worst FMLs&lt;/a&gt;. And it reminds me to mention my other objection to this whole business: how transparently fake most of the entries are. Really, some slight effort toward plausibility is not too much to ask.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="pop culture"/></entry><entry><title>like the commenter said: fonally!</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2009/04/07/like-the-commenter-said-fonally/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-04-07T11:36:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-04-07T11:36:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2009-04-07:/2009/04/07/like-the-commenter-said-fonally/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last week &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.juliansanchez.com/2009/04/02/sic-transit-gloria-conde/"&gt;Julian got laid off&lt;/a&gt;, part of a bloodbath at Ars that resulted from the Conde Nast powers-that-be deciding that having excellent, industry-leading online properties didn't fit with their long-term business strategy of making it to retirement without being bothered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was pretty disappointing to see, both as a …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last week &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.juliansanchez.com/2009/04/02/sic-transit-gloria-conde/"&gt;Julian got laid off&lt;/a&gt;, part of a bloodbath at Ars that resulted from the Conde Nast powers-that-be deciding that having excellent, industry-leading online properties didn't fit with their long-term business strategy of making it to retirement without being bothered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was pretty disappointing to see, both as a friend and as someone who enjoys reading quality journalism about tech policy. However! Just because he's no longer being paid to cover, say, government wiretapping, doesn't mean that he isn't &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.juliansanchez.com/2009/04/07/solution-to-the-fringe-glyph-cipher/"&gt;making contributions to our cultural discourse&lt;/a&gt;. I can only assume this is what inspired Yglesias to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://yglesias.thinkprogress.org/archives/2009/04/social_production_and_demographic_changes.php"&gt;write this&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Lest anyone think I'm teasing Julian, let me remind you that I'm the same guy who once &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.zunta.org/blog/archives/2006/05/11/lost_the_plot/"&gt;meticulously converted the Dharma Initiative logo into a vector graphics format&lt;/a&gt; — I'm not a fan of &lt;em&gt;Fringe&lt;/em&gt;, but being the first to crack its code is pretty cool.)&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="pop culture"/></entry><entry><title>Live! Nude! Post-humans!</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2009/03/07/live-nude-post-humans/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-03-07T11:23:00-05:00</published><updated>2009-03-07T11:23:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2009-03-07:/2009/03/07/live-nude-post-humans/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I haven't seen &lt;em&gt;Watchmen&lt;/em&gt; yet — Emily and I were traveling last night, bound for a quick vacation in Texas. Just about the time everyone else was suffering through &amp;quot;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LJRthpxDM10"&gt;Citizen Solder&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot; I was tucking into an enormous plate of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.chuys.com/location.html"&gt;delicious blue corn tortillas&lt;/a&gt;. So I say this based on the comic …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I haven't seen &lt;em&gt;Watchmen&lt;/em&gt; yet — Emily and I were traveling last night, bound for a quick vacation in Texas. Just about the time everyone else was suffering through &amp;quot;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LJRthpxDM10"&gt;Citizen Solder&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot; I was tucking into an enormous plate of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.chuys.com/location.html"&gt;delicious blue corn tortillas&lt;/a&gt;. So I say this based on the comic, not the film.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But of course &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.prospect.org/csnc/blogs/tapped_archive?month=03&amp;amp;year=2009&amp;amp;base_name=in_defense_of_the_penis"&gt;Phoebe's right&lt;/a&gt; that there's a double standard when it comes to female and male nudity in films, and our discomfort at either is a bit silly. &lt;em&gt;Watchmen&lt;/em&gt; seems like an odd time to make that case, though, because here the nudity is used precisely &lt;strong&gt;because&lt;/strong&gt; we're uncomfortable with it. Dr. Manhattan wanders around naked, and that seems odd to us. But it doesn't seem odd to him because he's a superbeing that's almost completely alienated from humanity. To him a body is a construct, and it's impossible to understand the social conventions surrounding it or anything else. If the audience was similarly blasé about Dr. M striding about in his deathday suit there wouldn't be any point to showing him doing so.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="pop culture"/></entry><entry><title>treating stupidity with the seriousness it deserves</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/12/22/treating-stupidity-with-the-seriousness-it-deserves/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-12-22T12:37:00-05:00</published><updated>2008-12-22T12:37:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-12-22:/2008/12/22/treating-stupidity-with-the-seriousness-it-deserves/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/the_wrestler"&gt;The Onion AV Club&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;em&gt;The Wrestler&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WWE devotees now have their own Passion Of The Christ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To which I say: it's about time. Hell, make it in Aramaic for all I care. I'll just be glad to see the industry exposed to a larger audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My throwaway holiday entertainment …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.avclub.com/content/cinema/the_wrestler"&gt;The Onion AV Club&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;em&gt;The Wrestler&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;WWE devotees now have their own Passion Of The Christ&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To which I say: it's about time. Hell, make it in Aramaic for all I care. I'll just be glad to see the industry exposed to a larger audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My throwaway holiday entertainment will be &lt;em&gt;The Spirit&lt;/em&gt;, but there is no movie that I'm more excited about than Darren Aronofsky's take on those who live their lives in and around the squared circle. The combination of idiotic childhood nostalgia and its underpinning layers of genuine, lately-discovered pathos is incredibly heady. Go ahead, look me in the eye and try to tell me that you wouldn't want to read a novel about Optimus Prime's painful divorce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At any rate, here's some related media to tide you over:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.moviesonline.ca/movienews_16103.html"&gt;interview with Aronofsky&lt;/a&gt;, in which his smark credentials are thoroughly proven&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.iht.com/articles/2008/12/04/arts/fake.php"&gt;Another Q&amp;amp;A, this time with writer Robert Siegel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.netflix.com/Movie/Beyond_the_Mat_Special_Edition/70000781"&gt;Beyond the Mat&lt;/a&gt;, a great documentary about the wrestling industry. You know that one scene with Stephen Drozd from &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.amazon.com/Flaming-Lips-Fearless-Freaks/dp/B0007NN6J2/ref=pd_bbs_sr_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;s=music&amp;amp;qid=1229983204&amp;amp;sr=8-1"&gt;the Flaming Lips movie&lt;/a&gt;? Well, picture the same thing, but with Jake &amp;quot;The Snake&amp;quot; Roberts and a thousand times more heartbreak.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content><category term="pop culture"/></entry><entry><title>you will be surprised to hear that I enjoy science fiction action movies</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/11/25/you-will-be-surprised-to-hear-that-i-enjoy-science-fiction-action-movies/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-11-25T11:26:00-05:00</published><updated>2008-11-25T11:26:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-11-25:/2008/11/25/you-will-be-surprised-to-hear-that-i-enjoy-science-fiction-action-movies/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I rewatched &lt;em&gt;Aliens&lt;/em&gt; over the weekend, and man: that's a pretty good movie!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do have one other thought to share, though. And it's this: you hear a lot about how influential the production design in &lt;em&gt;Blade Runner&lt;/em&gt; was, and that certainly seems true. But within the context of the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I rewatched &lt;em&gt;Aliens&lt;/em&gt; over the weekend, and man: that's a pretty good movie!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do have one other thought to share, though. And it's this: you hear a lot about how influential the production design in &lt;em&gt;Blade Runner&lt;/em&gt; was, and that certainly seems true. But within the context of the &lt;em&gt;Alien&lt;/em&gt; franchise, most of the attention is paid to H. R. Giger's creature designs. That seems to me to significantly underestimate the influence that the rest of the film's designs have had. In particular its portrayal of the marines and their equipment has been embraced/stolen by virtually every science fiction videogame franchise since. Some of this is just pragmatic — it's easy to make big, boxy vehicles; having an LED ammo counter on a weapon avoids the need for an extra HUD element — but to a large extent these ideas have been taken up because they're just &lt;em&gt;really good designs&lt;/em&gt;. At this point they've been reused so often that they more or less form the baseline for any depiction of futuristic infantry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now of course both &lt;em&gt;BR&lt;/em&gt; and the first &lt;em&gt;Alien&lt;/em&gt; movie were directed by Ridley Scott, so it makes no sense to propose an under/overrated auteur dynamic. &lt;em&gt;Aliens&lt;/em&gt; was helmed by James Cameron, and as a sequel it's necessarily more of an evolution of the preceding movie's aesthetic (which itself was less original than &lt;em&gt;BR&lt;/em&gt;) than an original universe. But I'd argue that while &lt;em&gt;BR&lt;/em&gt; had an immediate impact on the people making our popular culture, &lt;em&gt;Aliens&lt;/em&gt; was quietly internalized by a generation of future game designers who have only recently begun making their presence known as both they, and their chosen medium, have come of age.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="pop culture"/></entry><entry><title>Smuggling Varmints Unethically</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/11/19/smuggling-varmints-unethically/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-11-19T20:55:00-05:00</published><updated>2008-11-19T20:55:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-11-19:/2008/11/19/smuggling-varmints-unethically/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I didn't see &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://pygmalioninablanket.blogspot.com/2007/11/thanksgiving-came-early-to-our-house.html"&gt;this episode&lt;/a&gt; so I can't say for sure, but the Law &amp;amp; Order: SVU that I just watched with Charles seems like a strong contender for greatest of all time. That's not saying much, of course, since Law &amp;amp; Order is a terrible, terrible franchise. Still, check out the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I didn't see &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://pygmalioninablanket.blogspot.com/2007/11/thanksgiving-came-early-to-our-house.html"&gt;this episode&lt;/a&gt; so I can't say for sure, but the Law &amp;amp; Order: SVU that I just watched with Charles seems like a strong contender for greatest of all time. That's not saying much, of course, since Law &amp;amp; Order is a terrible, terrible franchise. Still, check out the plot summary as I related it to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://movering.com"&gt;Emily&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;There was a girl found shot but then she wasn't but it turned out to be her twin, except then also she had tiger bites on her, so of course they figured it was the tiger of this rap star (played by the guy from Outkast), but DNA proved it wasn't, so then Big Boi says the girl was part of an exotic animal smuggling ring and takes Stabler to them posing as a customs official who wants to become corrupt, and he steals some hair and it was THAT TIGER, but then Big Boi gets eaten by hyenas (which we know because a CSI said &amp;quot;check out that hyena vomit&amp;quot; and his chain was in it) so then Stabler goes back to the smugglers and tries to become better friends and sees a lady with a weird vest and the bad guys say &amp;quot;everyone is always picturing her naked, they don't stop to think about whether she's smuggling turtle eggs&amp;quot;, which proves how ingenious (aka evil) they are.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;SO the bad guys keep feeling out Stabler as a fake customs agent and they want him to help smuggle a VERY RARE GIBBON, and he does but they get suspicious and shoot him, but he's okay and they set up a sting at the airport where the gibbon is being brought into the country via a basketball, and they catch the bad guys in the act of selling it to an asian guy and the bad guys say &amp;quot;gentleman, there are now only SIXTEEN of these gibbons left in the wild, hahaha.&amp;quot;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;But then the cops arrive and everyone runs over rooftops and almost falls down, except it turns out one of the two bad guys was an undercover cop all along and the other smuggler is JUST THE TIP OF THE ANIMAL SMUGGLING ICEBERG!&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;whew&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;so that's how it ended&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, the MPAA may hunt you down (like so many gibbons) if you &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://isohunt.com/torrent_details/53395617/svu?tab=summary"&gt;illegally download the episode&lt;/a&gt;. But are you really prepared to depend on NBC's rerun-scheduling caprice when it comes to something so obviously awesome?&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="pop culture"/></entry><entry><title>the discerning aesthete's guide to media designed for teenage boys</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/11/19/the-discerning-aesthetes-guide-to-media-designed-for-teenage-boys/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-11-19T12:19:00-05:00</published><updated>2008-11-19T12:19:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-11-19:/2008/11/19/the-discerning-aesthetes-guide-to-media-designed-for-teenage-boys/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The new Bond movie: I liked it! The only film in the series that it seems worthwhile to compare it to is &lt;em&gt;Casino Royale&lt;/em&gt;, and on that score it's a mixed bag. On the one hand, &lt;em&gt;Quantum of Solace&lt;/em&gt;'s best parts are not as good as those of &lt;em&gt;Casino …&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The new Bond movie: I liked it! The only film in the series that it seems worthwhile to compare it to is &lt;em&gt;Casino Royale&lt;/em&gt;, and on that score it's a mixed bag. On the one hand, &lt;em&gt;Quantum of Solace&lt;/em&gt;'s best parts are not as good as those of &lt;em&gt;Casino Royale&lt;/em&gt;, if only because they don't involve awesome footchases built around parkour. On the other hand, &lt;em&gt;QoS&lt;/em&gt;'s worst parts manage to avoid the inclusion of high-stakes poker tournaments run by the villain, by which point in the movie it has been established that the local police force is in Bond's pocket so why don't they just arrest this guy anyway?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seriously: a poker tournament?! I can only assume that the people responsible for that decision will one day look back upon it and be as deeply ashamed as if they had written a getaway chase set on razor scooters, or a part for a villainous master-blogger, or an Aston Martin with an advanced camouflage system based on hypercolor t-shirt technology. Topicality is not the Bond series' strong suit. Also, as evil character tics go, having an inhaler is pretty lame — particularly if it isn't used to kill anybody.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new movie avoided those sorts of problems, instead opting for the more commonly accepted practice of just having lots of enormous plot holes. Why are the villains eschewing petrotyranny in favor of a plot to extract a somewhat higher profit margin on municipal water in Bolivia (the dastards!)? Why was that exploding hotel built out of hydrogen, again?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But all this is well within acceptable action movie tolerances, and Daniel Craig is pretty awesome. Also: I liked the title, dammit! I must reluctantly conclude that those who disagree are just mean.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class="docutils" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gears of War 2 has been acquired, partly on the strength of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.newyorker.com/reporting/2008/11/03/081103fa_fact_bissell?currentPage=all"&gt;this New Yorker profile of its lead designer&lt;/a&gt;, sent to me by my coworker Brian (be sure to also check out &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.magicalwasteland.com/2008/10/in_any_guise_a_poor_ambassador.htm"&gt;this comments-section exchange&lt;/a&gt; between the author and a critic, which &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://doombot.com/"&gt;Jason&lt;/a&gt; pointed out to me). It's shaping up to be the biggest Xbox release of the holiday season. If you'd like to come find me on XBL, my gamertag is Club Loser. Let me assure you: I'm quite bad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realize it's curmudgeonly of me, but I can't help but be dismayed by this generation's videogame franchises. Back in my day (&lt;em&gt;*stretches, pats belly*&lt;/em&gt;) our shooters stuck to paper-thin premises that were patently ludicrous and profoundly derivative, but which provided plenty of room for awesome non-sequiturs. There's, uh, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Doom_(video_game)"&gt;a portal to hell on Mars&lt;/a&gt;? And things are coming through it? Sure, let's go with that — &lt;em&gt;Aliens&lt;/em&gt; was pretty awesome, right? Or hey, maybe there's an &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Quake_3"&gt;intergalactic&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unreal_tournament"&gt;tournament&lt;/a&gt; where kidnapped fighters from all over the galaxy are brought and forced to fight for some reason? It was cool when it happened to Bruce Lee, and he didn't even have a rocket launcher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These days, things are a bit more homogenous and overengineered. The two biggest shooter franchises for Xbox are &lt;em&gt;Halo&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Gears of War&lt;/em&gt;. In one of them, superhumans on a distant planet are locked in a pitched battle against vaguely reptilian alien hordes driven by a crazed prophetic religion. In the other, superhumans on a distant planet are locked in a pitched battle against vaguely insectoid alien hordes who seem to feel it's not polite to discuss religion in a social or battlefield setting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this is fine. The resulting &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://news.teamxbox.com/xbox/15374/Gears-of-War-Novel-Update-Movie-Script-Confirmed/"&gt;movies and novelizations&lt;/a&gt; are irritating in principle, but also fine so long as you avoid watching or reading them — people like making money, after all. What's very, very irritating, though, is the compulsory delusion among the fanboy set which maintains that the settings and plots for these games are anything other than incredibly awful, derivative, sub-fanfic-level dreck, utterly unworthy of respect or serious consideration. Instead I end up reading gaming press pieces which assume that I know or care what the Pillar of Autumn is, or which include quotes from the games' creators that say things like &amp;quot;we think there's a lot more to explore in the Halo universe&amp;quot;. Sure! Of course! Who wouldn't want to see what wonders await us in a fictional world that includes ideas as original as lasers and machineguns and jeeps (oh, the jeeps!). Also there's a bunch of stuff stolen from &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ringworld"&gt;Larry Niven&lt;/a&gt;, but with fewer words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suppose I should just avoid those articles. But I need to know about the comparative deadliness of the next rocket launcher iteration! Or which add-on maps I'm going to be forced to buy! Or the next initiative that will try (and fail) to make teenagers on Xbox Live a bit less racist and homophobic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of this actually diminishes my excitement at the prospect of brutalizing strangers' avatars from the comfort of my home. There's skill involved, the gameplay is well-tuned, and it's thrilling to win. I just wish there were fewer pretentious narrative trappings surrounding the experience — or, if we really can't pare things down to a minimal core of deadliness, that the narrative filigrees could be made with a sense of good humor rather than just the idiot earnestness of the hack-who-doesn't-know-it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class="docutils" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also: to put all this into perspective, I spent yesterday playing laser tag.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="pop culture"/></entry><entry><title>NBC forced me to have these thoughts</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/08/20/nbc-forced-me-to-have-these-thoughts/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-08-20T21:16:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-08-20T21:16:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-08-20:/2008/08/20/nbc-forced-me-to-have-these-thoughts/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Curse them and their Olympic advertising:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does Visa really think this &amp;quot;only card accepted at the Olympics&amp;quot; business is a good idea? How many people hear that boast and think &amp;quot;Oh shit! Good thing I went with Visa — I'd hate to have to visit an ATM four years from now …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Curse them and their Olympic advertising:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Does Visa really think this &amp;quot;only card accepted at the Olympics&amp;quot; business is a good idea? How many people hear that boast and think &amp;quot;Oh shit! Good thing I went with Visa — I'd hate to have to visit an ATM four years from now, maybe.&amp;quot; My guess: fewer than the number that realize that Visa has taken their money and spent it on a) making other companies' customers' lives slightly less convenient and b) getting Morgan Freeman to relay that accomplishment to us.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kath_%26_Kim_(U.S._TV_series)"&gt;Kath and Kim&lt;/a&gt;. Maybe you'll be funny! You've got Selma Blair on your cast, and if someone's good enough for Hellboy she's good enough for me. But it's pathetically clear that you really, really want us to think you're like Arrested Development, sort of. And the shadow of Molly Shannon looms. I fear you, and for you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content><category term="pop culture"/></entry><entry><title>it's authenticity day at Manifest Density</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/08/19/its-authenticity-day-at-manifest-density/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-08-19T17:40:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-08-19T17:40:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-08-19:/2008/08/19/its-authenticity-day-at-manifest-density/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://attackerman.firedoglake.com/2008/08/19/personalitycrisesandcrabchips/"&gt;Spencer's right&lt;/a&gt;: I shouldn't get myself tangled up in questions of potato chip birthrights. Perhaps my intemperate comments were motivated by jealousy. After all, it's not like you can buy Utz Chili Half Smoke Chips. The Crab Chip belongs to Baltimore; maybe I only think I don't want it because …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://attackerman.firedoglake.com/2008/08/19/personalitycrisesandcrabchips/"&gt;Spencer's right&lt;/a&gt;: I shouldn't get myself tangled up in questions of potato chip birthrights. Perhaps my intemperate comments were motivated by jealousy. After all, it's not like you can buy Utz Chili Half Smoke Chips. The Crab Chip belongs to Baltimore; maybe I only think I don't want it because I know it can never truly be mine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the point of &lt;a class="reference external" href="/2008/08/14/we-will-not-speak-of-the-ketchup-chip/"&gt;that post&lt;/a&gt; stands! On Friday night, thanks to Ficke and Becks' generous snack-procurement, I had some Crab Chips back to back with Carolina Style BBQ Chips. I may have underestimated the Crab Chip, but Carolina BBQ remains the superior snack food.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="pop culture"/></entry><entry><title>savoring every drop of Watchmen-related media</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/08/15/savoring-every-drop-of-watchmen-related-media/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-08-15T13:47:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-08-15T13:47:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-08-15:/2008/08/15/savoring-every-drop-of-watchmen-related-media/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yglesias links to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20213273_3,00.html"&gt;Entertainment Weekly's chat with Zack Snyder&lt;/a&gt;, director of the upcoming &lt;em&gt;Watchmen&lt;/em&gt; movie adaptation, and hatches a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://yglesias.thinkprogress.org/archives/2008/08/who_watches_the_movie_studios.php"&gt;promising new conspiracy theory&lt;/a&gt;. I haven't got much to add, but I do want to point out &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.wizarduniverse.com/080808snyder.html"&gt;this Q&amp;amp;A between Snyder and Wizard Magazine&lt;/a&gt;. I understand the reservations about Snyder …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yglesias links to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.ew.com/ew/article/0,,20213273_3,00.html"&gt;Entertainment Weekly's chat with Zack Snyder&lt;/a&gt;, director of the upcoming &lt;em&gt;Watchmen&lt;/em&gt; movie adaptation, and hatches a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://yglesias.thinkprogress.org/archives/2008/08/who_watches_the_movie_studios.php"&gt;promising new conspiracy theory&lt;/a&gt;. I haven't got much to add, but I do want to point out &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.wizarduniverse.com/080808snyder.html"&gt;this Q&amp;amp;A between Snyder and Wizard Magazine&lt;/a&gt;. I understand the reservations about Snyder — and I share them, to some extent — but he's certainly saying all the right things.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="pop culture"/></entry><entry><title>things said so often during olympic telecasts that they cannot possibly be true</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/08/10/things-said-so-often-during-olympic-telecasts-that-they-cannot-possibly-be-true/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-08-10T19:18:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-08-10T19:18:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-08-10:/2008/08/10/things-said-so-often-during-olympic-telecasts-that-they-cannot-possibly-be-true/</id><content type="html">&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;This is the second most popular sport in the world after soccer.&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;She is one of the most famous people in China.&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Michael Phelps is charismatic and his races are interesting to watch.&amp;quot; (implied)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;quot;Russian tanks are rolling into Georgia.&amp;quot;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm on to you!&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="pop culture"/></entry><entry><title>grudging acceptance</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/08/07/grudging-acceptance/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-08-07T22:53:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-08-07T22:53:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-08-07:/2008/08/07/grudging-acceptance/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last night's &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.travelchannel.com/TV_Shows/Samantha_Brown"&gt;Samantha Brown&lt;/a&gt; episode about DC: actually pretty good. I suppose it ought to have been, since the Travel Channel is based in Chevy Chase. Still, it was kind of surprising to see someone do a not half-bad job representing the city. Brown herself is charming and funny, and …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last night's &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.travelchannel.com/TV_Shows/Samantha_Brown"&gt;Samantha Brown&lt;/a&gt; episode about DC: actually pretty good. I suppose it ought to have been, since the Travel Channel is based in Chevy Chase. Still, it was kind of surprising to see someone do a not half-bad job representing the city. Brown herself is charming and funny, and I hear she killed Andrew Zimmern in personal combat in order to land her own show. Hell, I would've given her a show for any two of those three.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="pop culture"/></entry><entry><title>take THAT, Ezra</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/08/07/take-that-ezra/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-08-07T11:05:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-08-07T11:05:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-08-07:/2008/08/07/take-that-ezra/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This (via &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.prospect.org/csnc/blogs/ezraklein_archive?month=08&amp;amp;year=2008&amp;amp;base_name=what_gender_are_you"&gt;Ezra&lt;/a&gt;) is a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.mikeonads.com/2008/07/13/using-your-browser-url-history-estimate-gender/"&gt;pretty fun little toy&lt;/a&gt; — it uses &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.niallkennedy.com/blog/2008/02/browser-history-sniff.html"&gt;this clever hack&lt;/a&gt; to figure out what sites you've recently visited, then compares it to demographic data from Quantcast to determine whether you're male or female. My results:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image1" class="center" src="http://www.manifestdensity.net/skitch/Mike_On_Ads_%C2%BB_Blog_Archive_%C2%BB_Using_your_browser_URL_history_to_estimate_gender-20080807-110426.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's right: my overpowering masculinity extends far; yea, even unto the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This (via &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.prospect.org/csnc/blogs/ezraklein_archive?month=08&amp;amp;year=2008&amp;amp;base_name=what_gender_are_you"&gt;Ezra&lt;/a&gt;) is a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.mikeonads.com/2008/07/13/using-your-browser-url-history-estimate-gender/"&gt;pretty fun little toy&lt;/a&gt; — it uses &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.niallkennedy.com/blog/2008/02/browser-history-sniff.html"&gt;this clever hack&lt;/a&gt; to figure out what sites you've recently visited, then compares it to demographic data from Quantcast to determine whether you're male or female. My results:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image1" class="center" src="http://www.manifestdensity.net/skitch/Mike_On_Ads_%C2%BB_Blog_Archive_%C2%BB_Using_your_browser_URL_history_to_estimate_gender-20080807-110426.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's right: my overpowering masculinity extends far; yea, even unto the document object model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually, though, I think I probably got this result in a nontypical way, as my browser history currently contains no links to ESPN. The most incriminating domains on my list include &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://jeroenwijering.com"&gt;jeroenwijering.com&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://digikey.com"&gt;digikey.com&lt;/a&gt; and, um, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://washingtontimes.com"&gt;washingtontimes.com&lt;/a&gt; (I don't read it for the articles! I swear!).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That, or maybe the script noticed that yesterday I read &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://radaronline.com/exclusives/2008/08/tucker-max-responds.php"&gt;an article about Tucker Max&lt;/a&gt;. Based on that datum alone the script should not only be able to tell that I'm male but also that I'm an asshole.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="pop culture"/></entry><entry><title>no tween market exploitation without representation</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/08/04/no-tween-market-exploitation-without-representation/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-08-04T16:13:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-08-04T16:13:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-08-04:/2008/08/04/no-tween-market-exploitation-without-representation/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://movering.com/node/558"&gt;&lt;img alt="image1" class="center" src="/static/2008/08/04/teenchoice-20080804-161320.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to professional entanglements it would be inappropriate for me to comment on &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://movering.com/node/558"&gt;these allegations&lt;/a&gt; other than to say that I find them troubling, and that I have complete faith that the good people behind the Teen Choice Awards will continue to do everything in their power to uphold the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://movering.com/node/558"&gt;&lt;img alt="image1" class="center" src="/static/2008/08/04/teenchoice-20080804-161320.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Due to professional entanglements it would be inappropriate for me to comment on &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://movering.com/node/558"&gt;these allegations&lt;/a&gt; other than to say that I find them troubling, and that I have complete faith that the good people behind the Teen Choice Awards will continue to do everything in their power to uphold the finest traditions of our democracy.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="pop culture"/></entry><entry><title>True Blood</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/08/04/true-blood/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-08-04T14:53:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-08-04T14:53:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-08-04:/2008/08/04/true-blood/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'll be up front with you: it's nothing but exposition, the art is so-so, the display software is terrible and it ends with an irritating cliffhanger. Still! If &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/08/03/arts/television/03rhod.html?_r=1&amp;amp;scp=1&amp;amp;sq=true%20blood&amp;amp;st=cse&amp;amp;oref=slogin"&gt;the Sunday NYT article&lt;/a&gt; wasn't enough for you, go read &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.hbo.com/trueblood/comicreader/"&gt;HBO's True Blood comic&lt;/a&gt;. If nothing else it serves to quickly establish …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'll be up front with you: it's nothing but exposition, the art is so-so, the display software is terrible and it ends with an irritating cliffhanger. Still! If &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2008/08/03/arts/television/03rhod.html?_r=1&amp;amp;scp=1&amp;amp;sq=true%20blood&amp;amp;st=cse&amp;amp;oref=slogin"&gt;the Sunday NYT article&lt;/a&gt; wasn't enough for you, go read &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.hbo.com/trueblood/comicreader/"&gt;HBO's True Blood comic&lt;/a&gt;. If nothing else it serves to quickly establish the ground rules for the upcoming series' world. Vampires, people! God, it takes so little to get me excited.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="pop culture"/></entry><entry><title>The Dark Knight</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/07/28/the-dark-knight/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-07-28T10:28:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-07-28T10:28:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-07-28:/2008/07/28/the-dark-knight/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I realize that our national conversation about Batman is already more or less over, but the weighty responsibilities of internet citizenship can't be shirked so easily. So: Emily and I went to see the new Batman movie on Friday, with &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://doombot.com"&gt;Jason&lt;/a&gt;, Gen, Sarah and two nice folks who disappeared so …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I realize that our national conversation about Batman is already more or less over, but the weighty responsibilities of internet citizenship can't be shirked so easily. So: Emily and I went to see the new Batman movie on Friday, with &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://doombot.com"&gt;Jason&lt;/a&gt;, Gen, Sarah and two nice folks who disappeared so quickly that I'm not sure they were ever there at all. Mr. and Ms. Soze, we'll call them (now and then not again).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emily hated it, and at the time this prompted me to stick up for the movie in an attempt to defend the institution of comic book adaptations. They've only grossed, what, a billion dollars this summer? Clearly this struggling art form needs our support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But now, thinking about it some more, I have some complaints.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the thing about the Batman movie: I want to signal my approval. Christopher Nolan is clearly thinking about Batman in the right way; the actors associated with the franchise are all doing an excellent job of adapting an awkwardly large and sometimes-cartoonish mythology into a filmed perspective that is as realistic as is realistically possible. The basic thesis of the movie was a good one, too, and an appropriate arc for the second movie of a Batman reboot. The movie looks right, it sounds right, it moves right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My only real problem with the film was everything that happens in it. Spoilers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why are we going to Hong Kong? Why are we giving all the &amp;quot;terrible binary choice&amp;quot; schemes to the Joker instead of the duality- and choice-obsessed Two-Face? Why are we suddenly inserting hamfisted topical controversies into our final act, and then using it as an excuse to pollute our climactic action scene with unimpressive and confusing CGI? Why is the culmination of the Joker's devotion to chaos a bunch of people on a barge &lt;em&gt;putting their votes in a hat?&lt;/em&gt; Remember when people were running screaming from poison blimps as Jack Nicholson's admittedly-ludicrous Joker gleefully presided over the deadly parade festivities? Wasn't that much, much better?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, why is the mayor wearing so much eye makeup?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as I said, I want to signal my approval: these are basically the right people to put in charge of Batman. And I &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.prospect.org/csnc/blogs/ezraklein_archive?month=07&amp;amp;year=2008&amp;amp;base_name=the_future_of_superhero_movies#107833"&gt;completely agree with Ezra&lt;/a&gt; when he says that the superhero movie genre has much more life left in it than many people realize. The archetypal nature of these characters makes them uniquely suited to big movies that are somewhat less stupid than can be reasonably expected. It's nice to be able to entrust beloved franchises to professionals who recognize that opportunity and want to do right by it, instead of giving it to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.imdb.com/find?q=joel+schumacher&amp;amp;sourceid=mozilla-search"&gt;incompetents&lt;/a&gt; or shame-faced wannabe-artistes who're looking for a payday to tide them over until they can shoot another doomed small film about terminal illness or divorce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I just want them to hire Bruce Timm and Paul Dini to write the script. Although they can keep whoever came up with the thing with the dude with the cellphone. That was pretty awesome.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="pop culture"/></entry><entry><title>coming soon as an impassioned letter in Wizard</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/06/16/coming-soon-as-an-impassioned-letter-in-wizard/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-06-16T14:35:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-06-16T14:35:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-06-16:/2008/06/16/coming-soon-as-an-impassioned-letter-in-wizard/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Important business:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://mstem.wordpress.com"&gt;Via Matt S.&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://blog.wired.com/underwire/2008/06/captain-ameri-1.html"&gt;Leonardo DiCaprio as Captain America&lt;/a&gt;!? No no no. &lt;em&gt;That's the wrong kind of earnest.&lt;/em&gt; He looks wrong, is a pretty atrocious actor and has never pulled off a convincingly alpha-male leading role.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://thinkprogress.org/attackerman/2008/06/14/hulksomewhatdisappointedbutwillstillsmash/#more-1344"&gt;Hulk is about the Cold War&lt;/a&gt;? I have to defer to Spencer's greater …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Important business:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://mstem.wordpress.com"&gt;Via Matt S.&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://blog.wired.com/underwire/2008/06/captain-ameri-1.html"&gt;Leonardo DiCaprio as Captain America&lt;/a&gt;!? No no no. &lt;em&gt;That's the wrong kind of earnest.&lt;/em&gt; He looks wrong, is a pretty atrocious actor and has never pulled off a convincingly alpha-male leading role.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://thinkprogress.org/attackerman/2008/06/14/hulksomewhatdisappointedbutwillstillsmash/#more-1344"&gt;Hulk is about the Cold War&lt;/a&gt;? I have to defer to Spencer's greater familiarity with the franchise, but this seems all wrong to me. The Hulk is afraid of himself and his lack of self-control. He's defined by rage, isolation and the hopelessness of ever achieving normality. He's a teenage boy, in other words, Peter Parker but with a worse temper and gloomier attitude. Hulk is for anyone who's felt like the anger welling up inside of them could destroy the world, and been unsure if they liked the idea.
I mean, yes, radiation, etc. But that was just the unknowable technology of the day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</content><category term="pop culture"/></entry><entry><title>great advertisements I have recently known</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/06/09/great-advertisements-i-have-recently-known/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-06-09T10:27:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-06-09T10:27:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-06-09:/2008/06/09/great-advertisements-i-have-recently-known/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Don't make me pick a favorite:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;McDonald's &amp;quot;Southern Style&amp;quot; Chicken Sandwich&lt;/strong&gt; As the commercial points out, this is less a fried chicken and pickle sandwich than an ascendant generation's rallying cry. These people have different habits — and tastes! And they're &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; going to submit to the tyranny of traditional breakfast …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Don't make me pick a favorite:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;McDonald's &amp;quot;Southern Style&amp;quot; Chicken Sandwich&lt;/strong&gt; As the commercial points out, this is less a fried chicken and pickle sandwich than an ascendant generation's rallying cry. These people have different habits — and tastes! And they're &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; going to submit to the tyranny of traditional breakfast, old man. Also, the chicken is juicy and perfectly seasoned, two points which I'm mentioning in an entirely ordinary, conversational way.
I wanted to reach out to the screen and plaintively tell these hip young sandwich consumers that I, too, have eaten chicken for breakfast. I understand! Oh god, take me with you! But their faces would have been no less implacable had they been in the room instead of on the screen. My time is over. I must go into the West, and diminish.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Liberty/Freedom/Independence Disposable Catheters:&lt;/strong&gt; DID YOU KNOW that a recent Medicare decision means that you no longer have to suffer with reusable catheters? I sure was sick of the tedious boiling and sterile procedure associated with my reusable catheters. But it was hard for a comparatively sexy, somewhat vivacious catheter user like myself to find time to call. Finally, my mother (STILL ALIVE) convinced me. Boy, am I glad I did! The folks at Liberty/Freedom/Independence were so friendly (YOU WILL BE LESS ALONE), and now I have much more time for my active lifestyle, pictured here (GINGERLY BENDING DOWN TO PET CAT). I use Liberty/Freedom/Independence every time I &amp;quot;cath&amp;quot;! (EW)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content><category term="pop culture"/></entry><entry><title>f for fake</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2008/06/04/f-for-fake/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-06-04T12:34:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-06-04T12:34:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2008-06-04:/2008/06/04/f-for-fake/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Julian &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.juliansanchez.com/2008/06/03/this-is-a-film-about/"&gt;posted&lt;/a&gt; about &lt;em&gt;F for Fake&lt;/em&gt; yesterday, which prompted me to watch a few more clips of the film scattered around the internet. I have to admit that I'm not familiar with much of Orson Welles' body of work beyond &lt;em&gt;Citizen Kane&lt;/em&gt; and his famous &lt;em&gt;War of the Worlds&lt;/em&gt; broadcast …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Julian &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.juliansanchez.com/2008/06/03/this-is-a-film-about/"&gt;posted&lt;/a&gt; about &lt;em&gt;F for Fake&lt;/em&gt; yesterday, which prompted me to watch a few more clips of the film scattered around the internet. I have to admit that I'm not familiar with much of Orson Welles' body of work beyond &lt;em&gt;Citizen Kane&lt;/em&gt; and his famous &lt;em&gt;War of the Worlds&lt;/em&gt; broadcast. So I had assumed that there was no more complete and cruel affirmation of Welles' final, nihilistic hopelessness than his next-to-last acting credit: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0092106/"&gt;the voice of Unicron in the Transformers movie&lt;/a&gt;. But it appears that history has come up with innovative new sleights since then.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Within &lt;em&gt;F for Fake&lt;/em&gt; there's a monologue about Chartes Cathedral in which Welles expresses the idea that our individual impermanence doesn't imply futility — that there's dignity to be had in the moment and within our collective history. It's quite beautiful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, be sure to check out the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.youtube.com/comment_servlet?all_comments&amp;amp;v=pUrKCUTUSPo"&gt;associated Youtube comments&lt;/a&gt;, which together form a convincing rebuttal. I especially like the one comparing Welles' work (unfavorably) to that of Quentin Tarantino.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="pop culture"/></entry></feed>