<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Tom Lee - science</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"/><link href="/feeds/science.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>/</id><updated>2010-02-16T19:57:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>to clarify</title><link href="/2010/02/16/to-clarify/" rel="alternate"/><published>2010-02-16T19:57:00-05:00</published><updated>2010-02-16T19:57:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2010-02-16:/2010/02/16/to-clarify/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Matt has &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://yglesias.thinkprogress.org/archives/2010/02/is-the-universe-a-hologram-should-we-care.php"&gt;graciously responded&lt;/a&gt;, pointing me toward a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://consc.net/papers/matrix.html"&gt;David Chalmers essay&lt;/a&gt; that I think I've skimmed in the past. Revisiting it, I think I didn't express the question I'm wondering about clearly enough.&amp;nbsp; Chalmers (and Matt) seem to basically be saying that it's not worth letting Cartesian hypotheticals keep you …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Matt has &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://yglesias.thinkprogress.org/archives/2010/02/is-the-universe-a-hologram-should-we-care.php"&gt;graciously responded&lt;/a&gt;, pointing me toward a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://consc.net/papers/matrix.html"&gt;David Chalmers essay&lt;/a&gt; that I think I've skimmed in the past. Revisiting it, I think I didn't express the question I'm wondering about clearly enough.&amp;nbsp; Chalmers (and Matt) seem to basically be saying that it's not worth letting Cartesian hypotheticals keep you up at night, no matter how irrefutably plausible they may be.&amp;nbsp; I agree!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what I find interesting about the holographic hypothesis is what Chalmers dismisses at the end of this passage:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Computational Hypothesis says that physics as we know it not the fundamental level of reality. Just as chemical processes underlie biological processes, and microphysical processes underlie chemical processes, something underlies microphysical processes. Underneath the level of quarks and electrons and photons is a further level: the level of bits. These bits are governed by a computational algorithm, which at a higher-level produces the processes that we think of as fundamental particles, forces, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Computational Hypothesis is not as widely believed as the Creation Hypothesis, but some people take it seriously. Most famously, Ed Fredkin has postulated that the universe is at bottom some sort of computer. More recently, Stephen Wolfram has taken up the idea in his book &lt;em&gt;A New Kind of Science&lt;/em&gt;, suggesting that at the fundamental level, physical reality may be a sort of cellular automata, with interacting bits governed by simple rules. And some physicists have looked into the possibility that the laws of physics might be formulated computationally, or could be seen as the consequence of certain computational principles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One might worry that pure bits could not be the fundamental level of reality: a bit is just a 0 or a 1, and reality can't really be zeroes and ones. Or perhaps a bit is just a &amp;quot;pure difference&amp;quot; between two basic states, and there can't be a reality made up of pure differences. Rather, bits always have to be implemented by more basic states, such as voltages in a normal computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't know whether this objection is right. I don't think it's completely out of the question that there could be a universe of &amp;quot;pure bits&amp;quot;. But this doesn't matter for present purposes. We can suppose that the computational level is itself constituted by an even more fundamental level, at which the computational processes are implemented. It doesn't matter for present purposes what that more fundamental level is. All that matters is that microphysical processes are constituted by computational processes, which are themselves constituted by more basic processes. From now on I will regard the Computational Hypothesis as saying this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't know whether the Computational Hypothesis is correct. But again, I don't know that it is false. The hypothesis is coherent, if speculative, and I cannot conclusively rule it out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Computational Hypothesis is not a skeptical hypothesis. If it is true, there are still electrons and protons. On this picture, electrons and protons will be analogous to molecules: they are made up of something more basic, but they still exist. Similarly, if the Computational Hypothesis is true, there are still tables and chairs, and macroscopic reality still exists. It just turns out that their fundamental reality is a little different from what we thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The situation here is analogous to that with quantum mechanics or relativity. These may lead us to revise a few &amp;quot;metaphysical&amp;quot; beliefs about the external world: that the world is made of classical particles, or that there is absolute time. But most of our ordinary beliefs are left intact. Likewise, accepting the Computational Hypothesis may lead us to revise a few metaphysical beliefs: that electrons and protons are fundamental, for example. But most of our ordinary beliefs are unaffected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those &amp;quot;few metaphysical beliefs&amp;quot; are important, though! Contrary to what Chalmers implies, similar fundamental discoveries in other domains have, in fact, greatly informed our concept of how consciousness operates.&amp;nbsp; The understanding that the brain is the seat of the mind; and that neuronal firing is essential to its function; and that that function can be mediated by drugs or damage which can alter reported phenomenal experience and, we have strong reason to suspect, the mind itself -- these may all be philosophically irrelevant from Chalmers' perspective, as none of these have seriously shaken our faith in personal agency or qualia or the integrity of the conceptual world we inhabit or anything like that.&amp;nbsp; Chalmers would probably not go this far, but I think personal experience has an irresistible, biologically-determined immediacy, and the practical, personal psychological upshot of our discoveries about consciousness seems almost certain to be minimal.&amp;nbsp; Being alive is going to keep seeming the way it currently does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the aforementioned discoveries did give us some good clues about the limits of consciousness (its time resolution, for instance), and avenues for thinking about how to create it artificially, and how morally concerned we should be about canned tuna's dolphin-safe status. Certainly they blew dualism right out of the water (as far as most people are concerned).&amp;nbsp; It seems like the truth of the holographic hypothesis -- and that we experience ourselves as part of the holographic projection and not of the underlying lower-dimensional brane -- could also have some implications for how we think about, say, the possibility of panpsychism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or maybe not!&amp;nbsp; My aim is not to imply that the HH could be cause for a &amp;quot;nothing is real!&amp;quot;-style freakout, but I do think there might be more meat here than Matt's first impression implies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, the most likely explanation is that I'm fundamentally misunderstanding (or New Scientist misconstruing) the HH.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="science"/></entry><entry><title>lithium</title><link href="/2009/10/01/lithium/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-10-01T17:19:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-10-01T17:19:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2009-10-01:/2009/10/01/lithium/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I need to resist the urge to drone on and on about this, but having failed to heed Matt's encouragement to weigh in on the vital &amp;quot;worst bar in DC&amp;quot; debate, I feel obliged to pick this one up: why is &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.cnas.org/blogs/naturalsecurity/2009/09/lithium-not-just-nirvana-song.html"&gt;CNAS's post about lithium&lt;/a&gt; dumb?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, some caveats: other …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I need to resist the urge to drone on and on about this, but having failed to heed Matt's encouragement to weigh in on the vital &amp;quot;worst bar in DC&amp;quot; debate, I feel obliged to pick this one up: why is &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.cnas.org/blogs/naturalsecurity/2009/09/lithium-not-just-nirvana-song.html"&gt;CNAS's post about lithium&lt;/a&gt; dumb?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, some caveats: other than a brief tour through the world of materials science as an undergrad, several years' worth of pestering ChemE PhD friends about related issues, and time spent watching resource-shock warnings fail to materialize, I have no credentials to offer on this score.&amp;nbsp; Defer to official-looking PDFs!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Onward. The first and most galling part is this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Lithium is the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://periodic.lanl.gov/elements/3.html"&gt;lightest metal in nature&lt;/a&gt; and an excellent conductor of electricity, and these two properties make it especially useful for batteries.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is just completely wrong. Lithium is useful for batteries because of its pronounced &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Standard_electrode_potential_%28data_page%29"&gt;electrode potential&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp; Its lightness is a welcome attribute too, of course.&amp;nbsp; But the person who wrote that sentence simply doesn't know much about batteries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other problem with the article is its wishy-washy buy-in of the peak lithium frame (the idea has been more forcefully expressed elsewhere).&amp;nbsp; Most of the world's production of lithium ore comes from just a few places, and while CNAS acknowledges that they're politically stable, Bolivia is on the docket as &lt;em&gt;also&lt;/em&gt; having a lot of lithium, and what if they become the key source?!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyone who looks for them will see these resource-scare stories pop up on sites like Slashdot every once in a while.&amp;nbsp; It's frustrating, and all too easy to fall for, but the dire scenarios they foretell never seem to come to pass.&amp;nbsp; I remember a professor with grave concerns about the unreliability of Kazakhstan's chromium barons; yet a decade later, I have more stainless steel-clad consumer crap than ever.&amp;nbsp; And he was an expert!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the general public, the capacity for resource fearmongering is much worse.&amp;nbsp; Most people don't understand where metal comes from (admittedly, it is &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.thetoasterproject.org/"&gt;sort of mysterious&lt;/a&gt;).&amp;nbsp; As they attempt to puzzle out this question, the facts that they have to work with tend to be A) we're running out of oil! and B) prospecting for gold looks hard in westerns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neither of these are really applicable to most mining.&amp;nbsp; Oil's primary use is as fuel -- it's energy, not a durable good, and consequently we run through a ton of it.&amp;nbsp; As a result, small price shifts can have really serious consequences across the economy.&amp;nbsp; If you had to buy a new laptop battery every time your old one ran out of juice, the prospect of increasing lithium prices would concern me much more than it does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gold, meanwhile, is a heavy and therefore scarce element, and its nonreactivity helps to ensure that it's difficult to mine.&amp;nbsp; It has some valuable properties, but it's mostly valuable because it's so rare.&amp;nbsp; Applying lessons about the difficulty of mining gold to the mining of other substances is a mistake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the thing: ore is just material that has a little more of the substance you want in it than regular old rocks and dirt.&amp;nbsp; It's a slightly better starting material, and therefore a more economical one to process.&amp;nbsp; But there are lots of grades of ore.&amp;nbsp; It sounds like Bolivia's got some good stuff!&amp;nbsp; If that doesn't work out, though, we can probably find some not-quite-as-good stuff (look! Wikipedia says &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lithium#Occurrence"&gt;a firm has figured out how to economically extract lithium from hectorite clay&lt;/a&gt;!). Or we can reactivate those not-currently-economical American mines that the CNAS post alludes to. Or we can recycle more lithium.&amp;nbsp; All it takes is money and a reckless disregard for the environment.&amp;nbsp; This is one of those things that the market really will solve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So (still-theoretical) problems with our lithium supply could be bad news for the economic viability of electric cars, but we should resist the idea that we're going to run out of any minerals.&amp;nbsp; I think we're a long way from needing to panic about lithium supplies the way that we need to panic about oil supplies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Helium, though -- boy, I don't know. My friends Jeff and Marie have got me worried about it. Seriously: we need it to cool some extremely interesting magnets, it's only found as a byproduct of natural gas extraction -- the helium is trapped underground along with the NG -- and once it's in the atmosphere it diffuses into space. Stop buying balloons, you monsters!)&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="science"/></entry><entry><title>coal is a much better bicyclist than you</title><link href="/2009/07/16/coal-is-a-much-better-bicyclist-than-you/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-07-16T14:38:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-07-16T14:38:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2009-07-16:/2009/07/16/coal-is-a-much-better-bicyclist-than-you/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="20090716_coalhelmet.jpg" class="right" src="/static/2009/07/16/20090716_coalhelmet.jpg" style="width: 261px; height: 282px;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yglesias links to a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dc.thecityfix.com/"&gt;new blog&lt;/a&gt; about &amp;quot;sustainable mobility&amp;quot;. As a bike triumphalist, this is right up my alley. But the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dc.thecityfix.com/there-must-be-a-catch-right/"&gt;post at the top of the page&lt;/a&gt; is... unfortunate. Entitled &amp;quot;There Must Be a Catch, Right?&amp;quot;, it discusses a student's proposal to attach power-generating systems to the fleets of …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="20090716_coalhelmet.jpg" class="right" src="/static/2009/07/16/20090716_coalhelmet.jpg" style="width: 261px; height: 282px;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yglesias links to a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dc.thecityfix.com/"&gt;new blog&lt;/a&gt; about &amp;quot;sustainable mobility&amp;quot;. As a bike triumphalist, this is right up my alley. But the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dc.thecityfix.com/there-must-be-a-catch-right/"&gt;post at the top of the page&lt;/a&gt; is... unfortunate. Entitled &amp;quot;There Must Be a Catch, Right?&amp;quot;, it discusses a student's proposal to attach power-generating systems to the fleets of bikesharing programs, collect riders' spare energy, sell it back to the grid and pass the savings on to the consumer. It sounds great! Until you start doing math!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's some confusion about whether the power would come from regenerative braking or is siphoned off during pedaling. For a moment, let's keep this in the realm of the plausible and stipulate that it'll be from regenerative braking (anybody who's used a generator-powered bike light knows that they make pedaling unpleasantly difficult). How much energy could be harvested from a cyclist coming to a complete stop? Well, let's specify an implausibly heavy average cyclist (100 kg/220 lbs), an implausibly heavy bike (20 kg/45 lbs), an implausibly fast speed (48 kph/30 mph). Plug it into &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kinetic_energy#Newtonian_kinetic_energy"&gt;this equation&lt;/a&gt; and you'll get 10,773 joules per stop. Now let's specify an also-implausible 100 stops per mile — you'd be accelerating to 30mph and stopping every 53 feet. How much energy would you generate for every mile traveled?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The depressing answer: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.google.com/search?hl=en&amp;amp;q=1077300+joules+to+kilowatt+hours&amp;amp;aq=f&amp;amp;oq=&amp;amp;aqi="&gt;about 0.2 kilowatt hours&lt;/a&gt;. Which, using &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.eia.doe.gov/cneaf/electricity/epm/table5_3.html"&gt;these figures&lt;/a&gt;, works out to about 2.25 cents' worth of electricity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And of course not only are the above figures unrealistically optimistic, but the impracticality of having everyone drag along extension cords introduces new problems: the battery system will cost you a lot of energy. The conversions from kinetic energy to electrical energy, from electrical energy to chemical energy, and from chemical energy back to electrical energy will all be far from perfectly efficient. I wouldn't be surprised to see this eat up half of the energy generated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sadly, this doesn't look like a compelling case for spending money to outfit bikes with regenerative braking systems. You'll save much, much more energy by simply avoiding motorized transportation than you will by trying to squeeze more energy out of your bike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But although this is bleak news for this particular instance of innumerate ecothusiasm, I still find the situation kind of inspirational: it's a reminder that the forces we casually harness are incredibly vast when compared to the relatively meager capabilities of our biology. That's not bad for a species that watches as much &lt;em&gt;Law &amp;amp; Order&lt;/em&gt; as we do.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="science"/></entry><entry><title>the worst part is that the jokes are already tired. well alright, not the WORST part.</title><link href="/2009/04/29/the-worst-part-is-that-the-jokes-are-already-tired-well-alright-not-the-worst-part/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-04-29T17:10:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-04-29T17:10:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2009-04-29:/2009/04/29/the-worst-part-is-that-the-jokes-are-already-tired-well-alright-not-the-worst-part/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.cnn.com/2009/HEALTH/04/29/swine.flu/index.html"&gt;CNN&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Researchers do not know how the virus is jumping relatively easily from person to person, or why it's affecting what should be society's healthiest demographic. Many of the victims who have died in Mexico have been young and otherwise healthy.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's too early to say if this is the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.cnn.com/2009/HEALTH/04/29/swine.flu/index.html"&gt;CNN&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Researchers do not know how the virus is jumping relatively easily from person to person, or why it's affecting what should be society's healthiest demographic. Many of the victims who have died in Mexico have been young and otherwise healthy.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's too early to say if this is the mechanism (or even if a genuine trend exists making young people more susceptible), but one possible explanation is a cytokine storm, in which the body's immune system reacts so violently that it causes damage. There's an interesting discussion of all this &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://scienceblogs.com/aetiology/2009/04/swine_flu_and_deaths_in_health.php"&gt;over at ScienceBlogs&lt;/a&gt;. Luckily for me, my immune system kinda sucks.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="science"/></entry><entry><title>fascinating</title><link href="/2009/02/02/fascinating/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-02-02T17:40:00-05:00</published><updated>2009-02-02T17:40:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2009-02-02:/2009/02/02/fascinating/</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://idlewords.com/2007/04/the_alameda-weehawken_burrito_tunnel.htm"&gt;I had no idea&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="science"/></entry><entry><title>today in misleading science news</title><link href="/2008/09/17/today-in-misleading-science-news/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-09-17T11:01:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-09-17T11:01:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2008-09-17:/2008/09/17/today-in-misleading-science-news/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hey, look! &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2008/09/080916143910.htm"&gt;An exciting article&lt;/a&gt; about energy storage technology! Graphene ultracapacitors, son! As the piece notes, these new doodads offer &amp;quot;double the capacity of existing ultracapacitors&amp;quot;, and &amp;quot;higher power capability&amp;quot; than batteries!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article then goes on to discuss how off-peak power storage is a major problem facing renewable energy …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hey, look! &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2008/09/080916143910.htm"&gt;An exciting article&lt;/a&gt; about energy storage technology! Graphene ultracapacitors, son! As the piece notes, these new doodads offer &amp;quot;double the capacity of existing ultracapacitors&amp;quot;, and &amp;quot;higher power capability&amp;quot; than batteries!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The article then goes on to discuss how off-peak power storage is a major problem facing renewable energy sources. Which is true! But of course ultracapacitors have absolutely nothing to do with solving that problem. Graphene-based ultracaps may be twice as good as existing ultracaps (although that leaves them lagging behind the still-maybe-not-imaginary &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eestor"&gt;EEStor&lt;/a&gt; offering). But a 2x improvement still leaves ultracaps capable of storing only about a fifth as much energy as a boring ol' chemical battery. That &amp;quot;higher power capability&amp;quot; refers to the speed with which they can deliver or take a charge, not how much energy they can hold. For some applications that's a crucially important attribute. Just not, y'know, the ones the article talks about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As usual a misleading press release from a university (in this case: hook 'em ultracapacitors!) has been gleefully adapted by a credulous reporter. Somewhere along the line a claim that this may solve our energy problems and/or cure cancer will invariably be added. The poor professors and grad students being given the credit for saving our society will have their quotes — in which they honestly explain the legitimately impressive but not immediately world-changing work they've done! — placed in a context that they must find deeply embarrassing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My suggestion: get your tech news from &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://technologyreview.com/"&gt;MIT Technology Review&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://arstechnica.com"&gt;Ars&lt;/a&gt;. And if something sounds amazing, go find the associated &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://slashdot.org"&gt;Slashdot&lt;/a&gt; thread and read it. You'll usually find at least a few surprisingly informative comments from engineers with expertise relevant to the alleged breakthrough.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="science"/></entry><entry><title>there is no better battery</title><link href="/2008/08/20/there-is-no-better-battery/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-08-20T14:55:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-08-20T14:55:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2008-08-20:/2008/08/20/there-is-no-better-battery/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ryan and I have been going back and forth &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.ryanavent.com/blog/?p=1335#comment-92836"&gt;in his comments&lt;/a&gt; about the likelihood of carsharing services going electric. I think it's unlikely because they'd have to spend too much time charging; he thinks they're a good candidate for early rollout of the charging infrastructure necessary for such a …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Ryan and I have been going back and forth &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.ryanavent.com/blog/?p=1335#comment-92836"&gt;in his comments&lt;/a&gt; about the likelihood of carsharing services going electric. I think it's unlikely because they'd have to spend too much time charging; he thinks they're a good candidate for early rollout of the charging infrastructure necessary for such a switch. Most recently he said:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
In practice, this could be achieved incrementally. Tweak business models over a ten year period through which you slowly switch from gas engines to plug-in hybrids to all electric, over which period, presumably, battery technology slowly improves. Neednâ€™t be done all at once.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this is a point that's worth making here and at some length: &amp;quot;presum[ing that] battery technology improves&amp;quot; is setting yourself up for failure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In truth, there have only been a few noteworthy improvements in battery tech during Ryan and my lifetimes: longer-lived NiCd and NiMH batteries; some improvement in alkaline batteries; and the popularization of lithium batteries. But look closer and you'll realize that most of these aren't actually battery innovations, per se: they're benefits of the microprocessor revolution. Cheap, smart charging circuitry allowed us to avoid memory effects; to balance load across cells; and to monitor lithium cells' temperature and voltage as they charge so that they don't catch fire (well... &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WeWq6rWzChw"&gt;usually&lt;/a&gt;), thereby finally making lithium a viable option for consumer electronics. Those are all important developments, but at this point we've wrung about as much as we can out of charging our batteries more cleverly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of this has done much to improve the fundamental energy storage densities of the underlying chemistries. These have been known for a long time now, and nothing is going to change them — &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Table_of_standard_electrode_potentials"&gt;nor are there any more promising elements like lithium&lt;/a&gt; waiting to be tamed (well, none that aren't radioactive, anyway). The glacial pace of improvement in battery technology really can't be overemphasized. The lead-acid battery was developed in 1859, for pete's sake. It's really heavy relative to the energy it stores, can produce explosive fumes if overcharged, and sometimes requires the addition of distilled water. Yet it's still the best battery technology we have for supplying the high current necessary to turn over an engine. A century and a half and we haven't come up with anything better!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It may &lt;em&gt;seem&lt;/em&gt; like batteries have improved dramatically — consider the lifespan of an iPod Nano versus a portable cassette player. But this is misleading. In fact it's a byproduct of more energy-efficient technologies. Which isn't to dismiss energy effiency! But electric motors are already &lt;em&gt;extremely&lt;/em&gt; efficient. And when it comes to vehicles, we're unfortunately dealing with hard physical limits related to how much energy it takes to move a car. So long as we're committed to EVs being able to perform like and drive safely near gasoline-powered cars, we will find ourselves with less room for improvement than people would like to think.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't mean to be a downer, but it's difficult to overstate what a serious problem this is, or for how long it's been one. Hydrocarbons are an unbelievably efficient way to store energy when compared to electrochemical cells, and I seriously doubt anything will change that. Hopefully I'll be proven wrong. But smart people have been working on the battery problem for decades and decades, propelled by the lure of the financial bonanza that a breakthrough would represent. And while they've made impressive improvements, none come anywhere close to competing with gasoline's energy density. We're still &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Energy_density#Energy_density_in_energy_storage_and_in_fuel"&gt;an order of magnitude away&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now of course there are always fuel cells. And nanotech's vast surface areas may deliver unexpected breakthroughs. But a bet that counts on a better battery is still a very, very bad wager.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="science"/></entry><entry><title>the weirding way to better brain health</title><link href="/2008/07/31/the-weirding-way-to-better-brain-health/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-07-31T11:32:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-07-31T11:32:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2008-07-31:/2008/07/31/the-weirding-way-to-better-brain-health/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;... or, &amp;quot;Kwisatz Haderacetylcholinergic Drug Alternatives&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.medpagetoday.com/MeetingCoverage/ICAD/tb/10320"&gt;Rember&lt;/a&gt; drug that's showing promising efficacy against Alzheimer's is really pretty exciting. For a long time I've had blind faith that my generation wouldn't have to face Alzheimer's, at least not the way folks currently do. I was hopeful that the solution would arrive …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;... or, &amp;quot;Kwisatz Haderacetylcholinergic Drug Alternatives&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.medpagetoday.com/MeetingCoverage/ICAD/tb/10320"&gt;Rember&lt;/a&gt; drug that's showing promising efficacy against Alzheimer's is really pretty exciting. For a long time I've had blind faith that my generation wouldn't have to face Alzheimer's, at least not the way folks currently do. I was hopeful that the solution would arrive in time for our parents, too — now it looks like it might.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The story behind the drug is interesting. Naturally, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://pipeline.corante.com/archives/2008/07/31/rember_for_alzheimers_methylene_blues_comeback.php"&gt;Derek Lowe&lt;/a&gt; is the place to go for an informed perspective on the matter. He (and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://blog.wired.com/wiredscience/2008/07/new-alzheimers.html"&gt;Wired&lt;/a&gt;) both note that Rember is actually a very old drug: Methylene Blue, which has been used for everything from malaria to psychiatric disorders to intestinal surgery. It's got a long history and seems to be quite safe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it is very, very blue. And that leads to some side effects. From &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Methylene_blue"&gt;the Wikipedia article&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Methylene blue was used at the end of the century as a successful treatment for malaria. It disappeared as an anti-malarial during the wars in Asia, as U.S. soldiers disliked its two inevitable, fully reversible side effects: green urine and blue sclera.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blue sclera — as in the used-to-be-whites of your eyes. So yes: grandma might remain mentally sharp, but she's going to look like she just wandered off the set of &lt;em&gt;Dune&lt;/em&gt;. Awesome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image1" class="center" src="/static/2008/07/31/skitched-20080731-115749.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Presumably the drug can be used synergistically with the &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sapho_juice"&gt;Juice of Saphoo&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="science"/></entry><entry><title>machine-readable genetic grammar architecting for dummies</title><link href="/2008/05/19/machine-readable-genetic-grammar-architecting-for-dummies/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-05-19T13:43:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-05-19T13:43:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2008-05-19:/2008/05/19/machine-readable-genetic-grammar-architecting-for-dummies/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm not at all confident about which of his aliases I should be using, but I &lt;em&gt;am&lt;/em&gt; quite sure that son1's series of posts explaining the location of his work — right at the intersection of genetics and computer science — is pretty fascinating. I'm jealous, frankly: taking a problem and unraveling …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm not at all confident about which of his aliases I should be using, but I &lt;em&gt;am&lt;/em&gt; quite sure that son1's series of posts explaining the location of his work — right at the intersection of genetics and computer science — is pretty fascinating. I'm jealous, frankly: taking a problem and unraveling it into tasks that can be algorithmically accomplished is incredibly satisfying; I can only imagine how interesting it must be when the problem is something as complex and challenging as studying genes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So go! Read! &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://bayes.wordpress.com/2008/05/13/seeing-the-logic-of-classical-genetics-part-i/"&gt;part 1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://bayes.wordpress.com/2008/05/13/northern-lights-2/"&gt;part 2&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://bayes.wordpress.com/2008/05/14/apparently-one-idea-was-all-i-ever-had/"&gt;part 2a&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://bayes.wordpress.com/2008/05/15/its-getting-hot-adhere/"&gt;part 3&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://bayes.wordpress.com/2008/05/15/its-not-one-of-my-tricks-its-my-conclusion/"&gt;part 4&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="science"/></entry><entry><title>something like an epiphenomenon</title><link href="/2008/04/13/something-like-an-epiphenomenon/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-04-13T22:38:00-04:00</published><updated>2008-04-13T22:38:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2008-04-13:/2008/04/13/something-like-an-epiphenomenon/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Friday night was the first time in a good long while that I got to expound angrily (/drunkenly) on the subject of free will. But here! Look! I come home and Slashdot is linking to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.wired.com/science/discoveries/news/2008/04/mind_decision"&gt;a writeup&lt;/a&gt; of an experiment that reconfirms and extends my &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://l3d.cs.colorado.edu/~ctg/classes/lib/cogsci/haggard.pdf"&gt;all-time favorite neuroscience result (PDF …&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Friday night was the first time in a good long while that I got to expound angrily (/drunkenly) on the subject of free will. But here! Look! I come home and Slashdot is linking to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.wired.com/science/discoveries/news/2008/04/mind_decision"&gt;a writeup&lt;/a&gt; of an experiment that reconfirms and extends my &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://l3d.cs.colorado.edu/~ctg/classes/lib/cogsci/haggard.pdf"&gt;all-time favorite neuroscience result (PDF)&lt;/a&gt;. Apparently April is mechanism month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, you should check out one or the other of those links if you aren't already familiar with Libet's famous work. It's creepy, clever and morbid — a combination that I aspire to myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MORE, AND A REQUEST:&lt;/strong&gt; Man, it really &lt;em&gt;has&lt;/em&gt; been a while. But Tim has some interesting things to say &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://techliberation.com/2008/04/14/cartesian-theater/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and I left a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://techliberation.com/2008/04/14/cartesian-theater/#comment-41193"&gt;long comment&lt;/a&gt; in response, which gave me occasion to remember that I had written &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.zunta.org/blog/archives/2005/02/25/superposition_a/"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;, and in general if you would like to shoot the shit about consciousness I'd love to take you up on it. I had kind of thrown up my hands a few years ago and decided to learn about electronics instead, but I think I'd like to be able to begin speaking meaningfully about this again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first question: what should I be reading? The last time I seriously checked into these issues I was thinking about buying &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.amazon.com/Quest-Consciousness-Neurobiological-Approach/dp/0974707708/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;s=books&amp;amp;qid=1208196000&amp;amp;sr=8-1"&gt;Christof Koch's book&lt;/a&gt;, but I ended up getting distracted/discouraged by its price tag and length. Has anything with a similar level of sophistication and noteworthiness come out since then, or is it time to grit my teeth and see what Prof. Koch has to say?&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="science"/></entry><entry><title>tautologous, but highly patentable</title><link href="/2008/02/28/tautologous-but-highly-patentable/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-02-28T12:26:00-05:00</published><updated>2008-02-28T12:26:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2008-02-28:/2008/02/28/tautologous-but-highly-patentable/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://pipeline.corante.com/archives/2008/02/27/antidepressants_depressing_news_or_not.php"&gt;Derek Lowe's blog&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
The actual mechanism of the placebo effect is a field of great interest and potentially great importance.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's right: someday soon scientists may be working to develop a pill that can mimic the placebo effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, I find this immensely cheering. I think I love this …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;From &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://pipeline.corante.com/archives/2008/02/27/antidepressants_depressing_news_or_not.php"&gt;Derek Lowe's blog&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
The actual mechanism of the placebo effect is a field of great interest and potentially great importance.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's right: someday soon scientists may be working to develop a pill that can mimic the placebo effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, I find this immensely cheering. I think I love this universe the most when it's operating at maximum ridiculousness.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="science"/></entry><entry><title>candy heart delectability by color</title><link href="/2008/02/13/candy-heart-delectability-by-color/" rel="alternate"/><published>2008-02-13T11:26:00-05:00</published><updated>2008-02-13T11:26:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2008-02-13:/2008/02/13/candy-heart-delectability-by-color/</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;(In descending order.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;White&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Orange&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pink&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Yellow*&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Purple*&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Green&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that the odds of me eating myself sick when presented with candy hearts approaches unity for all colors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;* Ranked position is within margin of error.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="science"/></entry><entry><title>entropy: pro and con</title><link href="/2007/11/15/entropy-pro-and-con/" rel="alternate"/><published>2007-11-15T10:43:00-05:00</published><updated>2007-11-15T10:43:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2007-11-15:/2007/11/15/entropy-pro-and-con/</id><summary type="html">&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PRO:&lt;/strong&gt; Towels are self-drying.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CON:&lt;/strong&gt; Dust accumulates on surfaces regardless of the moral culpability of the surface's owner. This is typically the first thing that comes to mind when I hear the phrase &amp;quot;cosmic injustice&amp;quot;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PRO:&lt;/strong&gt; The tendency of energy to seek less-ordered states allows physical work to exist in …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PRO:&lt;/strong&gt; Towels are self-drying.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CON:&lt;/strong&gt; Dust accumulates on surfaces regardless of the moral culpability of the surface's owner. This is typically the first thing that comes to mind when I hear the phrase &amp;quot;cosmic injustice&amp;quot;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PRO:&lt;/strong&gt; The tendency of energy to seek less-ordered states allows physical work to exist in the universe, which can can be harnessed by order-increasing processes, including those that form the basis of life.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CON:&lt;/strong&gt; Videogame controller cords frequently become tangled.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PRO/CON:&lt;/strong&gt; Bags of candy (e.g. Skittles) are self-mixing. However, this is somewhat offset by the resulting necessity of M&amp;amp;M sorting, which significantly drives up the per-unit cost of rock &amp;amp; roll.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PRO:&lt;/strong&gt; Ice makes drinks colder.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;CON:&lt;/strong&gt; The inevitable heat death of the universe. This sounds like it will be a drag.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;VERDICT:&lt;/strong&gt; Mixed. Entropy allows life to exist, but also means that life will consist largely of tidying up. It's unclear whether this is a net positive or negative.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="science"/></entry><entry><title>science journalism: still terrible</title><link href="/2007/08/15/science-journalism-still-terrible/" rel="alternate"/><published>2007-08-15T14:40:00-04:00</published><updated>2007-08-15T14:40:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2007-08-15:/2007/08/15/science-journalism-still-terrible/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's perpetually surprising to me that articles like &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/08/14/science/14tier.html?ei=5124&amp;amp;en=22efff4469281187&amp;amp;ex=1344744000&amp;amp;adxnnl=1&amp;amp;partner=permalink&amp;amp;exprod=permalink&amp;amp;adxnnlx=1187101355-5HWiLxChv9ReqvISlLpTnQ"&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt; can find their way into the Science section of what is by most accounts a Newspaper For Smart People. Even more astounding is that they got David Chalmers to contribute some quotes to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should read the piece for …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's perpetually surprising to me that articles like &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.nytimes.com/2007/08/14/science/14tier.html?ei=5124&amp;amp;en=22efff4469281187&amp;amp;ex=1344744000&amp;amp;adxnnl=1&amp;amp;partner=permalink&amp;amp;exprod=permalink&amp;amp;adxnnlx=1187101355-5HWiLxChv9ReqvISlLpTnQ"&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt; can find their way into the Science section of what is by most accounts a Newspaper For Smart People. Even more astounding is that they got David Chalmers to contribute some quotes to it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You should read the piece for yourself, but the gist of what John Tierney excitedly reports is that Dr. Nick Bostrom, Oxford philosophy professor, has decided that we may all be living in a computer simulation. He reasons that future civilizations will become advanced enough to run simulations of brains, and that they'll make widespread use of this technology for entertainment or to research their past. If they use it enough, the odds of a given mind from any point in history occurring outside of the system become quite low. If you consider the possibility of nested simulations the odds diminish even further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The whole &amp;quot;ancestor simulation&amp;quot; premise sounds like it suffers from some confusion about the reversibility of deterministic processes. There's also a bit of an issue with thinking that a lack of information can be remedied with probabilistic hand-waving (&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://crookedtimber.org/2007/07/17/against-the-copernicans/"&gt;this Crooked Timber post&lt;/a&gt; rails against the technique nicely). Bostrom's ideas, or at least Tierney's writeup, seem to ignore the considerably better-developed and more interesting speculation about the possibility of an &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Omega_point_%28Tipler%29"&gt;Omega Point&lt;/a&gt;. And I have some anti-reductionist complaints that I doubt anyone reading this blog will be very receptive to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But mostly this is bad because it's all so &lt;em&gt;banal&lt;/em&gt;. Put a group of freshmen in a room with a copy of &lt;em&gt;Principles of Philosophy&lt;/em&gt;, the first &lt;em&gt;Matrix&lt;/em&gt; movie and a dime bag and you'll get pretty much the same thing (including the overly-cute World of Warcraft reference).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amazingly, this is actually only the second-worst science article I've recently read. Check out &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/technology/6945732.stm"&gt;the BBC's coverage of an amazing new &amp;quot;paper battery&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt; — a carbon-nanotube-based technology from Rensselaer that made Slashdot's frontpage yesterday. The writeup is bold enough to include a &amp;quot;How a paper battery works&amp;quot; graphic without actually demonstrating any evidence that the admittedly paper-based technology could be used as a battery. The article mentions voltage, but nothing about capacity. Neither does the original press release upon which it's based, which ought to be a red flag to anyone who took AP Physics and/or has wondered why we use batteries despite the existence of capacitors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This looks like an awful lot like a novel capacitor and nothing more. I seriously doubt it can store a fraction as much charge as even the cheapest chemical cell on sale at the nearest drugstore. Carbon nanotube ultracapacitors may become a useful technology someday, but we're nowhere near replacing the lithium batteries in your mobile electronics with them. But you'd never know from the article that this technology's energy-storage applications will likely be limited to digital watches... maybe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can only think of two reasons why science coverage is so awful, neither of which is particularly original, but both of which I can't resist repeating. First, there's obviously the question of expertise — journalists need to be generalists. Even when they consult an informed party for a quote, they may not trust that source's judgment about what makes (or fails to make) the story newsworthy — they just see &amp;quot;possible applications include curing cancer and humanity's lack of heat-vision&amp;quot; on the press release and decide to run with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, and more evident in the Tierney article, I suspect, is the industry's willingness to let science fans like Gregg Easterbrook pursue their hobby on their employer's dime (and newsprint) after proving themselves in some other journalistic area. I can't blame these writers for trying this — I'd do the same thing if I were in their position, and probably embarrass myself just as often. But the expertise problem must frequently stop their editors from exerting enough influence on the result.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE:&lt;/strong&gt; Tim Lee also thinks Tierney's article is &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://feeds.feedburner.com/~r/techliberation/~3/144497653/042679.php"&gt;pretty lame&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE 2:&lt;/strong&gt; BoingBoing has &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.boingboing.net/2007/08/15/hans_moravec_on_livi.html"&gt;posted&lt;/a&gt; a letter in which the writer implies that Dr. Bostrom is ripping off a 90s sci-fi author who used a similar premise in one of his stories. That seems extremely unlikely to me, but I do think it's good further evidence of how obvious the idea is.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="science"/></entry><entry><title>the chemical basis of karma</title><link href="/2007/06/20/the-chemical-basis-of-karma/" rel="alternate"/><published>2007-06-20T15:31:00-04:00</published><updated>2007-06-20T15:31:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2007-06-20:/2007/06/20/the-chemical-basis-of-karma/</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://neurophilosophy.wordpress.com/2007/06/20/eating-foie-gras-may-increase-risk-of-alzheimers/"&gt;Eating foie gras may increase your risk of Alzheimerâ€™s&lt;/a&gt;. Still, this could be for the best if the first neurons to go are the ones that allow us to feel empathy for geese.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="science"/></entry><entry><title>blogospheric cross-pollination</title><link href="/2007/06/08/blogospheric-cross-pollination/" rel="alternate"/><published>2007-06-08T11:41:00-04:00</published><updated>2007-06-08T11:41:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2007-06-08:/2007/06/08/blogospheric-cross-pollination/</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Via &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://science.slashdot.org/article.pl?sid=07/06/08/1414244&amp;amp;from=rss"&gt;Slashdot&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://arstechnica.com/articles/culture/ars-takes-a-field-trip-the-creation-museum.ars"&gt;Ars Technica takes a trip to the Creationist Museum&lt;/a&gt;. There's a nice Flickr set of the trip &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/drjonboyg/sets/72157600301874014/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't know... Between the relatively high production values and the tantalizing promise of Triceratops rides, I think they make a pretty good case.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="science"/></entry><entry><title>another victory for talking out of my ass</title><link href="/2007/04/27/another-victory-for-talking-out-of-my-ass/" rel="alternate"/><published>2007-04-27T17:35:00-04:00</published><updated>2007-04-27T17:35:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2007-04-27:/2007/04/27/another-victory-for-talking-out-of-my-ass/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Scientists &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.latimes.com/news/la-sci-bees26apr26,0,7437491.story?track=mostviewed-storylevel"&gt;say&lt;/a&gt; the bees are probably dying from a fungus, possibly in combination with a virus. They're also optimistic about it being treatable with antibiotics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Beekeeper: Now listen bees, you've got to take the &lt;em&gt;entire bottle&lt;/em&gt;. Don't stop just because you're feeling better.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Bees: [DEAFENING BUZZ]&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Beekeeper: Alright then.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Via …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Scientists &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.latimes.com/news/la-sci-bees26apr26,0,7437491.story?track=mostviewed-storylevel"&gt;say&lt;/a&gt; the bees are probably dying from a fungus, possibly in combination with a virus. They're also optimistic about it being treatable with antibiotics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Beekeeper: Now listen bees, you've got to take the &lt;em&gt;entire bottle&lt;/em&gt;. Don't stop just because you're feeling better.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Bees: [DEAFENING BUZZ]&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Beekeeper: Alright then.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Via Slashdot.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="science"/></entry><entry><title>two neuroscience links</title><link href="/2007/04/18/two-neuroscience-links/" rel="alternate"/><published>2007-04-18T13:35:00-04:00</published><updated>2007-04-18T13:35:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2007-04-18:/2007/04/18/two-neuroscience-links/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;First, a discussion of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://neurophilosophy.wordpress.com/2007/04/16/diagnosing-dostoyevskys-epilepsy/"&gt;Dostoyevsky's epilepsy&lt;/a&gt;. I haven't got much to add; it's interesting stuff, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.spectrum.ieee.org/apr07/4982/1"&gt;this article on Numenta&lt;/a&gt;, the brain-like computing startup from one of the guys behind Palm and Treo. I'd read &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.wired.com/wired/archive/15.03/hawkins.html"&gt;this Wired article&lt;/a&gt; on the startup a little while ago. What they're doing is …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;First, a discussion of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://neurophilosophy.wordpress.com/2007/04/16/diagnosing-dostoyevskys-epilepsy/"&gt;Dostoyevsky's epilepsy&lt;/a&gt;. I haven't got much to add; it's interesting stuff, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.spectrum.ieee.org/apr07/4982/1"&gt;this article on Numenta&lt;/a&gt;, the brain-like computing startup from one of the guys behind Palm and Treo. I'd read &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.wired.com/wired/archive/15.03/hawkins.html"&gt;this Wired article&lt;/a&gt; on the startup a little while ago. What they're doing is interesting, and I'm sure they've got some very smart people working for them. But in both articles Hawkins takes pains to poo-poo neural networks as a failed AI technology, and to distance his own &amp;quot;HTMs&amp;quot; from them. Yet after reading the descriptions of his technology (and the training and parameter-tuning it requires) and accounts of the sorts of tasks that HTMs can perform, the tech sounds a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; like multilayer &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Perceptron"&gt;perceptrons&lt;/a&gt;. The dog-identifying tasks he points to are really just a more advanced case of the sorts of problems they had us solve in Intro to Neural Networks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm all for moving beginner toolkits out of Matlab and into the open source world — I'm excited about Numenta, and hope it does well. But there's no reason to put down the accomplishments of those who came before you when what you're doing seems to be a variation on the techniques they pioneered.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="science"/></entry></feed>