<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Tom Lee - tech</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/feeds/tech.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>https://tomlee.wtf/</id><updated>2012-05-15T18:44:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>unsolicited advice</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2012/05/15/unsolicited-advice/" rel="alternate"/><published>2012-05-15T18:44:00-04:00</published><updated>2012-05-15T18:44:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2012-05-15:/2012/05/15/unsolicited-advice/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Will Wilkinson is &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.economist.com/blogs/democracyinamerica/2012/04/technology-politics-and-hope"&gt;too kind to me&lt;/a&gt;, but too cruel in general:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
[The] hyperventilating false drama about never-delivered transformative change is by no means unique to the tech beat. Here on the politics blogs, we're only too happy to remind our readers that every coming election is the most important …&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Will Wilkinson is &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.economist.com/blogs/democracyinamerica/2012/04/technology-politics-and-hope"&gt;too kind to me&lt;/a&gt;, but too cruel in general:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
[The] hyperventilating false drama about never-delivered transformative change is by no means unique to the tech beat. Here on the politics blogs, we're only too happy to remind our readers that every coming election is the most important election in a generation, that the fate of our civilisation depends upon which of two barely discernible politicians' cronies get paid. If we can't generate a narrative with live-or-die stakes out of meaningless developments in public-opinion polls, then we've got nothing worthwhile to offer. Reflecting too often upon the ultimate triviality of almost everything we write about does no good for technology or politics writers, or for their readers. The illusion that the next thing will be truly meaningful has always meant more to us than the reality of the next thing. I agree with Mr Lee that there is something quite sad in the way Mr Madrigal, after having discovered that he has been reporting on nothing of significance, does not then go on to draw the well-warranted conclusion that he has wasted some of the best years of his youth foolishly yammering on about ephemera, but instead doubles down and declares &amp;quot;we all better hope that the iPhone 5 has some crazy surprises in store for us later this year&amp;quot;. But it's only sad because life is sad. Really, why not roll the rock back up the hill?&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am rarely out-gloomed, but I think this is one such instance. So let me present a case for technology being meaningful. I think it's possible! Anyone who knows me can tell you that, contra my somewhat embittered bloggy pronouncements, I love technology. I mess around with Arduino on weekends; I obsessively amass, modchip and then fail to actually play game consoles; I spent my holiday building a programmable array of Christmas lights; and I can put my hand on a Digikey packing slip without leaving my bed (though this last credential is perhaps as much about messiness as it is about geekiness).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The point is that I believe in this stuff. Information technology, in particular, is incredibly powerful and democratically accessible, and I genuinely think it can improve our society. When you see me getting upset about the tech industry, it's because I feel that others have lost sight of this. They're making this inspiring thing I love into a silly business school game, or they're making ignorant promises -- on my behalf, it feels like! -- about things they don't understand and which won't ever come to pass. Loudmouths are distracting from good work done humbly. Fuck those guys; I hate 'em. I wish they would shut up and go away. But since they won't, we might as well get on with things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're someone with technical skills, hopefully you you will prove to be better at ignoring those people than I have. Aside from that, I'd like to talk about the ways that I feel a career making technology can be meaningful. Because I really do believe it's possible; I would hate the people who know me, who work with me, to read this blog and conclude that I feel otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not, mind you, that your job has to define you. There's nothing wrong with doing an honest day's work and coming home to enjoy your family, or partner, or dog. Pick up a hobby. Enjoy your vacations. In a few short decades you will only exist as the memories of your loved ones. A few more and you'll be nothing more than a couple of kilobytes in the Mormons' genealogical databases. I wish I had a better deal to offer, but by all accounts history is relentless, and it seems assured that rocking back and forth muttering/tweeting about &amp;quot;innovation&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;disruption&amp;quot; will be no charm against it. The important thing is to try not to waste the time you have on stupid bullshit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I should warn you: this will be grandiose and sappy. To wit:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="improve-the-world"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Improve the World&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yes, the hi-tech, still-quite-expensive things that you build will mostly be used by rich people. That's just a for-now thing, though. Smartphone adoption is already better than home broadband penetration. Speaking &lt;em&gt;very&lt;/em&gt; conservatively, in two generations, everyone in America will be using this technology. In four, I'd bet on everyone in the world using it. And in the meantime, you can push on the decisionmakers. Correcting asymmetries of information can ameliorate asymmetries of power, despite &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://gurstein.wordpress.com/2010/09/02/open-data-empowering-the-empowered-or-effective-data-use-for-everyone/"&gt;the occasional troublingly counterintuitive result&lt;/a&gt;. Look at what &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://publiclaboratory.org/home"&gt;Public Laboratory&lt;/a&gt; is doing: democratizing technology to make it possible for ordinary people to monitor and -- hopefully -- legally defend the quality of their environment. I'm admittedly biased, but I find their work incredibly inspiring.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of efficiency gains are made possible by better information -- &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.greenbuttondata.org/"&gt;dynamic energy pricing systems&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://relayrides.com/"&gt;car&lt;/a&gt;- and &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://toronto.bixi.com/corporate/bixi-corpo"&gt;bike&lt;/a&gt;-sharing fleets, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.nest.com/"&gt;programmable thermostats&lt;/a&gt;. Information technology has a real role to play in keeping the earth habitable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But you don't have to know anything about IR filters or weather balloons or Arduino to make a difference. Designing a webform that serves the needs of some fraction of a social worker's clients, freeing resources for others: that's work that isn't flashy, but is truly important. By way of example, my friend Chris helped build a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.mixmarket.org/"&gt;clearinghouse of performance data for the microfinance sector&lt;/a&gt;, and though I know the day-to-day development experience was nearly indistinguishable from any other CMS-project-hell, it still seems to me a very fine thing to have done. I'm sure that toiling on the EHR problem is even more mind-numbing, and yet it's unquestionably of huge potential importance. Writing a line of code can feel very distant from the act of directly alleviating human suffering, but that distance is and will continue to shrink.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="create-knowledge"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Create Knowledge&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The callowness and innumeracy of those promoting the Big Data brand almost defies belief, but (I should remind myself more frequently) it's important not to let this distort your perspective. Yes, there are dopes who don't understand that a properly selected sample of their (inevitably clickstream or social media) data could get them the same &amp;quot;insights&amp;quot; (always insights) as their massive Hadoop infrastructure. Plus it would let them use scientific-looking error bars, which I bet they would enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there really are problems in need of solving which are bigger than human cognition. The gulf between the people who think their FitBits will extend their lifespan and the people working on actual computational biology problems is vast, but those willing to traverse it should be celebrated. There are archives to be digitized, regressions to be run, extraterrestrial radio signals to be processed. There are &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://groups.google.com/d/msg/superfastmatch/duzeewx_7-0/pzCqzFVtxxgJ"&gt;more disciplines than I can imagine&lt;/a&gt; that could make use of our skills if only they were introduced to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="make-art"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Make Art&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of this stuff is changing us, and we're going to need to spend some time figuring out how -- particularly as the energies, quantities and general magnitudes of the things we can manipulate grow ever more threateningly huge. Somehow we're going to have to give this old monkey brain the slip.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That would be the pragmatic case, but maybe it's foolish to try to mount one. What better thing could there be to spend your time on than making beauty? Besides, you'd be hard-pressed to read much of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://rhizome.org/"&gt;rhizome.org&lt;/a&gt; or the (now-defunct) &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://new-aesthetic.tumblr.com/"&gt;New Aesthetic Tumblr&lt;/a&gt; or the increasingly philosophically-minded indie game scene and not come away convinced that a bunch of exciting, fast-moving (and yes, somewhat insufferable) conversations are reaching crescendo &lt;em&gt;right now&lt;/em&gt;. It's getting to be the part of the party where you have to shout to be heard, and either everyone will start to dance or there'll be a fight or we'll get up on the roof. &lt;em&gt;Something&lt;/em&gt; interesting is sure to happen -- it probably already is, in fact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="try-at-the-very-least-not-to-hurt-anyone"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Try, At The Very Least, Not To Hurt Anyone&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few subdisciplines that you should probably stay away from. &amp;quot;Neuromarketing,&amp;quot; Zynga-style games, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.wired.com/epicenter/2012/04/ff_klout/"&gt;Klout scores&lt;/a&gt; and other algorithmic approaches to eliminating human agency, dignity and/or equality strike me as basically evil, and though the trend they represent is probably unstoppable, I sure wouldn't want to be associated with it. Ditto becoming one of the quants designing the HFT engines of tomorrow, or one of the parasites that make their living off of SEO.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the more benign/less high-skill end of the spectrum, coupon sites are starting to look less like a positive-sum marketing interaction and more like a system for skimming small businesses' revenue. This model has been deployed to arguably good effect in the past (newspapers! Gmail!), but this latter phase seems to merely be subsidizing my fellow yuppies' lifestyles in a sort of bizarrely regressive retail sales tax scheme. If you have the economic freedom to choose, I'm confident that you'll be able to find something more productive to do with your time and talents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="if-you-absolutely-must-play-the-startup-game"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;If You Absolutely Must Play The Startup Game&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understand that you're unlikely to come up with a million dollar idea solely by sticking together free software like so many legos, hoping that lightning will strike and you'll wake up to a valuable population of users who are now pleasantly locked into your product by network effects and/or transition costs. Sure, it happens -- for now, Instagram still counts as an example rather than a punchline -- but a lotto ticket offers only slightly worse odds, and requires you to spend much less time fiddling with Keynote. It's simply too easy for other, smarter people to have the same idea and build it. Competitive markets are good for consumers and bad for entrepreneurs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if the startup dream compels you, I would suggest two things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, realize that ICT makes information cheaper. That's it, really. If you want to earn money with this technology, you should look for tractable problem areas where information is still expensive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, connect your project to the logistical nightmare that is the real world. Ship physical goods, install a bikesharing fleet, go meet with the bureaucracy to get the data you need for your business intelligence site. These things are hard to do without leaving the house (or at least picking up the phone), and consequently fewer of them are being done. Another handy heuristic bucket: pursue ideas that require capital for things other than loft space, foosball tables and your bar tab. The low hanging fruit has been plucked, in other words. Reach higher. It'll certainly be more interesting, and you might even improve your odds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="i-m-a-lucky-guy"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;I'm a Lucky Guy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've already copped to not being a startup guy myself. I guess I should probably acknowledge that I'm not a particularly cheerful person, either. But while I have admittedly made some terrible decisions, my professional choices haven't been half bad, if I do say so myself. I'm extremely grateful to have the opportunity I do: one that affords me the chance to do work that I count as meaningful across a couple of the above dimensions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can't guarantee you'll have the good fortune I've had in finding a fulfilling way to spend your workdays, but I do wish you luck at not wasting your time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="tech"/></entry><entry><title>big data and doing big things</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2011/07/22/big-data-and-doing-big-things/" rel="alternate"/><published>2011-07-22T10:23:00-04:00</published><updated>2011-07-22T10:23:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2011-07-22:/2011/07/22/big-data-and-doing-big-things/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Spencer is &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://spencerackerman.typepad.com/attackerman/2011/07/nexus-7.html"&gt;right&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.wired.com/dangerroom/2011/07/darpas-secret-spy-machine/all/1"&gt;this Wired piece about DARPA's Nexus 7 initiative is very good&lt;/a&gt;. Nexus 7 is an ambitious data processing effort meant to synthesize both traditional signals (e.g. vehicle tracking data) and unorthodox signals (market fruit prices seem to be their favorite example) into useful intelligence through sophisticated …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Spencer is &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://spencerackerman.typepad.com/attackerman/2011/07/nexus-7.html"&gt;right&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.wired.com/dangerroom/2011/07/darpas-secret-spy-machine/all/1"&gt;this Wired piece about DARPA's Nexus 7 initiative is very good&lt;/a&gt;. Nexus 7 is an ambitious data processing effort meant to synthesize both traditional signals (e.g. vehicle tracking data) and unorthodox signals (market fruit prices seem to be their favorite example) into useful intelligence through sophisticated analytic techniques taken from the social sciences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it's a pretty good reminder of why I'm wary of the Big Data movement. &amp;nbsp;These were my two favorite bits:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the surface, there wasn’t much to it: just a graph of violence in the Jalalabad region, and a plot of those fruit prices. When the level of violence was stable — reliably low, or reliably high — so were those prices. Fruit sellers knew what to expect. But when there were sudden swings in the number of attacks, the prices shot up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore, the Nexus 7 team said, you could use the fruit as an indirect indicator of instability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reaction was less than rapturous.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Right from the start, I’m like: Oh. My. God,” one of the people who attended a Nexus 7 presentation tells Danger Room. “A high school kid could do that.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Afterward, Dugan presented the pilot as a triumph — a “big breakthrough” that impressed a bevy of four-star generals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Privately, she was underwhelmed. Dugan was looking for projects that could save troops’ lives, and maybe even bend the direction of the war. By that standard, fruit-price swings seemed pretty inconsequential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the presenters maintained an aura of confidence. Oh, this is just a test. Give us more data sources, they said, and we’ll make better connections. We’ve got the hardware: a cloud computing platform that would soak up all kinds of classified and open source intelligence data. We’ve got the software: these social science PhDs and counterinsurgency veterans, who can figure out how to apply that data to rebuild Afghanistan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&amp;quot;One assumed there was some secret mound of data to be exploited. But it’s just not true.&amp;quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've fallen prey to this temptation: thinking that your mastery of &lt;em&gt;awesome tools&lt;/em&gt; means you're about to do some &lt;em&gt;awesome stuff&lt;/em&gt; (perhaps via some cleverly counterintuitive Freakonomic insight). Unfortunately, it's not that easy. You actually need to have a great idea before great things will happen, and it's difficult to come up with great ideas unless you both know and care -- deeply -- about the topic you're planning to examine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's important to acknowledge that the story of Nexus 7 seems to be told, to some extent, from the perspective of people in the military establishment who feel insulted or threatened by the project. &amp;nbsp;But that in itself is telling: it's never a good idea to enter a field of inquiry with the assumption that those who preceded you were well-meaning simpletons -- particularly when your reasons for thinking so boil down to a difference in the complexity of your tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this same story is about to unfold in the tech industry, albeit with a more cheerful tone. &amp;nbsp;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.readwriteweb.com/archives/jobs_for_data_scientists_explode_across_the_market.php"&gt;Consider this recent post from Read Write Web about the explosion in job listings mentioning the phrase &amp;quot;data scientist&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&amp;quot;Right now, everybody with data knows that there's value in there, that they should be doing something,&amp;quot; says Edd Dumbill, program chair for&amp;nbsp;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://strataconf.com/"&gt;Strata&lt;/a&gt;, O'Reilly's new conference on Data.&amp;nbsp;&amp;quot;Trouble is, nobody's entirely clear on the next steps, but they do know that a data scientist can help frame questions and transform data into useful insight.&amp;quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They don't &amp;quot;know&amp;quot; this. They're assuming it. &amp;nbsp;And this leaves me worried, because the ability to draw meaning from mountains of information is almost always going to depend on the specific question being examined more so than the tools being used or the investigator's level of enthusiasm for the idea of quantitative analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's not that I don't believe in the techniques and tools that have these folks so excited. &amp;nbsp;It's not even that I think nothing will come of data-rich firms applying quantitative analytic techniques. These things have got me excited, too! &amp;nbsp;I'm trying to make sure we take advantage of the same kinds of tools at work. &amp;nbsp;Still, there's no substitute for good ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, this wave of hype doesn't seem much different from the one that occurred at the start of the last decade. &amp;nbsp;&amp;quot;Look at the power of webservers and online payment processing!&amp;quot; we exclaimed. &amp;quot;Can you imagine the benefits they'll yield when applied to the problem of selling pet food?&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those things &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; powerful. But that's beside the point.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="tech"/></entry><entry><title>shell scripts work better than giant puppets</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2010/12/13/shell-scripts-work-better-than-giant-puppets/" rel="alternate"/><published>2010-12-13T12:10:00-05:00</published><updated>2010-12-13T12:10:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2010-12-13:/2010/12/13/shell-scripts-work-better-than-giant-puppets/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;There were two good pieces on NPR this morning discussing the reaction to Wikileaks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, there's &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.npr.org/2010/12/13/131979010/corporations-are-drawn-into-wikileaks-controversy"&gt;this story&lt;/a&gt;, which briefly gets at some of the concerns about Twitter as a platform for activism that I tried to express in &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.prospect.org/cs/articles?article=the_cost_of_hashtag_revolution"&gt;this piece&lt;/a&gt;. The point Shirky makes is an important one: so …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;There were two good pieces on NPR this morning discussing the reaction to Wikileaks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, there's &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.npr.org/2010/12/13/131979010/corporations-are-drawn-into-wikileaks-controversy"&gt;this story&lt;/a&gt;, which briefly gets at some of the concerns about Twitter as a platform for activism that I tried to express in &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.prospect.org/cs/articles?article=the_cost_of_hashtag_revolution"&gt;this piece&lt;/a&gt;. The point Shirky makes is an important one: so much vital expression now happens in privately-controlled mediums that nominal speech rights are often a bit beside the point. This, combined with the fact that we seem to be relitigating the &amp;quot;should shield laws apply to bloggers?&amp;quot; question, makes me think that we're collectively more confused about how you can and ought to be able to speak on the internet than I would've expected. Hopefully we'll muddle our way through to a productive conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, they did a piece &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.npr.org/2010/12/13/132015315/as-u-s-hunts-hacktivists-some-ask-is-it-worth-it"&gt;discussing the costs of prosecuting participants in Operation Payback&lt;/a&gt;, and it's also worth a read. I'm sympathetic to the basic dilemma: going after the participants is a lot like calling in Interpol for a vandalism case. Individual actors are only responsible for substantial damage when considered together; and nobody's very happy about the idea of locking up bored rich kids. Still, it's worth keeping in mind that &lt;em&gt;this is what a hard computer crime problem looks like&lt;/em&gt;. It's not thrilling to me to read that the FBI and DOJ are basically shrugging their shoulders and saying, &amp;quot;Eh, that sounds too hard.&amp;quot; This is all the more galling when these agencies &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; bothering to pursue computer crime enforcement agendas around intellectual property. Like it or not, distributed international attacks are the class of problem most in need of solving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One other thing I'd add: keep an eye on how useful the &amp;quot;cybersecurity&amp;quot; community makes itself during this process. My guess is that they'll keep their traps shut (or at least spend their time gleefully fretting about what kind of funding requests Stuxnet will necessitate) while the &amp;quot;computer security&amp;quot; community does the hard work of grappling with the Operation Payback DDoS. On the other hand, I suppose the cybersec guys were probably the ones behind DDoSing Wikileaks, so, y'know, your tax dollars at work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third: about that DDoS. I'm not sure what to say about it, really. I find the argument that it &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.cpeterson.org/2009/07/21/in-praise-of-some-ddoss/"&gt;can be considered civil disobedience&lt;/a&gt; to be more compelling than I would've expected. I'm somewhat sympathetic to arguments like the one &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://timothyblee.com/2010/12/10/the-case-against-ddos/"&gt;Tim makes here&lt;/a&gt; (or that's discussed in &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.deannazandt.com/2010/12/12/legitimate-civil-disobedience-wikileaks-and-the-layers-of-backlash/comment-page-1/#comment-46538"&gt;this comment&lt;/a&gt;). But I think the idea that past instances of civil disobedience were done in an orderly manner by uniformly thoughtful people who did their best not to inconvenience anyone else is probably wishful thinking. I'm no expert on this stuff, but that strikes me as the sort of perceptual shift that happens after a movement is vindicated by history. You're going to have to piss some people off. Otherwise you might as well go schedule a protest march for all the good it'll do you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And although I'm not particularly sympathetic to Payback's targeting of Amazon — cowardly though the firm's behavior may have been, too many others rely on the AWS infrastructure, and there are plenty of hosts out there — the payment-processing and DNS control points now being counter-attacked by Operation Payback really do represent worrying concentrations of power. These systems are controlled by entities that are immune to public oversight, yet seem to be completely compliant when state agents ask them to restrict their customers' liberty. That's a recipe that should worry libertarians a lot more than it seems to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, there's Gawker. And although it's probably a mistake to conflate all of these actors, there do seem to be some connections. The &amp;quot;Anonymous&amp;quot; community is becoming a sort of petulant digital Fight Club that's going to be very difficult to combat, and which behaves in a chaotic and unprincipled manner. That they're targeting those who &lt;em&gt;dare to talk about them&lt;/em&gt; is pretty dismaying; that the only way to respond seems likely to be a combination of quiet state cooption of ISPs and throwing children in jail — that's incredibly depressing.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="tech"/></entry><entry><title>a charlatan-friendly ecosystem</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2010/09/26/a-charlatan-friendly-ecosystem/" rel="alternate"/><published>2010-09-26T16:04:00-04:00</published><updated>2010-09-26T16:04:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2010-09-26:/2010/09/26/a-charlatan-friendly-ecosystem/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Alex Payne &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://twitter.com/al3x/status/25614922261"&gt;points&lt;/a&gt; to a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.links.org/?p=998&amp;amp;utm_source=feedburner&amp;amp;utm_medium=feed&amp;amp;utm_campaign=Feed%3A+links%2FZvUZ+%28Ben+Laurie+Blathering%29"&gt;blog post by Ben Laurie&lt;/a&gt; that discusses Diaspora and Haystack, and how projects like these can attract huge amounts of press, only to flame out as their charismatic founders' incompetence is revealed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I agree with Ben's post, but it's worth being a bit more explicit …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Alex Payne &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://twitter.com/al3x/status/25614922261"&gt;points&lt;/a&gt; to a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.links.org/?p=998&amp;amp;utm_source=feedburner&amp;amp;utm_medium=feed&amp;amp;utm_campaign=Feed%3A+links%2FZvUZ+%28Ben+Laurie+Blathering%29"&gt;blog post by Ben Laurie&lt;/a&gt; that discusses Diaspora and Haystack, and how projects like these can attract huge amounts of press, only to flame out as their charismatic founders' incompetence is revealed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I agree with Ben's post, but it's worth being a bit more explicit about what allows these situations to arise: the quality of most tech journalism is abysmal. I mean really inexcusably bad. Mainstream publications regularly assign writers to cover the software industry that have a level of understanding regarding the field that would be unacceptable in an intern. The most esteemed practitioners in the tech press are either focused on the consumer electronic user experience or are building personal brands around faith-based tech triumphalist movements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this sort of environment, it should be no surprise that an embarrassing hype cycle can emerge -- one that talented self-promoters will use to enhance their status and wealth. I find it difficult to assign all that much blame to those self-promoters: the whole problem is that &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dunning%E2%80%93Kruger_effect"&gt;they don't know any better&lt;/a&gt;. What more can we expect? Besides, it's very easy to start believing your own bullshit once people with seemingly-meaningful professional credentials start validating it. Self-promoters will self promote; it's not realistic to expect them to be the ones providing diligence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suspect that the problem may have to do with the structure of the industry: if you know much about it, you're probably going to be able to make more money participating in it than writing about it. I don't know enough about finance to really judge, but it seems as though that press sector suffers from a similar systemic disability -- certainly all can agree that the financial press didn't cover itself in glory in advance of the recent financial crisis. Once that story became big enough, talented generalist journalists filtered in and did the job properly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But unless and until the skill premium for the software industry diminishes relative to journalism I'm not sure there's a good way to align incentives in a way that fixes this problem. The best we can do is to recognize that the journalists who wrote excitedly about Haystack and Diaspora made a mistake; they were fooled, and they wasted our time. There's no need to tar and feather anyone, but their credibility needs to suffer if we want this situation to improve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe we don't need it to improve! It's not that important, to be perfectly honest. But it sure does bug the hell out of me.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="tech"/></entry><entry><title>I could use some GMaps help</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2010/06/06/i-could-use-some-gmaps-help/" rel="alternate"/><published>2010-06-06T13:19:00-04:00</published><updated>2010-06-06T13:19:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2010-06-06:/2010/06/06/i-could-use-some-gmaps-help/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Way back when, I wrote a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dcist.com/map/"&gt;Google Maps application&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.dcist.com"&gt;DCist&lt;/a&gt; that overlaid the DC Metro system on the usual GMaps tiles. People found it useful -- me especially, since I think it helped me land a job at &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.echoditto.com"&gt;EchoDitto&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp; Its only real innovation was some simple, hacked-up geometry that would …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Way back when, I wrote a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dcist.com/map/"&gt;Google Maps application&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.dcist.com"&gt;DCist&lt;/a&gt; that overlaid the DC Metro system on the usual GMaps tiles. People found it useful -- me especially, since I think it helped me land a job at &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.echoditto.com"&gt;EchoDitto&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp; Its only real innovation was some simple, hacked-up geometry that would horrify a cartographer, but which allowed me to make an attractive map that recalled &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://wmata.com/rail/maps/map.cfm"&gt;the more stylized WMATA map&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp; It wasn't rocket science, but I still occasionally get emails from developers asking me how I did it (which is slightly bizarre, given that the code is right there for them to see).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In 2007 the GMaps API got an update, and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://dcist.com/2007/07/13/dcist_maps_come.php"&gt;I converted the project into something called a mapplet&lt;/a&gt;. I had to rewrite a few things, but it was more or less the same.&amp;nbsp; The main difference was that mapplets were used through the maps.google.com interface -- you could add a bunch at the same time, but you could still use Local Search and permalinking and comments about businesses and other Googly innovations from within the interface.&amp;nbsp; I didn't have to implement any of that stuff!&amp;nbsp; Instead, users could simply have their polished Google Maps experience supplemented by my modest mapplet.&amp;nbsp; Handy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, over the last few weeks I've started receiving reports that the mapplet's behaving weirdly.&amp;nbsp; Load the mapplet, then do a search for something -- the station markers will disappear, and sometimes some of the lines that are supposed to connect them will, too.&amp;nbsp; It looked to me like an event handler had started working differently, so I went to investigate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alas!&amp;nbsp; It turns out that v2 of the API has been deprecated.&amp;nbsp; They're on to v3 (not so bad) and they've discontinued the mapplet platform entirely (bad)!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can still make the lines appear on a Google Map.&amp;nbsp; But I don't think I can do it on the maps.google.com interface.&amp;nbsp; This is a drag: I don't think the thing's half as useful as a standalone product as it is when it supplements search functionality.&amp;nbsp; And I really don't want to reimplement the entire maps.google.com interface (even though, yes, they expose the API for their local search stuff).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So! Developers! Anyone out there dealt with this? I'm not eager to dump a huge amount of time back into this project -- a project that's increasingly unnecessary thanks to Google Transit and the addition of transit stations to the GMaps tileset, but which is still useful when you're working at a modestly wide zoom level.&amp;nbsp; But it would be nice to get things working again.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="tech"/></entry><entry><title>browser warnings</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2010/03/18/browser-warnings/" rel="alternate"/><published>2010-03-18T14:23:00-04:00</published><updated>2010-03-18T14:23:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2010-03-18:/2010/03/18/browser-warnings/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://motherjones.com/kevin-drum/2010/03/you-and-your-browser"&gt;Kevin Drum elects to take security advice from Microsoft&lt;/a&gt;. This is not a good idea!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a nutshell: MS says that users ignore warnings about unsigned encryption keys, which makes those warnings useless.&amp;nbsp; Some browsers, like Firefox, make it &lt;em&gt;really difficult&lt;/em&gt; to ignore unsigned keys, but that's annoying, and MS …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://motherjones.com/kevin-drum/2010/03/you-and-your-browser"&gt;Kevin Drum elects to take security advice from Microsoft&lt;/a&gt;. This is not a good idea!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a nutshell: MS says that users ignore warnings about unsigned encryption keys, which makes those warnings useless.&amp;nbsp; Some browsers, like Firefox, make it &lt;em&gt;really difficult&lt;/em&gt; to ignore unsigned keys, but that's annoying, and MS says we should abandon such efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is wrong.&amp;nbsp; Those warnings are saying: &amp;quot;The URL you entered means that you've asked for a snoop-proof connection, so okay, your connection to this server is encrypted; however, &lt;em&gt;I can't verify that this server is who it's claiming to be&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;quot;&amp;nbsp; Your conversation with the server will be private, but you could be subject to a so-called man-in-the-middle attack, whereby someone hijacks the local network segment you're on and starts speaking on behalf of, say, bankofamerica.com.&amp;nbsp; The magic of the certificate authority system means that they can't do this without generating a warning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is one caveat: if they simply don't try to use encryption, the warning won't be generated.&amp;nbsp; This is one of the reasons why you're supposed to check for &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://"&gt;https://&lt;/a&gt; in the URL whenever you submit sensitive information; not just so that your password isn't available to everyone else on the Bolt Bus (though that's a good reason, too), but also so that anyone pretending to be a server they're not will get caught.&amp;nbsp; Unfortunately, people aren't very good at checking for that little s in the URL or that little key icon or whatever other little security indicator your browser provides, so the bad guys just direct their victims to unsecured sites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's too bad, but it isn't a sign that warnings about unsigned keys are bad ideas.&amp;nbsp; Actually, the fact that phishers have drifted away from that link in the security chain means that &lt;em&gt;it's working properly&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;nbsp; Weakening it isn't any kind of solution.&amp;nbsp; MS security researchers would be better-served by spending more time thinking about how to get people to notice when they ought to be using a secure site.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="tech"/></entry><entry><title>engineering only seems cool after the fact</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2010/03/16/engineering-only-seems-cool-after-the-fact/" rel="alternate"/><published>2010-03-16T13:03:00-04:00</published><updated>2010-03-16T13:03:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2010-03-16:/2010/03/16/engineering-only-seems-cool-after-the-fact/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.prospect.org/cs/articles?article=the_curated_web"&gt;The American Prospect&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://chneukirchen.org/trivium/2010-03-16"&gt;Trivium&lt;/a&gt;!&amp;nbsp; Worlds colliding!&amp;nbsp; It's great!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read the article, though, and found myself disagreeing with its author, Marisa Meltzer.&amp;nbsp; How can you provide an accounting of Tumblr's success and not use the word &amp;quot;Gawker&amp;quot; once?&amp;nbsp; The service was launched in New York in the right kind …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.prospect.org/cs/articles?article=the_curated_web"&gt;The American Prospect&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://chneukirchen.org/trivium/2010-03-16"&gt;Trivium&lt;/a&gt;!&amp;nbsp; Worlds colliding!&amp;nbsp; It's great!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read the article, though, and found myself disagreeing with its author, Marisa Meltzer.&amp;nbsp; How can you provide an accounting of Tumblr's success and not use the word &amp;quot;Gawker&amp;quot; once?&amp;nbsp; The service was launched in New York in the right kind of scene, was pitched in the right kind of way, attracted the right kind of writers, and grew from there. Like so many successful products, you can't simply run Tumblr's featureset backward through the perfectly-deterministic mechanism of the imagined market and arrive at a proper accounting of why it succeeded and its competitors failed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I agree that it's worth talking about the subtle mechanics of the site -- how there's a thumbs-up mechanism but no thumbs-down; I think the consolidation of reader and blog into a single form is a genuinely interesting idea. But Meltzer's account seemed to me a bit like explaining the success of the iPod via a discussion of its clickwheel.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="tech"/></entry><entry><title>another day, another bad WaPo op-ed</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2009/09/28/another-day-another-bad-wapo-op-ed/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-09-28T12:51:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-09-28T12:51:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2009-09-28:/2009/09/28/another-day-another-bad-wapo-op-ed/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's hardly worth noting, but &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2009/09/27/AR2009092703026.html"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; is a lousy editorial.&amp;nbsp; A couple of points, one of which I buried in the last post about net neutrality:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Comcast's reversal of its decision to fiddle with Bittorrent seems to be getting bandied about as an example of the market taking care of …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It's hardly worth noting, but &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/content/article/2009/09/27/AR2009092703026.html"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; is a lousy editorial.&amp;nbsp; A couple of points, one of which I buried in the last post about net neutrality:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Comcast's reversal of its decision to fiddle with Bittorrent seems to be getting bandied about as an example of the market taking care of things. People should be less sanguine: it was not market pressure from clients but rather PR pressure from activists that forced Comcast to back down.&amp;nbsp; And if the net neutrality issue hadn't been looming at the time, the outcome could easily have been different.&amp;nbsp; Mustering that level of coordinated outrage is not a sustainable model for policing ISP behavior.&amp;nbsp; Other ISPs offer evidence of gloomier scenarios: in Canada, Rogers has been throttling Bittorrent -- and, in fact, all encrypted traffic, since it can't distinguish encrypted BT from encrypted anything-else -- since at least 2005.&amp;nbsp; Similar difficulties face customers of some Australian ISPs.&amp;nbsp; And there are other policies that have been in place so long that people have stopped complaining: unless something has changed, I'm still prohibited from running a server for personal use off my home connection (in principle a server of any type; in practice, port 80 is the only one that will be caught). And it was years -- years! -- before Comcast disclosed or even acknowledged the existence of its secret bandwidth caps.&amp;nbsp; Neutrality opponents are mistaking a single victorious battle for the absence of a war.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Post piece refers to the broadband market as &amp;quot;a vibrant and well-functioning marketplace&amp;quot;. In truth, it's &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.dslreports.com/shownews/Global-Broadband-Prices-Plummet-98942"&gt;stagnated&lt;/a&gt;: in North America, prices remain steady -- at a rate above what much of the developed world pays -- while ongoing improvements in speed show little hope for of catching up with the networks of countries significantly poorer than the US.&amp;nbsp; If the Post wants to argue that net neutrality will make the situation even worse, fine. But they don't even seem to realize that by global standards our domestic broadband marketplace is an underperformer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content><category term="tech"/></entry><entry><title>making Redskins Radio usably portable</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2009/09/10/making-redskins-radio-usably-portable/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-09-10T22:51:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-09-10T22:51:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2009-09-10:/2009/09/10/making-redskins-radio-usably-portable/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Surely any Redskins fan will agree that foremost among Dan Snyder's sins is his selection of a broadcast outlet that only provides its audio stream in Flash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See, I'm going to be heading back from Philly this Sunday, and many Sundays besides, and I'd rather not miss the whole goddamn …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Surely any Redskins fan will agree that foremost among Dan Snyder's sins is his selection of a broadcast outlet that only provides its audio stream in Flash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See, I'm going to be heading back from Philly this Sunday, and many Sundays besides, and I'd rather not miss the whole goddamn football season.&amp;nbsp; If WTEM provided an MP3 stream this would be no problem -- the FStream iPhone app would let me listen to the game on stretches of I-95 well beyond the anemic reach of 980 AM.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's not the case, though.&amp;nbsp; WTEM uses a Flash-based streaming system, apparently through a vendor called streamtheworld.com.&amp;nbsp; That's fine for the web browser, but the iPhone's too stupid to deal with Flash.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I set out to provide an alternate stream.&amp;nbsp; Amazon offers on-demand virtual servers through its EC2 service, and my first thought was to fire one of those up for each game.&amp;nbsp; At ten cents an hour it would be affordable, and I could use the more-competent server to transcode the Flash stream into a more iPhone-compatible MP3 stream.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got far enough along this path that I might as well share my work.&amp;nbsp; Here's a quick recipe for setting up a VLC-transcoding-capable server on EC2:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;Launch the following Ubuntu AMI: ami-ed46a784&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;Make sure that you've opened port 8080 in the relevant security settings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;div class="first line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Execute these commands:&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;apt-get -y update&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;apt-get -y install libmp3lame-dev&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;apt-get -y install ffmpeg libavcodec-unstripped-52&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;apt-get -y install vlc vlc-plugin-esd mozilla-plugin-vlc&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;div class="first line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;Execute something similar to, but not quite this:&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;sudo -u nobody vlc -vvv &amp;quot;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://208.80.52.80/WTEMAM"&gt;http://208.80.52.80/WTEMAM&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot; --sout '#transcode{acodec=mp3,ab=64}:standard{access=http,mux=asf,dst=}'&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is close.&amp;nbsp; It's &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; close.&amp;nbsp; If you run this and then load up &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.videolan.org"&gt;VLC&lt;/a&gt; -- the amazingly useful media player -- and connect to the AMI on port 8080, you'll get a 64 kbps transcoded MP3 stream of the WTEM flash audio stream.&amp;nbsp; It works well!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I don't know the specific incantation that makes this MP3 stream compatible with &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://phobos.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewSoftware?id=289892007&amp;amp;mt=8"&gt;FStream&lt;/a&gt; on the iPhone.&amp;nbsp; I tried various playlist formats.&amp;nbsp; I tried various audio formats.&amp;nbsp; I tried various container formats.&amp;nbsp; There doesn't seem to be any decent documentation on the internet telling me what to do.&amp;nbsp; It just says it's connecting, forever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But while searching for a solution I discovered something interesting: there's an iPhone version of VLC!&amp;nbsp; True, it's 13 megs, and yeah, it's only available on jailbroken phones (via the Cydia package manager).&amp;nbsp; But it works great!&amp;nbsp; I pointed it at &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://208.80.52.80/WTEMAM"&gt;http://208.80.52.80/WTEMAM&lt;/a&gt; and it started spitting out incomprehensible sports radio babble almost immediately.&amp;nbsp; Admittedly, that was over wifi.&amp;nbsp; But I see no reason to expect it to perform any worse over 3G than an equivalent MP3 stream would.&amp;nbsp; I'll be giving it a shot on Sunday during the Giants game. And while I'm sorry to not be providing an MP3 stream for other fans, I'm glad to offer another reason to jailbreak your phone.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="tech"/></entry><entry><title>more robots</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2009/08/19/more-robots/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-08-19T14:56:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-08-19T14:56:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2009-08-19:/2009/08/19/more-robots/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Tim &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://timothyblee.com/?p=452"&gt;wades in&lt;/a&gt; to the debate about robots replacing low-skilled workers. I don't think I &lt;a class="reference external" href="/2009/08/09/will-machines-render-low-skilled-workers-useless/"&gt;made my case&lt;/a&gt; as strongly as I could have, and consequently I can't resist responding, if only briefly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I didn't react to the &amp;quot;cost of materials and energy&amp;quot; argument as forcefully as I should have …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Tim &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://timothyblee.com/?p=452"&gt;wades in&lt;/a&gt; to the debate about robots replacing low-skilled workers. I don't think I &lt;a class="reference external" href="/2009/08/09/will-machines-render-low-skilled-workers-useless/"&gt;made my case&lt;/a&gt; as strongly as I could have, and consequently I can't resist responding, if only briefly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I didn't react to the &amp;quot;cost of materials and energy&amp;quot; argument as forcefully as I should have. I really, really, really don't think this is going to be an issue. Machines are &lt;em&gt;much&lt;/em&gt; more efficient than humans -- that's sort of the whole point. It's not at all a subtle difference, but rather a massive leap (they don't call the first sweeping wave of automation a revolution for nothing). The price of technology continues to fall. And the energy costs we're talking about are slight: keeping a Roomba charged takes about &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.treehugger.com/files/2008/12/this-or-that-roomba-versus-upright.php"&gt;a third as much power&lt;/a&gt; as illuminating the lamp on your nightstand -- and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.daviddarling.info/encyclopedia/C/AE_compact_fluorescent_lamp.html"&gt;that's if the lamp is using a compact fluorescent bulb&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tim's discussion of our hardwired preference for other humans is an interesting one. But I'm not sure this is a problem that will be as resistant to engineering as he thinks. Consider &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.japantrendshop.com/paro-robotic-healing-seal-p-144.html"&gt;Paro, the robot seal&lt;/a&gt;. By all accounts he works pretty well at soothing nursing home patients. Tim's probably right that people would prefer -- and pay for -- a human R.N. rather than Rosie the Robot in nursing scrubs. But if a suite of relatively simple assistive technologies is cheaper than either -- partially automated showers, biomonitors, pill reminders and the like -- they'll probably settle for that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Human labor remaining competitive with robots seems to assume that one of two things will happen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, wages for unskilled labor could be pushed even further down. Presumably this is supposed to happen as average income continues to rise. I'm not sure how this can be considered feasible, either practically or ethically -- we're basically talking about reinventing the serf.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, robots could become dramatically less economical due to some sort of resource or energy shock. But given robotic efficiency (and the reality of their still-falling prices), it's hard for me to envision this happening except in the sort of catastrophic scenario in which maintaining human employment levels would be the least of our worries.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="tech"/></entry><entry><title>iphone/nextbus progress</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2009/07/08/iphonenextbus-progress/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-07-08T23:54:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-07-08T23:54:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2009-07-08:/2009/07/08/iphonenextbus-progress/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/sbma44/3702613279/"&gt;&lt;img alt="nextbus on the iphone" class="right" src="http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2673/3702613279_5f14faf8ef_m.jpg" style="width: 133px; height: 240px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Nextbus stops! Served by Google App Engine! Displayed on the iPhone!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The app crashes as soon as you try to do anything after the map loads.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are way too many pins. And I don't want them to be pins anyway. And the stops aren't likely to change …&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/sbma44/3702613279/"&gt;&lt;img alt="nextbus on the iphone" class="right" src="http://farm3.static.flickr.com/2673/3702613279_5f14faf8ef_m.jpg" style="width: 133px; height: 240px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Nextbus stops! Served by Google App Engine! Displayed on the iPhone!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The app crashes as soon as you try to do anything after the map loads.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are way too many pins. And I don't want them to be pins anyway. And the stops aren't likely to change often so I should actually move this operation off the network and onto the iPhone, which might mean reimplementing &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geohash"&gt;geohash&lt;/a&gt;, which I don't yet fully understand (but know to be neat!).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I haven't written code to query Nextbus for predictions. This will be fairly easy, but exactly how I want to handle caching is an open question.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still: wheels, motion, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.S. Objective C suuuuuucks&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="tech"/></entry><entry><title>TCP/IP sanctions</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2009/07/08/tcpip-sanctions/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-07-08T09:45:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-07-08T09:45:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2009-07-08:/2009/07/08/tcpip-sanctions/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;It seems like the Iranian cyberactivist movement has marked the entrance of the term DDoS into our culture's shared vocabulary. There's a big DDoS attack going on right now, in fact: the Post &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://voices.washingtonpost.com/securityfix/2009/07/washington_post_white_house_fa.html?hpid=topnews"&gt;has coverage&lt;/a&gt; (they're among the targets), and I heard a piece about it this morning on NPR …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It seems like the Iranian cyberactivist movement has marked the entrance of the term DDoS into our culture's shared vocabulary. There's a big DDoS attack going on right now, in fact: the Post &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://voices.washingtonpost.com/securityfix/2009/07/washington_post_white_house_fa.html?hpid=topnews"&gt;has coverage&lt;/a&gt; (they're among the targets), and I heard a piece about it this morning on NPR. Governments are among the victims. People are starting to notice that the agencies responsible for dealing with this stuff don't have the power to do much more than write whitepapers. Governments are going to start doing things about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this will likely take two forms:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Legislated standards for ISPs. In particular, I imagine we'll see ports for IRC and SMTP, if not all non-http ports, move to a default-closed state. I'm not sure how you'll opt into opening them, but SMS verification of an online request seems to be increasing in popularity (my bank does this; Google does, too, when you start to use their App Engine service). There'll also likely be incentives or mandates put in place for things like server-side antivirus scanning of email attachments. The details matter quite a lot — the possibility of a corporate power-grab that constrains citizens' ability to interact securely is real — but I think such attacks can be fought off, and the result will probably be a good thing on the whole.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;These ISP standards could conceivably get written into trade agreements, at which point a more politically interesting possibility will arise: the imposition of economic or network sanctions against nations judged to have an out-of-control internet. Is there a damaging DoS attack coming from South Korea? Is that country's government judged not to have adequate standards in place to fight or prevent it? Cut 'em off the network, or throttle their traffic. There's a constituency for this: the WIPO people would be only too happy to have this capability.
This opens up other interesting possibilities. For one thing, the mutually destructive nature of sanctions would become immediately clear to internet users in a way that isn't always obvious in the comparatively sluggish realm of trade. And for another, online false flag operations would become a more serious concern. A hacker group could conceivably blackmail a small, cloutless nation under the threat of eliciting an international network crackdown.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It'll be interesting (and no doubt horrifying) to see deep packet inspection debated on the House floor. I think we're headed that way, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh yeah: let me plug &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.csoonline.com/article/print/220336"&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt;, which is the more entertaining narrative about a DoS attack that I've come across.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="tech"/></entry><entry><title>more NextBussery</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2009/07/06/more-nextbussery/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-07-06T11:10:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-07-06T11:10:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2009-07-06:/2009/07/06/more-nextbussery/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://greatergreaterwashington.org/post.cgi?id=2807"&gt;GGW points me&lt;/a&gt; toward some &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://sfappeal.com/news/2009/06/who-owns-sfmta-arrival-data.php"&gt;pretty discouraging news about how NextBus has treated other transit app developers&lt;/a&gt;. They assert their copyright on arrival times; they demand licensing agreements, yet refuse to do so on a small scale; and, perhaps most astoundingly, they say that free iPhone apps count as commercial …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://greatergreaterwashington.org/post.cgi?id=2807"&gt;GGW points me&lt;/a&gt; toward some &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://sfappeal.com/news/2009/06/who-owns-sfmta-arrival-data.php"&gt;pretty discouraging news about how NextBus has treated other transit app developers&lt;/a&gt;. They assert their copyright on arrival times; they demand licensing agreements, yet refuse to do so on a small scale; and, perhaps most astoundingly, they say that free iPhone apps count as commercial use of the data because apple sells the iPhone on the strength of the app store's offerings. Ugh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the bright side, the technical aspects of my work on a map-based NextBus iPhone app are proceeding well. At the moment there are no obvious obstacles that need to be overcome. That's not to say those obstacles don't exist — they almost certainly do — but a &lt;em&gt;seemingly&lt;/em&gt; clear path ahead is about the best you can hope for in a technical project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, and I had another look at the GTFS/NextBus stop match-up. The news is still bad. I'd hoped that the average distance between stops was being pulled up by a few bad matches, but that doesn't seem to be the case. In fact there are only about two dozen matched stops closer than 10m from one another. I'll have another look eventually (maybe NextBus is using a different projection system?), but for now the NB dataset is sufficiently complete that I can rely on it for my work.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="tech"/></entry><entry><title>GTFS and NextBus don't match up</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2009/07/01/gtfs-and-nextbus-dont-match-up/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-07-01T22:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-07-01T22:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2009-07-01:/2009/07/01/gtfs-and-nextbus-dont-match-up/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;NextBus launched! It's exciting. I and a lot of other area developers are looking at how to take advantage of the realtime GPS data that NextBus collects to make the DC transit system easier to use. I haven't gotten too far with it — I'm just poking around — but the early …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;NextBus launched! It's exciting. I and a lot of other area developers are looking at how to take advantage of the realtime GPS data that NextBus collects to make the DC transit system easier to use. I haven't gotten too far with it — I'm just poking around — but the early word is that NextBus isn't going to make this easy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First: they're claiming copyright on the location of metrobuses. They serve their data as XML, and each &amp;lt;body&amp;gt; tag looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&amp;lt;body &lt;span class="pre"&gt;copyright=&amp;quot;All&lt;/span&gt; data copyright NextBus 2009. Allowed use is for noncommercial purposes &lt;span class="pre"&gt;only.&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not great. But okay, whatever — whether this data is copyrightable in a meaningful sense is the first question; whether WMATA willingly sold off their bus locations is the second. But realistically, NextBus can apply whatever license terms on their service that they'd like, and can plausibly enforce them against commercial users. So that'd bring us back to where we are, which is fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But just because NextBus says it's &lt;em&gt;okay&lt;/em&gt; to have the data doesn't mean they're going to make it easy. Your browser makes a lot of requests to NextBus in order to show a map, of course, but the most interesting ones are to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://wmata.nextbus.com/service/googleMapXMLFeed"&gt;http://wmata.nextbus.com/service/googleMapXMLFeed&lt;/a&gt;, a script that performs a number of different operations based on what querystring parameters it's passed. For instance, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://wmata.nextbus.com/service/googleMapXMLFeed?command=routeConfig&amp;amp;a=wmata&amp;amp;r=64&amp;amp;key=1424073267381"&gt;http://wmata.nextbus.com/service/googleMapXMLFeed?command=routeConfig&amp;amp;a=wmata&amp;amp;r=64&amp;amp;key=1424073267381&lt;/a&gt; will get you a list of stops and route geometry for the 64 bus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if you paste that URL into your browser, you'll get this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&amp;lt;Error &lt;span class="pre"&gt;shouldRetry=&amp;quot;false&amp;quot;&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;``&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;Feed can only be accessed by NextBus map page.``&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&amp;lt;/Error&amp;gt;&lt;/tt&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Charming. But of course it works in the context of the map. So we need to figure out what the difference is. &lt;a class="reference external" href="/2009/07/01/nextbus_headers.txt"&gt;Here's&lt;/a&gt; a complete conversation between my browser and NextBus. And here's a specific request that worked for that URL:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;http://wmata.nextbus.com/service/googleMapXMLFeed?command=routeConfig&amp;amp;a=wmata&amp;amp;r=64&amp;amp;key=1424073267381&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;GET &lt;span class="pre"&gt;/service/googleMapXMLFeed?command=routeConfig&amp;amp;a=wmata&amp;amp;r=64&amp;amp;key=1424073267381&lt;/span&gt; HTTP/1.1&lt;/tt&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Host: wmata.nextbus.com&lt;/tt&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;User-Agent:&lt;/span&gt; Mozilla/5.0 (Macintosh; U; Intel Mac OS X 10.5; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;en-US;&lt;/span&gt; rv:1.9.0.11) Gecko/2009060214 Firefox/3.0.11&lt;/tt&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Accept: &lt;span class="pre"&gt;text/html,application/xhtml+xml,application/xml;q=0.9,*/*;q=0.8&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;Accept-Language:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;en-us,en;q=0.5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;Accept-Encoding:&lt;/span&gt; gzip,deflate&lt;/tt&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;Accept-Charset:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;ISO-8859-1,utf-8;q=0.7,*;q=0.7&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;Keep-Alive:&lt;/span&gt; 300&lt;/tt&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Connection: &lt;span class="pre"&gt;keep-alive&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Referer: &lt;span class="pre"&gt;http://wmata.nextbus.com/googleMap/customGoogleMap.jsp?a=wmata&amp;amp;cssFile=http://www.wmata.com/css/nextbus.css&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Cookie: userProfile_rev1=wmata|A11|A11_A11_0|7067|8166&amp;amp;wmata|64|64_64_0|16797|7073&amp;amp;wmata|64|64_64_0|6454|16793&amp;amp;; __utma=222659997.501906468.1246378684.1246395595.1246496449.3; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;__utmz=222659997.1246496449.3.3.utmccn=(referral)|utmcsr=wmata.com|utmcct=/rider_tools/nextbus/arrivals.cfm|utmcmd=referral;&lt;/span&gt; userID_rev4=5534021; __utma=64696752.769952994.1246496428.1246496428.1246496428.1; __utmb=64696752; __utmc=64696752; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;__utmz=64696752.1246496428.1.1.utmccn=(organic)|utmcsr=google|utmctr=nextbus+wmata|utmcmd=organic;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;Coyote-2-407c7b2d=c0a80a66:0;&lt;/span&gt; JSESSIONID=53015434E8CF00D3FEC91D4B491FFA08; __utmb=222659997; __utmc=222659997&lt;/tt&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It actually can't be that many things. There's the set of session-maintaining cookies, the HTTP referrer header, and the user agent reported by the browser (or some combination). Spoiler alert: it's the referrer. So! Borrowing the referring URL from the headers (it checks for more than just the domain), we can use &lt;em&gt;curl -e&amp;quot;http://wmata.nextbus.com/googleMap/customGoogleMap.jsp?a=wmata&amp;amp;cssFile=http://www.wmata.com/css/nextbus.css&amp;quot; &amp;quot;http://wmata.nextbus.com/service/googleMapXMLFeed?command=routeConfig&amp;amp;a=wmata&amp;amp;r=64&amp;amp;key=1424073267381&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; and get back &lt;a class="reference external" href="/2009/07/01/routeconfig.xml"&gt;this file&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's got three things in it: stops; routes, which are ordered lists of stops; and paths, which define the shape of the lines that'll be drawn to represent the routes (because roads have twists and turns, connecting stops with straight lines is insufficient).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is pretty much how the GTFS dataset is organized. So you might expect to be able to match up the stops from GTFS to NextBus. Well, here's a stop from NextBus:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&amp;lt;stop &lt;span class="pre"&gt;tag=&amp;quot;5880&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;title=&amp;quot;11th&lt;/span&gt; St Nw + H St Nw&amp;quot; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;dirTag=&amp;quot;null&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;lat=&amp;quot;38.90032&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;lon=&amp;quot;-77.02657&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="pre"&gt;stopId=&amp;quot;1001159&amp;quot;/&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the same stop from a fresh download of the WMATA GTFS dataset:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;7591 / NW 11TH ST &amp;amp; NW H ST / 38.899812 / &lt;span class="pre"&gt;-77.027053&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's a drag. The IDs don't match. The human-readable stop names don't match. &lt;em&gt;Even the latitude and longitude don't match&lt;/em&gt;. I mean, sure, they're close. But making these line up is going to be a sloppy, relatively expensive calculation. Now, true, it probably only has to happen once. It's not that hard of a problem. It's just that it's so &lt;em&gt;unnecessary&lt;/em&gt;. Ah well. I've got an email in to Metro; we'll see if they can provide a cleaner solution than the one I'm thinking about scripting up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UPDATE:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://blog.case.edu/gps10/2006/01/30/debugging_nextbus"&gt;Some thoughts on NextBus's javascript interface from 2006&lt;/a&gt;. A few things have changed since then, but from my initial investigation I'd say that not &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; much is different — just URLs, mostly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An alternative to messing with the protected javascript interface is to scrape the HTML for the &amp;quot;next arrival time&amp;quot; pages. But a) this only gets you distance-expressed-as-time, which is lousy data compared to actual lat/lon coordinates and b) it's still messy, as &amp;quot;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://mihasya.com/blog/?p=203"&gt;apparently NextBus hired a live bear to write their markup&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot; (the author of that post does have his &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://github.com/mihasya/yourmuni/tree/master/"&gt;scraping code up on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;, though).&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="tech"/></entry><entry><title>smuggling data out of Iran</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2009/06/27/smuggling-data-out-of-iran/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-06-27T11:48:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-06-27T11:48:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2009-06-27:/2009/06/27/smuggling-data-out-of-iran/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://attackerman.firedoglake.com/2009/06/26/what-a-week/"&gt;Via Spencer&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://washingtontimes.com/news/2009/jun/26/protesters-use-navy-technology-to-avoid-censorship/?feat=home_headlines&amp;amp;"&gt;an interesting article&lt;/a&gt; about the Iranian protesters' use of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.torproject.org/"&gt;Tor&lt;/a&gt;, The Onion Router. I'm a &lt;a class="reference external" href="/2007/07/24/last-years-model/"&gt;big&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.zunta.org/blog/archives/2005/03/23/said_it_once_be/"&gt;fan&lt;/a&gt; of Tor, and have seen it successfully used to evade dictatorial regimes in the past (specifically the people running &lt;a class="reference external" href="/2008/01/23/nba-league-pass-from-across-many-leagues/"&gt;NBA League Pass&lt;/a&gt;). But it's probably worth pointing out Tor's limits as …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://attackerman.firedoglake.com/2009/06/26/what-a-week/"&gt;Via Spencer&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://washingtontimes.com/news/2009/jun/26/protesters-use-navy-technology-to-avoid-censorship/?feat=home_headlines&amp;amp;"&gt;an interesting article&lt;/a&gt; about the Iranian protesters' use of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.torproject.org/"&gt;Tor&lt;/a&gt;, The Onion Router. I'm a &lt;a class="reference external" href="/2007/07/24/last-years-model/"&gt;big&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.zunta.org/blog/archives/2005/03/23/said_it_once_be/"&gt;fan&lt;/a&gt; of Tor, and have seen it successfully used to evade dictatorial regimes in the past (specifically the people running &lt;a class="reference external" href="/2008/01/23/nba-league-pass-from-across-many-leagues/"&gt;NBA League Pass&lt;/a&gt;). But it's probably worth pointing out Tor's limits as they pertain to the situation in Iran.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, you really can't count on Tor for anonymity or encryption. The right way to do encryption on the internet is for your machine and the server with which it's communicating to agree on a cryptographic arrangement that begins with you and ends with it. If the server isn't expecting to receive encrypted content, it won't know what to make of any such content that it receives — that's kind of the point of encryption, right? So at some point Tor needs to decrypt your traffic and send it out onto the internet in its original, exposed form. Before it does that it passes it back and forth between who-knows-how-many nodes, concealing its point of origin. But hiding your IP address won't do you much good if malevolent actors get their hands on the eventually-decrypted content and it contains your email address, or Twitter login name, or whatever else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And it's not too hard for them to do this. Tor relies on kind-hearted souls to run &amp;quot;exit nodes&amp;quot; — the spots where traffic gets decrypted and sent back into the plain internet. And if you run an exit node, you can easily choose to look at all of the traffic coming through it. In 2007 one clever guy &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.securityfocus.com/news/11486/1"&gt;did just that&lt;/a&gt;, and managed to capture a sensitive information being emailed by embassy staffers. Looking at the Tor &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.torproject.org/docs/tor-doc-relay.html.en"&gt;exit node instructions&lt;/a&gt;, it doesn't look like any node-approval bureaucracy has been added since this incident (nor should there have been, in my opinion). So there's nothing stopping the Iranian government from setting up some exit nodes, grabbing whatever fraction of total Iranian Tor traffic lands in their laps, pulling email addresses and names from it and going after those people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nor is there any reason why Tor can't be blocked. SSL traffic — the most widely used, genuinely secure encryption on the internet (it's what protects your credit card number from snoopers when you buy something from Amazon) — is blocked in Iran. Now, given that Tor is working while SSL isn't, the latter is probably being blocked through the relatively crude measure of turning off traffic on port 443, which is the standard port associated with &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://"&gt;https://&lt;/a&gt; URLs. But with a semi-modern firewall it's possible to block encrypted traffic regardless of the port — I've worked in offices that do this. That would effectively kill SSH, SSL, Tor and any other way of concealing online activities from eavesdropping government agents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Actually, the government could do far worse. They could allow traffic through, but flag encrypted traffic to non-commercial sites for investigation. Or they could set up man in the middle attacks and rely on users to approve the certificate warning they receive. Or they could create redirects that send people to phishing sites that resemble Twitter and capture passwords but seemlessly pass tweets through to the real Twitter and then use the credentials to secretly arrange tweetups and the attendees all &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; they're walking into an underground storefront but then why is it so dark and the doors close and they're in THE BACK OF A TRUCK and it pulls away toward who knows where! OMG! Cut to our hero!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But that would be a lot of trouble. And for all of the conspiracy theories floating around Twitter about Iranian sysops planting hashtags to splinter the online protest's efficacy, the actual shape of Evil Iranian IT probably looks a lot less like the climactic scenes of &lt;em&gt;Neuromancer&lt;/em&gt;. That's not to say that the import of the online part of these protests is nil — I've pretty well been convinced that my initial skepticism was too extreme. But it is to say that we should resist writing any definitive-sounding encomiums about the tools being used to get internet traffic out of Iran. The sad truth is that if the monopoly ISP is run by repressive theocrats with adequate time and resources, aspiring online activists are kind of screwed. To the extent the authorities care, anything that works very well is going to stop working soon enough.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="tech"/></entry><entry><title>you must always be ready to be suddenly transported back to Arthurian times</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2009/06/26/you-must-always-be-ready-to-be-suddenly-transported-back-to-arthurian-times/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-06-26T12:35:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-06-26T12:35:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2009-06-26:/2009/06/26/you-must-always-be-ready-to-be-suddenly-transported-back-to-arthurian-times/</id><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;No joke: I spend kind of a lot of time thinking about how to pull off &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.thomasthwaites.com/thomas/toaster/page2.htm"&gt;stuff like this&lt;/a&gt; (you can see the finished product &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.newscientist.com/gallery/dn15018-pick-of-the-pictures/1"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). Using a microwave to smelt iron is totally cheating, though. As is division of labor, obviously.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="tech"/></entry><entry><title>great ways to watch mediocre television</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2009/06/15/great-ways-to-watch-mediocre-television/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-06-15T20:32:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-06-15T20:32:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2009-06-15:/2009/06/15/great-ways-to-watch-mediocre-television/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sort-of-recommended:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Harper's Island&lt;/em&gt;, a CBS horror miniseries that Emily &lt;strong&gt;EDIT: And I! And I!&lt;/strong&gt; began watching over the weekend. It's not good in the traditional/objective/subjective/plausible sense, but it's not all that bad. It's essentially a conventional horror movie spread over a thirteen episode miniseries. That lets the …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sort-of-recommended:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Harper's Island&lt;/em&gt;, a CBS horror miniseries that Emily &lt;strong&gt;EDIT: And I! And I!&lt;/strong&gt; began watching over the weekend. It's not good in the traditional/objective/subjective/plausible sense, but it's not all that bad. It's essentially a conventional horror movie spread over a thirteen episode miniseries. That lets the action ramp up at a pleasantly leisurely pace, but the long home stretch threatens to buckle under the weight of a series of red herrings and a body count that seems to climb simply because the writers don't know what else to do. But there are four more episodes left, so it's too early to make any definitive judgments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Definitely recommended:&lt;/strong&gt; Netflix's offering of &lt;em&gt;Harper's Island&lt;/em&gt; as a streamable product as the episodes air. This was a little confusing — I couldn't figure out why the number of episodes in the series was growing (has I miscounted?), and last night Emily and I were left worrying that the first season had ended with a particularly irritating cliffhanger. Actually, though, it was just Netflix serving as the on-demand service that that Comcast denies to my Tivo-having self. And they say that a la carte TV service is impossible...&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="tech"/></entry><entry><title>I HAVE OPINIONS ABOUT THE NEW IPHONE!!!!</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2009/06/09/i-have-opinions-about-the-new-iphone/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-06-09T15:35:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-06-09T15:35:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2009-06-09:/2009/06/09/i-have-opinions-about-the-new-iphone/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday Apple announced a shiny new version of its signature mobile device. This prompted considerable acclaim. However, within hours of the announcement, new revelations emerged. It became known that — presumably due to the malign influence of AT&amp;amp;T (a company that, unlike Apple, is capable of wrongdoing) — the new iPhone …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday Apple announced a shiny new version of its signature mobile device. This prompted considerable acclaim. However, within hours of the announcement, new revelations emerged. It became known that — presumably due to the malign influence of AT&amp;amp;T (a company that, unlike Apple, is capable of wrongdoing) — the new iPhone would be sold under a nefarious scheme specifically constructed to line the pockets of those peddling it at a rate brazenly designed to cover the cost of each unit's production — &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.crunchgear.com/2009/06/08/want-an-iphone-3g-s-already-have-an-iphone-3g-be-prepared-to-pay-700-to-upgrade/"&gt;and even more&lt;/a&gt;, if you can believe it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you might imagine, this has prompted considerable outrage, which has in turn spurred real grassroots action. And even if those online petitions and Twitter accounts somehow fail to force AT&amp;amp;T to start buying Americans free electronics, surely the tide will be turned by thoughtful essays like &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.techcrunch.com/2009/06/08/why-the-iphone-3g-s-may-be-a-suckers-bet-right-now/"&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;, in which the author explains why it's vitally important that companies do everything they can to accommodate the customers whose fanaticism renders them price insensitive and/or whose contractual commitment has already been secured.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr class="docutils" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seriously, though: at $99 they're going to sell a staggering number of these things. People are actually just upset about the reality of handset subsidies. Well, good. They should be! There are many things wrong with these subsidies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, they're a particularly opaque form of consumer credit — you only have to read a few examples of the outrage alluded to above to see that most consumers haven't really internalized how they work. That's never a good thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second, underwriting handsets forces carriers to lock down both customers and their phones in order to recoup the subsidy cost. By necessitating long-term contracts, friction is introduced to the market and competition is hindered. By requiring a hardware architecture that supports locking, carriers can more easily cripple phones' functionality. And since carrier locking reduces the reusability and resalability of handsets, more phones are discarded. It's a terrible set of incentives for consumers: every one or two years you're offered a new electronic gadget at (seemingly) below market cost! And if you choose to take it, your old handset's value is next to nothing, thanks to software restrictions imposed upon it. It's a recipe for electronic waste.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Third, the opacity of the finance mechanism at work helps support bad perceptions about the fair price of mobile data service. It's pretty clear that (given the bandwidth caps and speed limitations in place) mobile broadband has an artificially high price*. Admittedly, that's probably mostly because businesses are the main purchasers of mobile broadband, and they're less price sensitive than consumers. But this situation must be at least somewhat informed by consumers' expectation that any given mobile account will cost $50+ per month. The popularity of the subsidy scheme makes it so that for most cutting edge services, a la carte (or even month to month) service isn't an option at all — you have to enter into a contract even if you already own the device. Speaking as someone who has a bunch of devices and a strong desire to have them all constantly connected, this is pretty inconvenient.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But you know whose fault this is? Yours! Or ours, anyway. This country's consumers have pretty clearly signaled their preference for subsidized handsets, and aren't interested in hearing about the inefficiencies that those subsidies produce. I'm not immensely pleased about this collective decision, but that's the way it's going to be for the foreseeable future. The very least we can do is not whine about the inescapable consequences of this system — coming so soon after an economy-wide consumer credit implosion, these demands for free money (or at least a free extension of existing loans) are a bit much to take.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Incidentally, I do think there's some reason for hope — over the long term, anyway. Wireless standards will eventually converge thanks to the efficiencies of the market and the physical limits on radio bandwidth. Once that happens there'll be no reason to buy a new transceiver every year or two. Presumably there'll be a similar leveling off in demand for these devices' other capabilities, as handset manufacturers start to reach the sort of semi-stable compromise between power consumption, processing muscle and cost that microcomputer processor manufacturers have begun to find in the past few years (add display capability and size to that list for mobile devices, of course). I wouldn't expect it to happen for a decade or so, but eventually we'll start treating our handsets more like the watches they've replaced — as potential heirlooms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;* I can purchase daily unlimited GPRS traffic through Boost Mobile for $0.10. That's a very slow service, but of course costs don't scale evenly with the number of bits transferred. If a profitable unlimited data business can be run at that rate — including advertising, accounting overhead, bandwidth costs and infrastructure — then clearly 2.5/3G services (which typically cannot be purchased on a daily or even monthly basis) are being sold at a phenomenal markup.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="tech"/></entry><entry><title>giving up on DD-WRT</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2009/05/11/giving-up-on-dd-wrt/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-05-11T09:26:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-05-11T09:26:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2009-05-11:/2009/05/11/giving-up-on-dd-wrt/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a class="reference external" href="/2009/05/05/artomatic-update-python-on-the-fonera/"&gt;DD-WRT adventures&lt;/a&gt; have come to an end. I spent a long time finding the perfect firmware, cramming Python into it, massaging libraries and... found an immovable roadblock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the thing: in DD-WRT the serial port — which I intend to use for communication between the Arduino and Fonera — is connected …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;My &lt;a class="reference external" href="/2009/05/05/artomatic-update-python-on-the-fonera/"&gt;DD-WRT adventures&lt;/a&gt; have come to an end. I spent a long time finding the perfect firmware, cramming Python into it, massaging libraries and... found an immovable roadblock.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's the thing: in DD-WRT the serial port — which I intend to use for communication between the Arduino and Fonera — is connected to the Linux console. This makes sense: that port is there as an interface of last resort, but it'w only useful if it's actually connected to something like the shell. Unfortunately, a side effect of this is that all incoming communication triggers system commands — regardless of whether it's from an administrator who's just accidentally screwed up his ethernet port or from a microcontroller trying to politely say hello. Worse, the console hogs the serial port, preventing my Python script from reading from it at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This linkage is established when the kernel is invoked. That's not an easy thing to change without recompiling DD-WRT. It &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.dd-wrt.com/phpBB2/viewtopic.php?t=28104&amp;amp;highlight=stty"&gt;can be undone at runtime&lt;/a&gt; using a program called setconsole, but that program isn't compiled into the DD-WRT firmware I have — I'd have to recompile to get it. And if I'm going to recompile things, why not just use &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.openwrt.org"&gt;OpenWRT&lt;/a&gt;? It's smaller, easier to build and more customizable. And while DD-WRT and its community is undoubtedly better for most people trying to simply turn their routers into better routers, OWRT's got more people ready to discuss the esoteric router territory where I've found myself. The order of magnitude difference in the projects' respective IRC channel populations is proof enough of that. Sure, in OWRT exotic network configurations may require a bit more wading through documentation and conf files (as opposed to DD-WRT's pleasantly powerful web interface). But that's a small price to pay if the goddamn thing actually &lt;em&gt;works&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So last night I successfully &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://kamikaze.openwrt.org/docs/openwrt.html#x1-390002"&gt;built&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://wiki.cuwin.net/index.php?title=Flashing_the_La_Fonera_with_OpenWRT"&gt;installed&lt;/a&gt; OpenWRT. I had to do it in a &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://virtualbox.wordpress.com/images/"&gt;VirtualBox Ubuntu image&lt;/a&gt; — building OWRT on OS X is &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://forum.openwrt.org/viewtopic.php?id=318"&gt;possible&lt;/a&gt; but a bit of a pain. Other than that, it went great. I haven't yet put the install through its python-using paces — I found I'd accidentally left a few packages out on my first pass, so after establishing that SSH worked I set it to recompile and went to bed — but every software component I need (python-mini, setconsole, pyserial, stty, etc.) was right there in the menuconfig build system. Clearly &lt;em&gt;somebody&lt;/em&gt; has gotten these things to work in the past — tonight I hope to be next one to accomplish that feat.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="tech"/></entry><entry><title>Artomatic update</title><link href="https://tomlee.wtf/2009/04/28/artomatic-update/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-04-28T14:29:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-04-28T14:29:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:tomlee.wtf,2009-04-28:/2009/04/28/artomatic-update/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I stayed up way too late last night working on my piece for Artomatic. Playing with electronics can frequently be frustrating — everything goes wrong, then keeps going wrong, and at the end of the night you're left with nothing besides a pile of wasted components and a vague worry about …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I stayed up way too late last night working on my piece for Artomatic. Playing with electronics can frequently be frustrating — everything goes wrong, then keeps going wrong, and at the end of the night you're left with nothing besides a pile of wasted components and a vague worry about how much lead you've just ingested. Other times, though, everything seems to go right, and that's how it went last night. There's still much more work to be done, but I'm making definite progress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The piece in question involves a set of &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://images.google.com/images?q=reception%20bell&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;btnG=Search+Images"&gt;reception bells&lt;/a&gt; that can be rung through electronic means, and the manual ringing of which can be similarly detected. The first part is done, in a proof-of-conceptish way — I have 12V solenoids installed that can push the clapper into the bell with satisfying vigor — but isn't completely wired up yet, largely because if you run a solenoid incorrectly it'll, er, melt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other major task is the detection of a manual ring. I initially thought I'd manage this by electrically isolating the clapper from the dome of the bell, then checking for a completed circuit between them. Ah, the naivete of youth. It turns out that this is a lousy way to make a circuit; worse, it's hard to solder wires onto an anodized bell; worse still, it's &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; hard to solder to a bell without changing its tone to something unpleasant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead I decided to detect when the clapper breaks an infrared beam. &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.sparkfun.com/commerce/product_info.php?products_id=241"&gt;These things&lt;/a&gt; seemed promising due to their physically decoupled nature, but there's no filter to prevent visible light from affecting the photodiode. This might've worked fine inside the darkness of the bell, but it made prototyping a pain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.sparkfun.com/commerce/product_info.php?products_id=247"&gt;These&lt;/a&gt; work much better, although the gap between the emitter and detector is juuuust too small to work with the bell's clappers. Bravely ignoring the package's admonishments to avoid breaking open devices made of gallium arsenide, I sawed 'em in half and mounted them with hot glue, and they've been working great ever since.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Incidentally, I don't think I poisoned myself — the GaAs is only used for the actual semiconducting materials, not the mounting armature, and the package allowed me to see that I would only be cutting plastic if I separated the two halves.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are the fruits of my labor: a creepy video of yours truly showing off an LED blinking in time to the dings of the bell. I still have a minor issue to resolve related to one clapper's tendency to bounce (mechanically, not electrically), but I think I can account for that behavior in software.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="center docutils container"&gt;
&lt;embed src="http://blip.tv/play/Af3OIgA" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" width="500" height="400" allowscriptaccess="always" allowfullscreen="true"&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next I'll be prototyping the full bell-strike-detection solution; doing the same for the solenoid; soldering those working circuits onto the breakout/power board; adding active cooling to the case; getting two way serial communication working between the Fonera and Arduino; writing the final software; and then doing the boring, non-electronic stuff: staining, sanding, installation. I've got about a month to get it all done, and right now I'm feeling pretty good about it. But there are certainly still a lot of loose ends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking of which! Anybody got a pair of bar stools or similarly-sized tables that I can borrow for the month of June?&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="tech"/></entry></feed>