<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Tom Lee - tech, Uncategorized</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"/><link href="/feeds/tech-uncategorized.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>/</id><updated>2010-02-23T16:26:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>fly, EAGLE, fly</title><link href="/2010/02/23/fly-eagle-fly/" rel="alternate"/><published>2010-02-23T16:26:00-05:00</published><updated>2010-02-23T16:26:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2010-02-23:/2010/02/23/fly-eagle-fly/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I made my first EAGLE schematic!&amp;nbsp; I'm sure it's horribly broken, but I'm still feeling pretty good about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://assets.sunlightlabs.com/blog/door/schematic.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image1" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1286" src="/static/2010/02/schematic_small-1.png" style="width: 550px; height: 313px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;If you're interested in getting the source file, head over to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://sunlightlabs.com/blog/2010/our-door-opener-science-project/"&gt;the post on Sunlight Labs&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp; And if you do, please be gentle.&amp;nbsp; Advice on what I've gotten wrong would be …&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I made my first EAGLE schematic!&amp;nbsp; I'm sure it's horribly broken, but I'm still feeling pretty good about it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="line-block"&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="http://assets.sunlightlabs.com/blog/door/schematic.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image1" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-1286" src="/static/2010/02/schematic_small-1.png" style="width: 550px; height: 313px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="line"&gt;If you're interested in getting the source file, head over to &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://sunlightlabs.com/blog/2010/our-door-opener-science-project/"&gt;the post on Sunlight Labs&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;nbsp; And if you do, please be gentle.&amp;nbsp; Advice on what I've gotten wrong would be welcome, though.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ALSO:&lt;/strong&gt; Thanks to the diligent outreach efforts of Sunlight's own Nicko Margolies, the original post has now been picked up by &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://hackaday.com/2010/02/23/more-cellphone-controlled-door-locks/#comments"&gt;Hack-a-Day&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://blog.makezine.com/archive/2010/02/android_controlled_door_opening_lin.html"&gt;MAKE&lt;/a&gt;. Neat! And better still, educational: I've already had a number of revisions suggested to me by the Hack-a-Day &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://hackaday.com/2010/02/23/more-cellphone-controlled-door-locks/#comments"&gt;commenters&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ALSO ALSO:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.engadget.com/2010/02/25/linksys-router-turned-into-smartphone-controlled-doorman-video/"&gt;Engadget, too&lt;/a&gt;! Though I've gotta say: &lt;em&gt;man&lt;/em&gt; are the commenters there morons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="%20http://www.engadget.com/2010/02/25/linksys-router-turned-into-smartphone-controlled-doorman-video/comments/25762786/"&gt;&lt;img alt="it'd be so money, bro" class="aligncenter" src="/static/2010/02/23/baller_indeed-20100225-103631.jpg" style="width: 489px; height: 73px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The wages of internet success, I suppose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;AAAAAND:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://gizmodo.com/5480362/the-nerdiest-way-youll-see-a-door-opened-all-week"&gt;Gizmodo&lt;/a&gt;. That'll just about do it, I think. Their commenters are &lt;em&gt;mean&lt;/em&gt;. Which I &lt;em&gt;like&lt;/em&gt;. I want the apparent EE to offer some more information, though.&amp;nbsp; I think he's at least partly wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="tech, Uncategorized"/></entry><entry><title>fear of a black hat</title><link href="/2009/12/07/fear-of-a-black-hat/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-12-07T14:18:00-05:00</published><updated>2009-12-07T14:18:00-05:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2009-12-07:/2009/12/07/fear-of-a-black-hat/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Earlier this week my old boss, JP, sent me a note saying that the full-text RSS script I'd written was being shut down.&amp;nbsp; EchoDitto was nice enough to continue hosting it on their servers, but it had been consuming an increasing share of resources, and finally it needed to be …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Earlier this week my old boss, JP, sent me a note saying that the full-text RSS script I'd written was being shut down.&amp;nbsp; EchoDitto was nice enough to continue hosting it on their servers, but it had been consuming an increasing share of resources, and finally it needed to be killed.&amp;nbsp; Sad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, horrifying.&amp;nbsp; JP had mentioned it idly, but until I saw the Google Alert for &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.blackhatworld.com/blackhat-seo/blackhat-lounge/145882-echodittolabs-down.html"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; I didn't quite realize what had been going on.&amp;nbsp; The self-described black-hat search engine optimization crowd -- the folks who assemble sites peppered with ads that are designed to attract search engine traffic, aka &amp;quot;link farms&amp;quot; -- had been using my script to steal other people's content and republish it on their own sites.&amp;nbsp; Using this sort of genuine content helped them snag traffic more effectively than they could with the gibberish that you sometimes see in spam, so they were sorry to see the script go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, I appreciate the attention, but it's not exactly what I had in mind for my work when I released it.&amp;nbsp; So I explained the situation, and bid them adieu:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="/static/2009/12/blackhat_seo_lg.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="blackhat_seo_lg" class="aligncenter size-medium wp-image-1118" src="/static/2009/12/blackhat_seo_lg-96x300.png" style="width: 96px; height: 300px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was at least somewhat aware of this danger, and consequently didn't open-source the code (thank goodness).&amp;nbsp; It was still a bit of a shock to see the reality of what I'd wrought, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still believe what I wrote in that &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://echodittolabs.org/blog/2007/05/full-text-rss"&gt;initial post&lt;/a&gt;: it's pointless for online publishers to try to control how their readers consume content.&amp;nbsp; If you wish to publish digitally, you need to accept the realities that come with doing so.&amp;nbsp; Pretending otherwise is just going to inconvenience your readers and slow your business's necessary evolution.&amp;nbsp; Prolonging that process seems likely to increase the painfulness of the process, not eliminate it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those curious, the algorithm was exactly what many in comments had guessed.&amp;nbsp; I used some regular expressions to build a hierarchical structure representing all the &amp;lt;div&amp;gt; and &amp;lt;td&amp;gt; elements in each page associated with an RSS item.&amp;nbsp; These tags are the ones most often used to provide a page's layout, and the full text of an entry can usually be found in a single instance of such a container.&amp;nbsp; I then traversed this structure, looking for the text excerpt from the original RSS item.&amp;nbsp; Once found, the rest of that container's contents could be pulled out.&amp;nbsp; It's a simple idea, though the realities of HTML -- and the difficulty of preserving byte offsets between a sanitized working copy and the original -- made the actual implementation require quite a bit more cleverness (and caching) than it may sound like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result worked pretty well. Still, there were a few problems with the approach.&amp;nbsp; For one thing, comments were frequently included in the same container as the main entry.&amp;nbsp; For another, the script would fail if the RSS entry text was a summary of the item rather than an excerpt. I think that both of these are surmountable problems: a better approach would examine the &amp;quot;textiness&amp;quot; of each container using a variety of scoring metrics.&amp;nbsp; Something similar could be used for detecting the start of comments (which tend to be peppered with timestamps, quotations of the original text, and occur after a big &amp;lt;h[1-6]&amp;gt; containing the word &amp;quot;comment&amp;quot;).&amp;nbsp; I took a stab at a new, Pythonic implementation using Adrian Holovaty's &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://www.holovaty.com/writing/templatemaker/"&gt;templatemaker&lt;/a&gt; and a few other tools, but a lack of immediate success (and much higher computational demands than the original script) made the project fall by the wayside.&amp;nbsp; Now that I know how it might be used, I'm even less likely to pick it back up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I'd still love to see my algorithm adapted by the people who make RSS readers, and would be happy to talk to any interested and qualified parties about making that happen.&amp;nbsp; Those SEO morons don't appear to be particularly technically proficient -- I'm not too worried about them managing to steal content via a client-side app (though certainly some thought should be given to the matter before giving the store away, say via Applescript).&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="tech, Uncategorized"/></entry><entry><title>making it easier to move from the browser to the iPhone</title><link href="/2009/07/24/browser-to-iphone/" rel="alternate"/><published>2009-07-24T11:32:00-04:00</published><updated>2009-07-24T11:32:00-04:00</updated><author><name>admin</name></author><id>tag:None,2009-07-24:/2009/07/24/browser-to-iphone/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Although it is arguably as much a business innovation as a technological one, there's no doubt that the iPhone has radically altered the mobile device landscape, and, in the process, profoundly changed the way that Americans think about sitting on the toilet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, its uses extend beyond this crass …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Although it is arguably as much a business innovation as a technological one, there's no doubt that the iPhone has radically altered the mobile device landscape, and, in the process, profoundly changed the way that Americans think about sitting on the toilet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, its uses extend beyond this crass but foremost example.&amp;nbsp; You've also got your standing-in-line downtime, the crucial waiting-for-coffee-to-brew period, and of course miscellaneous hours spent idly fiddling while in meetings. If I'm not mistaken, the Bureau of Labor Statistics is on record as saying that high scores from Sudoku games played on mobile devices account for most of the productivity gains of the past decade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Personally, I like to use the device to catch up on my online reading.&amp;nbsp; But this crucial electronic-fucking-around is slowed by the need to enter URLs.&amp;nbsp; If you're like me, typically you'll have some long-form article open in a neglected browser tab: say, 2000 words from Sasha Frere-Jones on why your implicit acceptance of the latest top 40 hit means you're more -- and less! -- racist than you thought.&amp;nbsp; It's something I mean to read, but which the demands of the workday have made me put off.&amp;nbsp; As I leave my desk to pursue less productive activities (food acquisition; interaction with humans), I frequently find myself wishing I had that article loaded on my handset.&amp;nbsp; But the only way to move it there without tedious typing is to email myself the link, then check my email, then click on the link.&amp;nbsp; If only there was an almost perfectly equivalent but slightly faster way!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, you're/I'm in luck!&amp;nbsp; I twittered this ridiculous first-world complaint the other day, and &amp;#64;tbridge and &amp;#64;jroo helpfully pointed me toward &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://prowl.weks.net/"&gt;Prowl&lt;/a&gt;, a $2.99 iPhone app that takes the 3.0 firmware's push notification capabilities and wraps them in a simple API.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This opens the door to creating a bookmarklet that grabs your browser's current URL and pushes it to your phone.&amp;nbsp; The phone will buzz, you'll click the &amp;quot;view&amp;quot; button, and you can then follow the link.&amp;nbsp; Easy!&amp;nbsp; Here's the bookmarklet.&amp;nbsp; Just follow these steps (which, I should note, have only been tested in Firefox 3.5):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Buy Prowl.&amp;nbsp; Open it on your iPhone -- you'll need to register with its parent site and give the app permission to display notifications.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Using your newly-created credentials, log into the Prowl site. Go to the settings tab and create an API key by clicking the appropriate button.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Paste the API key into the form field below. Click the &amp;quot;Create Bookmarklet&amp;quot; button. NOTE: the customization of the bookmarklet is done in client-side Javascript, entirely within your browser -- don't worry, you won't be sending me your API key.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Drag the newly-created button into your browser's quicklaunch bar.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simple!&amp;nbsp; Now when you click that bookmarklet a new window will be briefly opened.&amp;nbsp; It'll submit a request to the Prowl site that contains the current URL that you're looking at.&amp;nbsp; Shortly thereafter you should get a message on your phone with the link.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="docutils container"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class="docutils container" id="bkmklt"&gt;
&lt;a class="reference external image-reference" href="javascript:f=function()%7Bvar%20w=window.open(%22%22,%22wildebeast%22,%22width=30,height=30,scrollbars=0,resizable=1%22);var%20url=window.location.href;var%20html%20=%20%27%3Chtml%3E%3Chead%3E%3C/head%3E%3Cbody%3E%3Cform%20action=%22https://prowl.weks.net/publicapi/add%22%20method=%22POST%22%3E%3Cinput%20type=%22hidden%22%20name=%22apikey%22%20value=%22__APIKEY__%22%20/%3E%3Cinput%20type=%22hidden%22%20name=%22priority%22%20value=%220%22%20/%3E%3Cinput%20type=%22hidden%22%20name=%22application%22%20value=%22CTU%22%20/%3E%3Cinput%20type=%22hidden%22%20name=%22event%22%20value=%22Chloe%20says:%22%20/%3E%3Cinput%20type=%22hidden%22%20name=%22description%22%20value=%22%27%20+%20url%20+%20%27%22%20/%3E%3C/form%3E%3Cscript%20type=%22text/javascript%22%3Edocument.forms%5B0%5D.submit();%3C/script%3E%3C/body%3E%3C/html%3E%27;w.document.open();w.document.write(html);w.document.close();window.setTimeout(function()%7B%20w.close();%20return%20false;%7D,%20500);%7D;f();"&gt;&lt;img alt="Send it to my screen!" src="/static/2009/07/sendittomyscreen.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type="text/javascript"&gt;// &lt;![CDATA[&lt;br /&gt;
jQuery(function(){&lt;br /&gt;
   jQuery('#createbkmklt').click(function(){&lt;br /&gt;
      jQuery('a#bkmklt-link').attr('href', jQuery('a#bkmklt-link').attr('href').replace('__APIKEY__', jQuery('#apikey').val()));&lt;br /&gt;
      jQuery('a#bkmklt-link img').show();&lt;br /&gt;
   });&lt;br /&gt;
});&lt;br /&gt;
// ]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;As for the new window: I admit, it's inelegant to spawn a popup.&amp;nbsp; But the Prowl API only accepts POSTed requests, which, barring a sudden and deeply unwise decision on their part to host third-party scripts, rules out a more seamless AJAX solution.&amp;nbsp; The popup works well enough, although on especially slow connections the window may wind up closed before the request goes through.&amp;nbsp; A better solution would involve a timer that checks the spawned window for when its location.href property suddenly becomes inaccessible due to cross-domain security policies (indicating that the page it contains is now being served by the Prowl domain).&amp;nbsp; But my first crack at that didn't work, so for now you guys are stuck with this.&lt;/p&gt;
</content><category term="tech, Uncategorized"/></entry></feed>